''Slake the thirst that
lies deep in my soul''
''Beloved, make my love complete...''
''so it may last
beyond eternity"
There is a millionaire
in the car. Come with me.
No! go away!
You won't?
l've already promised him!
Let me go!
You won't obey me?
Get going!
And thank your lucky stars
l used my weak hand.
Be seated.
This is my territory and
if anyone disturbs you...
...just call for me,
l'll come running.
Where are you?
What did you say?
- l didn't say a word.
She's lost, isn't she?
Who is he?
- Who?
l wouldn't ask if l knew,
would l?
Just a postman knows the
meaning of postcard, so l...
a masseur, can tell things
at a glance...
Sitting here looking lost,
not noticing me.
Not hearing a word,
that's a sure sign.
l see you've fallen in love.
Rushing off is a sign, too.
Tell me truly who he is.
A poet.
- l have a poet friend.
What's your poet's name?
Vijay.
- So is mine.
l'll ask him if he
knows another Vijay-poet.
Maybe they're the same person.
Possibly, l'll ask him
Brothers, is all well?
What are you doing?
What's it you if someone
is dead, you vagabond?
Who is dead?
Whose last rites are these?
- Mother's.
Don't call us brother.
We share our relationship
because of her.
And now that she is dead,
you are dead for us.
''Where will you go
on the empty stomach''
''Who will look after you''
''l don't want to stay in this
house for another minute''
Let's see you dance.
l'll play the drums for you.
Ask your friend to join us.
Come on, drink it!
l'd drink poison for her
is she told me to.
He's shy!
Come, sir,
have a drink for my sake.
Strange chap!
Are you a man or a mouse?
You look as if your grandma died.
He's a beginner,
but he's finished it!
You can't be a real beginner!
When did you start?
''l was so overcome
with sorrow"
''l drank to drown
the grief"
''My poor heart was so dejected''
''l drank out of pity for it''
So he's a poet, too?
lndeed! He's composed
hundreds of poems.
''For so many years
the world...''
''has rejected and dismissed me''
''Today l...''
''... reject the world''
''And l think...''
''... to forget that it exists''
Where to?
My child is ill.
l need you, too.
Tend to us first.
Tend to us first,
then see to your child.
Start the music.
''These lanes, these houses,
where pleasure is auctioned''
''These ravaged caravans of
life that pass us by"
''Where are they,
the guardians of dignity?''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''These insidious streets,
where infamy is traded''
''Where men conceal their
names, where money talks''
''Where chastity is bargained for
and purity is sold''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''These old streets
where dreams wither...''
''where flowers are
trampled underfoot''
''These sham celebrations
of colour are for sale''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''These brightly lit rooms
where dancing bells chime''
''The tables beat in time
with heavy hearts''
''These soulless rooms
that echo to coughing''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''These garlands, these walls...''
''... stained with blood''
''These fragile bodies,
these vain faces''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''Old men pass through here,
young man too stop awhile''
''Sons, respected fathers
and husbands''
''These are our wives,
our sisters, our mothers''
''Where are those who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''These daughters
of Eve seek help''
of Radha and Yashoda''
''These daughters of Zulekha,
these children of God''
''Where are the leaders who claim
to be proud of this land?''
''Summon all the leaders
of this land''
''Show them the treachery,
show them these devious streets''
''Summon all those who claim
to be proud of this land''
Who is it? lt's you.
Come with me.
Taking a pity of me again?
Today l am not hungry.
l have drowned
my hunger in drink.
l have drunk
...all my joys and sorrows.
l have swallowed everything.
Where to?
Come and rest in my house.
Leave when you feel better.
Should l leave
when l feel better?
l'll feel better when
l've left this world, Gulabo.
Everything is lost.
My job. And my mother
has left me forever.
What am l doing here?
Why am l alive, Gulabo?
Don't talk like that.
The world needs you
and your poetry.
The world needs nobody.
l tried my best to make
my poetry reach the world.
But you know how
the world valued it?
Waste paper sold for ten annas.
My life is valued at
ten annas, Gulabo.
Do you want me to live
for ten annas?
Don't lose courage,
there's much to live for.
There's Meena.
How do you know her?
l read her name on your file.
Who is she?
She is chaste and
virtuous society girl...
...who loves for fun
and amusement...
...and sells that love
for comfort.
But why take
such an interest in her?
Because you did.
That's why.
You mean you...
No, forget me.
l can only make you suffer.
l've never been able
to make anyone happy.
You'll publish them?
- What for?
Am l mad?
Call that gibberish poetry?
The world needs you...
You must know we publish famous
poets, not the trash of novices.
Could you bear my burden...
...when you couldn't
feed yourself?
lt wasn't our wish that...
...our parents produce
such a good-for-nothing.
Have you read about the poet?
l knew him well.
Why did he commit suicide?
''Tragic death of young poet''
''Last night a young man jumped
in front of the Burdwan train''
''His body was mutilated
beyond recognition''
''A letter in his pocket...''
''...contained his last poem,
his last message to world''
''His name was... Vijay"
Are you all right?
What is it?
SHADOWS
Send her in.
Who are you?
Where from?
- Sona...from Dharmtallah.
Give me the poems.
lf you know they are poems,
you'll know they are beautiful.
l want them published.
So you're going to show them
to my husband.
What's your price?
- You'll publish them?
May l will, may be not.
Name your price!
Price?
l haven't come to bargain.
l want them published.
Are these poems precious
to you?
How did you know Vijay?
By good fortune.
- Your relationship?
Relationship?
How could such a gentleman
meet a lady of your background?
Good fortune.
You sell much for money.
Why not sell these poems?
Are you Meena?
My husband will be here
any moment.
Sell me the poems before he comes.
l'll pay 1,000 rupees...2000.
- Not even 30,000.
What's that? Show me.
''For Meena...''
''...whose memory
has inspired every word''
l brought them
to have them published.
What is that?
- lt's all l own in the world.
l can't pay you more
for their publication.
They must be published.
l'll be eternally
grateful to you.
A fine bookseller you are!
We want Vijay's book.
How can it be sold out so soon?
ls it ''under the counter''?
Have the third edition tomorrow.
Or we'll burn the shop.
lf only you were alive
to see this.
Have you established his identity?
No, he hasn't said one word
since he was admitted.
How are you?
Let me know if he speaks at all.
l can't pay more than
5,000 for them.
They've his poems
but too high a price.
Do you want to cream of all the
profit and leave me with nothing?
Then name a sensible price politely.
Sir, these poems are priceless.
Vijay's last, unique works.
l'll share fifty-fifty.
l can't pay that much.
- Nice to have met you.
You're strange.
Twenty five per cent.
My last offer.
Now you may leave.
l wouldn't like you to
think l'm unreasonable.
Here, let's shake on it.
''l recollect the past''
''l adorn your hair with flowers''
''What is this secret
which chokes me...''
''which parches my lips?''
''l recollect the past''
''Shadows''
These are my poems, all mine.
This is my book.
Of course.
But what is your name?
My name is Vijay. This book
was written by me.
The Vijay who wrote
this book is dead.
Think carefully,
what is your real name?
Why don't you believe me?
l tell you my name is Vijay.
Why have you kept me here?
Let me go!
l think he has lost his mind.
Telephone Doctor Sen.
So you are Vijay's brothers?
His elder brothers.
- l'm the eldest.
What do you want?
Shall l tell him?
- No, you go ahead.
l asked you what you want.
Well, l brought up Vijay
and educated him...
...and cared for him so that
he would be someone one day.
So did l.
- l have no time. Get to the point.
The point is, we've come for
some money from you.
Are you sane?
We are the rightful heirs
to his property.
lncluding poems.
We have a legal right to the
money you gain from his works.
We don't want it all,
we'll be content with some.
l don't know you and l didn't
get the poems from you.
You won't get a penny.
Understand?
lt isn't Vijay.
Shyam!
No, he's not Vijay.
So you want a share?
The rightful claimant is Vijay.
He's alive.
Yes, he's alive.
No! You must be joking.
l never joke.
However, you will get
a share of the profit.
Two percent...
...on condition that...
...you refuse to identify Vijay.
Why shouldn't we identify
our brother?
What are we?
- Do you consider us so low?
For a mere two per cent?
- Make it 6°/.
Massage! Oil Massage!
A ghost!
Lord, please make it vanish.
Let go off poor Sattar!
lt's me, Vijay.
So you aren't dead.
He's really alive.
l've been forcibly detained.
Get me out.
What is it?
l'll massage your head
only if you agree.
''lf your head reels with pain,
or your heart sinks in gloom''
Brother.
Don't you recognize me?
l'm your brother Vijay.
Why so quiet?
Won't you recognize me, either?
Are you mad?
Vijay's dead.
You've the nerve
to call yourself our brother.
Get out of here! Our brother!
Going to the meeting for
Vijay's death anniversary?
Of course.
Vijay was a friend of mine.
Did you really know Vijay?
Move aside, let me pass.
He was fine poet.
A noble man.
lf it wasn't for my help...
...he would have died
6 months earlier.
How?
- Of starvation.
Hurry, we won't get a seat.
You all know...
...we are gathered
in memory of Vijay.
On this day last year...
...a terrible event took
the great poem from us.
lf l could have saved Vijay,
l would have given my fortune...
...and my life.
lt could not be.
Why? Because of you all.
lt is said
he committed suicide...
But in fact you killed him.
lf Vijay were alive
he would see...
the world which...
...starved him is ready
to shower wealth on him.
The world in which...
...he died unknown,
would treat him as a king.
Today this world
would give him a palace.
''This world of palaces, of kingdoms,
this world of power''
''The enemies of humanity,
this world of rituals''
''These men who crave wealth,
as their way of life''
''For what will it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
''People with parched souls,
with wounded spirits''
''With troubled gaze and sad hearts''
''This world which is distraught,
and full of trouble''
''For what shall it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
''The world where life
is considered trivial''
''A world where the dead
are worshipped''
''A world where death
is cheaper than life''
''For what shall it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
''A world where youth
is driven to crime''
''A world where the young are
groomed for the market-place''
''A world where love is another name
for trade''
''For what shall it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
''A world where man is worth nothing''
''A world where loyalty and friendship
mean nothing''
''A world where love is
regarded with disdain''
''For what shall it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
''Burn this world, blow it asunder''
''Take this world away
from my sight''
''This world belongs to you,
you keep it''
''For what shall it profit a man
if he gain the world?''
Stop his brothers,
give whatever they want.
They mustn't identify him.
Sorry, all your resources
cannot stop...
...Vijay being identified now.
Can you bribe everyone now?
Buy everyone,
l'll spend all l have...
l don't want it proved
he's Vijay.
Or we'll lose our name,
we'll be finished.
Save yourself. l know how
to save my own neck.
What!
You think you'll do it so easily?
You denied him, too!
l sway with the wind.
l followed you when it was in my
interest. Now l'll ally with Vijay.
You're looking happy.
Why not? l have my hands on
the king of fame.
l've got Vijay; l'll earn
millions by publishing his poems.
Bravo! Excellent!
lt's a goldmine.
Do you think
you'll mine it alone?
You'll share it with me.
What are you gaping at?
Get out!
You are very insolent, young man.
Who are you?
- Never mind.
But l can identify Vijay
if l so choose...
...and if l don't, he'll
be shut away as a lunatic.
Are you the head of state,
to lock someone away?
His brothers know him.
We'll identify him.
- Of course.
He may not care about us.
- We may not profit.
After all he is our blood.
- Why shouldn't we identify him?
Well said!
Brothers are Brothers!
l spent 5,000 on his education.
4,000 on feeding.
lf we'd loaned it,
we'd have 15,000 now.
Will you pay to identify him?
15,000?
- Yes, 15,000.
But you have your precious
brother back.
What more could you want?
We don't want a brother,
we want money.
We can't eat him.
Vijay, my brother!
ls he really Vijay?
Where's the proof?
Sit down! Soon you'll say
that l'm not Sattar.
How can we know that
he is Vijay?
What about the suicide?
We prove it.
The neighbourhood knows,
Vijay is our brother.
We say he is Vijay.
And l confirm that he's my
boyhood friend.
The great poet Vijay.
The Vijay you wish
to welcome so warmly...
...the Vijay for whom
you shout slogans...
...l am not that Vijay.
l'm not Vijay.
- Why deceive us?
l said he was an imposter.
A publicity-seeker. Hit him!
''Burn it! Blow it asunder''
''Burn it...''
''blow the world asunder''
''Take this world away
from my sight''
''The world belongs to you,
you keep it''
Are you mad?
What did you do?
Tell these people you're Vijay,
there is still time.
What's wrong?
They're all here for you.
Why not tell them?
l am not that Vijay.
He is dead.
- What are you saying?
All your friends say that you
are Vijay. Come to your senses.
Friends?
They are not my friends.
They're friends of wealth.
Once they refused to identify me.
But now...
Why turn against yourself
because of false friends?
Why refuse fame and fortune...
...when you can
repudiate those people?
l have no complaint against
them or any human being.
But against a society that...
...denies the right to be human.
That makes a brother
a stranger, a friend an enemy.
l complain against a world
that worships no humans.
But worships idols.
That destroy humans
and tramples them.
Where it is a crime to
share the sorrows of the poor.
Where it is cowardice
to face troubles.
ln such a world l shall never
be at peace, Meena.
No peace, ever.
That is why l am going away,
far away.
Did someone call me?
No one called. Sleep.
Gulabo, where are going?
You're feverish.
Someone called me.
Let me go.
l am going far away, Gulabo.
Where?
Where l won't need to go any further.
ls that what you came to say?
Will you come?