Made by CVStudio v.1.0.2.1
[][][25][][]
Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Gloria Patri et Filii
et Spiritu Sancto,
sicut erat in principio nunc et
semper in secula saeculorum. Amen.
The second mystery consists in
Jesus' flagellation by the pillar.
Pater noster qui es in coelis
sanctificatur nomen tuum,
adveniat regnum tuum, fiat voluntas
tua sicut in coela et in terra,
panem nostrum quotidianum da nobis
hodie, dimitte nobis debita nostra
sicut nos dimittimus
debitorum nostris
et ne nos inducat in tentationem
sed libera nos a malo. Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Where are you going ?
You can't go ! Come back !
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus ventris
tui Jesus.
Sancta Maria, Mater Dei,
ora pro nobis peccatoribus,
nunc et in hora mortis nostrae.
Amen.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus
tecum, benedicta tu in mulieribus,
et benedictus fructus...
What's all this fuss about ?
- What happened ? Speak up !
- Excellency, please, forgive us...
but they found
a dead soldier in the garden.
What ?
Terrible riots are taking place
all over the country.
They brought this letter
from the Duke of Malvica.
He says it's a very urgent matter.
''Dear Fabrizio, read the horrible
news on the newspaper.
The Piedmontese have landed,
we're lost.
Tonight, my whole family and I
will take shelter
on the English ships at anchor.
I'm sure you'll do the same.
God save our beloved King.
I hug you.'' What a coward !
''An act of piracy was committed
on the 1 1th of May
after the landing
of armed people in Marsala.
It has subsequently been discovered
that it was the 800 men
driven by Garibaldi.
The bandits were able to avoid a
confrontation with the royal troops
by heading to Castelvetrano, where
they harmed the peaceful citizens
- ..with robberies and
devastations.'' - Garibaldi !
Paolo, you must move
to the Palermo palace.
- If we leave a house empty,
we'll lose it. - No, please !
Fabrizio, it's too dangerous !
Fabrizio, don't ! Don't !
We're at war !
- Francesco Paolo, call Mimì.
- Yes, father.
Mimì ! Mimì !
This is a revolution !
Mon Dieu ! C'est sa crise !
Oh, Madame !
Les gouttes !
I'm suffocating !
Concetta, dépêche toi ! Vite !
Voilà, Madame, voilà.
Buvez ça et ça ira mieux.
Mimì ! Domenico !
Mimì !
- Mimì's coming, dad.
- Dad ! - Mimì ! - Dad !
- Your Excellency, forgive me,
but we found a dead... - I know !
Mimì, go tell Don Antonio to hitch
the bays to the coupé. Go, go !
- I'll head to Palermo right
after dinner. - Yes, Excellency.
- Father Pirrone.
- Yes ?
- You'll go with me.
- Me ? - Right.
God protect us.
Fabrizio !
The streets are full of soldiers !
Stella, calm down.
You'll spend two hours with your
friends at Casa Professa.
- We'll be back by eleven.
- Fine, Excellency.
We're gonna have lunch
in half an hour.
All of us !
- What shall we do ? - Salve
Regina, Mater misericordiae,
vita, dulcedo et spes nostra,
salve.
A te clamamos exule filii Hevae,
a te suspiramus gementes et flentes
in hac lacrimarum valle.
Eja ergo advocata nostra,
illos tuos misericordiae oculos
ad nos convertes.
Et Jesus benedictum fructus ventris
tui, nobis hoc exilium ostende.
O clemens, o pia,
o dulcis Virgo Maria.
The stench of these swines doesn't
stop even when they're dead.
- Salvatore, did you inform
the barracks ? - Yes sir.
Excellency, we've already told
the barracks to come and get him.
Awful times, Excellency,
awful times.
Excellency, look at the fires
on the mountains !
- They're the rebels' camps.
- I can see them myself, Father.
ls Your Excellency by any chance
worried about Don Tancredi ?
Don Tancredi should avoid
bad and dangerous company.
- It is not Tancredi's fault !
It's the times' ! - Yes, I agree.
Nowadays,
a young man of good family
can't even play cards without
running into dangerous people.
- Yes, I understand, Excellency.
- Stop it, then.
- Even though, a little bit
of caution... - Oh, come on !
Stop !
Sergeant ! Sergeant !
Checkpoint of Villa Airoldi !
- Good evening, Excellency. - Good
evening. - I'm sorry, Excellency.
Let them pass. It is His Excellency
the Prince Salina.
- Good-bye, Excellence.
- Good-bye.
Let them pass !
This country would be wonderful,
Excellency, if...
If there were not so many Jesuits !
I'll come and pick you up in two
hours. And... enjoy your prayers.
Let's go !
- Where could we go ?
- At the inn by the harbor. - Yes.
Good evening, handsome sir !
- Melina, he's not for you. - Leave
me alone, mind your own business.
My dear Prince !
- Hello, Uncle.
- Tancredi !
- What were you up to,
last night, huh ? - Last night ?
Absolutely nothing, Uncle !
I was with friends.
It was a caste night.
Whereas I know about people
who were having fun in Palermo.
- Like whom ?
- Well, yourself, Uncle.
I saw you with my own eyes
at Villa Airoldi
talking to the Sergeant
by the checkpoint.
You're too old for that !
Plus, with a Reverend Father !
- Oh, the libertine remainings !
- Well, it's true, after all.
Mimì ?
Why are you dressed like that ?
What's going on ?
- A morning costume ball ?
- I'm leaving in an hour.
- I'm here to say good-bye.
- Why ?
Where are you going ?
It's not a duel, is it ?
Yes, a big one: a duel with the
King, with ''Franceschiello''.
I'm going to the mountains,
up to Ficuzza.
Something great is going to happen,
and I don't want to stay at home.
- Even if I did, they'd get me
right away ! - Are you crazy ?
Those people are mafia men !
They're all crooks !
- A Falconeri ought to stay with
us, on the King's side ! - Sure !
What king, though ? You've
said it yourself so many times:
''If only King Ferdinando
was still alive !''.
But Franceschiello...
No, dear uncle, no way.
Do you think that the so-called
''Gentleman'' will be better ?
He'll speak Turin dialect instead
of Neapolitan ! That's it !
What about
Don Peppino Mazzini's Republic ?
Believe me, Uncle,
if it weren't for us,
they'd set up a republic
in no time.
For everything to remain the same,
everything must change !
Did I make myself clear ?
I'll see you soon, Uncle.
I'll be back with the Tricolor !
The Tricolor !
You all fill your mouth up
with this word !
What is it compared to our
white banner with the golden lily ?
- What good will
a clash of colors do ? - Wait.
- And you'll see I'm right.
- You're a dreamer !
Good-bye, Uncle.
Good-bye.
See you soon !
- Bye, Rosalia, see you soon.
- Au revoir, Tancredi.
- Carolina.
- Good-bye.
- Bye !
- Bye.
Good-bye.
- Good-bye ! - Good-bye !
- Au revoir, Tancredi ! - Bye !
Tancredi.
Wait.
Uncle...
What are you doing ? You won't
support the revolution, will you ?
Thank you so much, Uncle.
See you soon !
Give my aunt a hug for me !
Tancredi !
Concetta, don't.
I'll be back soon.
Bye.
Bye, Concettina, see you soon.
Let's go.
- Good morning, Excellency.
- Good morning, Father.
- ls Your Excellency here
to confess ? - It's not Saturday.
Excellency, you should
listen to me and confess.
You see, Father, there's no need,
you already know everything.
- Confession isn't simply
telling our sins. - I know...
- It consists in repenting
for them. - I know !
What do you want from me ?
I'm a vigorous man.
I can't be content with a woman who
crosses herself before hugging me !
And who, afterwards,
can only say ''Jesus and Mary'' !
I had seven kids with her.
You know what ?
I never saw her navel !
It this fair ? I'm asking you,
Father, is it fair ?
She is the sinner.
Excellency...
I'm afraid I was too brusque.
Please, forgive me.
But do listen to me:
come to confession !
It doesn't even cross my mind !
Not today, at least.
I made a few important
political discoveries.
Do you know what's going on
in our country ? Nothing at all.
Just an imperceptible
change in ranks.
The middle-classes
don't want to destroy us,
they just want to take our place,
kindly, though,
maybe slipping a few thousand
ducats in our pockets.
And then, everything
will be the same as ever.
You see, Father, we live
in the country of arrangements.
ln a few words, sir, you plan on
coming to terms with the Liberals.
Even, with the Masons.
At our expense,
at the expense of the Church.
It is obvious that all our riches,
that actually belong to the poor,
will be grabbed by and split among
the most impudent ringleaders.
What will become of those destitute
the Church feeds and guides ?
How will those desperate
be pacified ? I'll tell you.
We'll give them all your lands,
bit by bit !
Our Lord healed the blind in body,
but what will become
of the blind in spirit ?
We're not blind in spirit,
dear Father.
We're just human beings living
in a world that's changing.
What are we supposed to do ?
The Church was explicitly
promised immortality.
As a social class,
we were promised nothing.
To us, eternity adds up
to a hundred years !
We have no obligation beyond
what we can see with our own eyes.
The Church does,
because it is bound to last.
- Comfort is implicit in its
desperation. - Excellency !
Do you think, Father, that if
one day the Church had the chance
to save itself sacrificing us,
it would hesitate ?
It wouldn't, but that's fair.
You'll have two sins to confess,
on Saturday, Excellency:
last night's carnal sin,
and today's spiritual. Remember.
Look at this beauty, Father.
It'll take more than Vittorio
Emanuele to deprive us
of the magic potion
we daily get to drink.
Let him go !
Come on, hurry, quick !
Come on !
Aim ! Fire !
Go away, you traitors !
You rogues ! Go away !
- Get him ! Get him !
- Traitor ! - Stop him !
Here he is !
- Let me go ! I'm innocent !
No ! No ! - Traitor !
- Let's hang him !
I'm innocent !
Let me go !
- Murderer !
- Help ! Let me go !
- Let's hang him !
- Coward !
Let's go !
All clear, go !
Keep to the wall !
Follow me !
- Come ! Come !
- That way ! That way !
- Save us ! Save us !
- The Garibaldians are here !
- Help me !
- Here ! Come here !
He's a murderer ! Let's take
the law into our own hands !
- He's a coward !
- Careful !
Come on, follow me !
- The cavalry !
- Don't fire, not yet ! Wait !
Fire !
Let's go !
First platoon, forward, march !
- Second platoon, forward, march !
- Everybody stay down !
Aim ! Fire !
- Bring some water ! Quick !
- A doctor ! Call a doctor !
- Hey, you, come here !
- What do you want ?
- What's going on ?
- They've gone !
- They must have reached the
harbor, by now ! - Let's go ! Go !
Jesus and Mary help us !
What do you reckon, Father ?
Will these glorious new times
bring better summers ?
Well... no...
The Government...
Hey ! Get out of the way !
Move it !
- Stop ! No one can pass !
- Move it !
- Stop ! - Why ? - The streets
are closed. - We have a pass.
No use,
the street to Bisaquino is closed !
- Halt ! Stop the carriages !
- Stop ! - Halt !
- I'm sorry, no one can go through.
- Stop them, they can't go through.
Let me see the pass, please.
- It seems our pass is not valid.
- That's not what I said.
We were told that all the passes
are to be considered suspended.
Do you think we're having fun ?
If I tell you to go back,
it means you have to go back.
Clear the way,
let the carriages go through !
Halt ! Stop !
Where do you think you're going ?
No way, nobody can go through !
I am Captain Falconeri,
I fought in Palermo on your side !
- I received an order, what should
I do ? - Mine is an order as well !
- Clear the way !
- Yes sir, fine, we will !
Come on, move aside, move,
clear the way.
Careful, move, move !
Come on !
Come on, come on !
Since you live amongst
the nobility, tell us:
what do the lords say
about this war ?
What does the Prince Salina
think, as proud as he is ?
You see, the lords, as you call
them, are not easily understood.
They live in their own universe,
which was not created by God,
but by themselves,
through centuries
of painful
and joyful experiences.
They rejoice or suffer for things
that mean nothing to us,
but that are vital to them.
I don't mean to say that the lords
are bad, on the contrary.
They are just... different.
They don't care about things
that are very important to us,
but they are afraid
of things we ignore.
Take the Prince Salina,
for example.
He couldn't possibly bear
to loose his house in Donnafugata,
where we're now going.
But... if you ask him what
he thinks about the revolution,
he'll say there was
no revolution at all,
- ..that everything will be the
same as ever. - I hope not !
Right...
We'd better read the breviary.
Let's see... Psalm 44.
''Effundit cor meum
verbum bonum dico ego
carmen meum regi, lingua mea stilus
et scribae velocis.
Speciosus est forma prae filiis
hominum, diffusa est gratia
super labia tua: propterea
benedixit tibi Deus in aeternum.
Cinge gladium tuum
super fenur potentissime,
decorum tuum et ornatum tuum.
Come on, hurry up.
Quick !
Lay it out well, come on ! You get
the bottles, and you the glasses !
Let's hurry, come on !
Quick, they're coming !
Whatever you command,
and let's hope for the best !
I'm so glad to see you again,
Excellency.
- Now we'll rest a little.
- Sure.
- You'll sit under those trees.
- We'll soon head to Donnafugata.
- Did the soldiers pass by ?
- They sure did.
- Did they cause any damage ?
- Yes...
- C'est pire qu'en Algerie ! - This
certainly isn't Algeria, my dear !
- It feels so good ! Do you want to
refresh a little ? - Yes. - Here.
Put it on your temples
and forehead.
It's so cool !
It feels really good !
- You feel better, huh ?
- Oh, yes !
Let's join the others,
the food will soon be gone !
May I have it back ?
Come on, let's go.
You're hungry, huh ?
- Father Pirrone, this is for you.
- The meat is excellent !
Everybody said: ''His Excellency
won't be able to leave Palermo.
It can't be expected that
he'll travel in times like these.
Who knows what happened
to His Excellency and his family !''
But they're all safe.
Thank God !
Of course we are ! What did you
expect would happen to us ?
Everything went just fine.
ln fact, a few days after
Garibaldi's arrival to Palermo,
Tancredi had brought home
a nice Tuscan General
who wished to admire
the villa's frescoes.
He was very helpful in providing
the passes to Donnafugata.
My family and I are very pleased
to have you here, General.
Thank you, Excellency.
He called you ''Excellency'' !
It's his first infraction
to Garibaldi's orders !
- Concetta !
- Welcome back.
- Mademoiselle.
- Tancredi.
Hello !
Dear aunt...
General, my nephew told me you
wish to see the villa's frescoes.
I'd love to, Excellency.
It'll soon be dark,
so let's do it now.
ln the middle, Flashing Jupiter,
Juno, Mars, Venus and Mercury.
On that side, Thetis is preceded
by a host of tritons and dryads,
and Apollo surrounded by clouds.
They're all exalting the glory
of Casa Salina.
Tancredi...
- Do you want a mint ?
- Yes, just the ones I like !
That's why I brought them !
- He's so pale... Are we sure the
wound is not bad ? - Excuse me ?
Well,
a promotion is well worth a wound !
I found myself
in those same places,
but what I can no longer find
are those days !
I found myself
in those same places,
but what I can no longer find
are those days !
The coaches are coming !
I'm pleased to welcome
Their Excellencies.
- Don Onofrio, how are you ?
- Well, Excellency.
The palace is in the exact state
you left it in.
- Very well, Don Onofrio.
- Finally !
Là ! Rosalie, quelle poussiêre, toi
aussi, pauvre petite, viens ici.
Very well indeed, Don Onofrio.
I am proud of shaking hands with
one who was wounded in Palermo !
I was made Captain just because
I got a gnat in the eye !
I know you did a lot for our cause,
Don Calogero !
- Crispi spoke very nicely about
you. - Thank you very much.
- Don Ciccio !
- Welcome back, Excellency.
Dear Teresina, it's such a pleasure
to see you again.
And you, of course.
So, what is new ?
What do you mean ?
- I don't know, Excellency...
Do you mind if... - Go ahead.
Te Deum laudamus !
Te Dominum confitemur.
Te aeternum Patrem
omnis terra veneratur.
Tibis omnes Angeli...
- Remember the invitations
to dinner for tonight. - Yes.
- You must invite the wives
as well. - Why ? - It's better.
lnvite Don Calogero and his wife,
the notary and his,
and Don Ciccio Tumeo, who,
thank God, doesn't have one.
- And all the others after dinner.
- Yes.
Sanctus, Sanctus,
Sanctus Dominus Deus Sabaoth.
Pleni sunt caeli et terra
maiestatis gloriae tuae.
Te gloriosus Apostulorum chorus,
Te Prophetarum laudabilis numerus.
- What ?
- It's Mimì, Excellency.
- Father Pirrone...
- What about him ?
He wishes to see Your Excellency
immediately.
- Fine, then, let him in.
- Yes, Excellency.
May I come in, Excellency ?
I'm so sorry, I didn't know...
- Don't be silly, Father.
- Yes, Excellency.
You are used to the nudity of the
soul, the body's is more innocent.
- Give me my bathrobe.
- Excuse me ? - The bathrobe !
Sure, here.
Come on, Father !
- Harder, Father, come on !
- Yes, Excellency.
- Take my suggestion. - Yes ?
- Do have a bath, once in a while.
Take a seat. Sit down !
Tell me,
what's all this hurry for ?
Well, Excellency...
I am in charge
of a very delicate mission.
A person you care very much about,
chose to open her heart to me,
and asked me to tell you,
maybe wrongly convinced
of your admiration for me...
- Could you be more concise ?
- Of course, Excellency. You see...
- Come on, Father ! Who is it ?
The Princess ? - Not at all !
The Princess is very tired,
she's resting, now.
I'm talking about Miss Concetta.
She's in love.
Miss Concetta ?
How... ?
Ah ! Rubbish !
I'm sorry if I've upset you,
I didn't think...
You see, Father a man can think of
himself as still young, even at 45.
But when he realizes his kids
are grown enough to fall in love,
old age becomes
all of a sudden overwhelming.
Excellency...
You haven't even asked me who...
the boy Miss Concetta...
No need.
She's so silly,
why didn't she tell me herself ?
What am I supposed to say ?
Well, Excellency, the wish to found
a Christian family
is very much welcomed
by the Church,
and Christ's presence at Cana...
Let's not lose track,
Father, please !
I mean to talk about
this one wedding,
not the Cana Wedding,
or wedding in general !
Has Don Tancredi proposed already ?
When did he ?
Well, I don't think he has made
any straight proposal, yet.
But Miss Concetta has no doubts.
His care, his looks, his words...
The little Princess
is sure he loves her
and she feels the proposal
is about to come.
Don't worry, Father,
we're not in danger, yet.
These are the fantasies
of a romantic, shy girl.
- Why do you say ''danger'' ?
- Father, can you picture her...
as ambassadress
to Vienna or St. Petersburg ?
I love Concetta, I like her.
She's so quiet and submissive.
- But Tancredi... Tancredi has
a great future ! - Yes, but...
Come on, Father, how could ever
Concetta, so virtuous and shy,
help a husband climb the slippery
stairs of the new society ?
Tancredi needs money.
Concetta will get a dowry,
of course.
But the fortunes of the family will
have to be split in seven !
Mark, I said seven.
Tancredi needs a lot more.
One of the Sutera girls,
for instance.
Yeah, I know, I know.
They're so ugly, poor things !
- But so rich, Father, very, very
rich ! - Yes, but what about...
What ? Love ?
Yeah, right, love ! It moves
heaven and earth for a year,
and nothing for the remaining
thirty. I know what love is.
- What ? - Excellency, what dress
do you wish to wear for dinner ?
Father, you'll tell Concetta
that I'm not upset at all,
but that we'll face the subject
when it'll be more than a fantasy.
- What should I wear ?
Any of my tailcoats. - Very well.
- Au revoir, Father.
- Excellency...
Good-bye.
Dad ! Don Calogero is coming up the
stairs. He's wearing a tailcoat !
A tailcoat !
Uncle, these news have affected you
more than the landing in Marsala.
Don Calogero with a white tie
is the sign there's a revolution !
Yes, it is a tailcoat indeed,
but... look at it !
And the shoes !
- Good evening, Don Calogero.
- Good evening, Prince.
- My wife... isn't feeling well.
- I'm very sorry. - Thank you.
I hope Their Excellencies will
allow my daughter Angelica's
coming in her place.
Of course ! Come, please.
For a whole month she's done
nothing but talk about
how much it would please her
to meet you, now that she's grown.
I remember her very well,
as a child. She was so cute !
We'll be glad to see her again.
- Good evening, Don Calogero.
- Good evening, Miss.
- Princess...
- Good evening, Don Calogero.
My daughter will be here soon.
She wasn't quite ready, yet.
It's such a short walk
from our place.
- We'll wait for her, Don Calogero.
- My wife isn't well. - I'm sorry !
As I was telling you, the Church
is in very bad conditions.
- I thought you had it repaired
last year. - I did !
But the eaves are all broken...
Support us and become VIP member
to remove all ads from OpenSubtitles.org