Is anyone there?
Micol must be up
to one of her tricks!
- Did Alberto or Micol phone?
- Micol.
- What a stupid joke!
- I was only fooling.
They're much too well-bred.
Maybe so,
but they're still not here.
- Is anyone there?
- Yes, I'm coming!
- Race you to the entrance!
- Don't leave me behind!
They're coming back.
We've waited so long,
I began to think they'd gone away.
No, the Finzi-Continis
never leave their kingdom.
The house must be
a long way from the gate.
Come in!
Straight ahead.
You can't miss it.
- What's that?
- A monster!
Does he bite?
With four teeth left,
what can he bite...
except corn mush?
- He's so damn big!
- He looks like a horse.
I thought the palace
only invited you...
but a lot of us were honored.
We can thank our Fascists
for the privilege.
Nice to see you loving as ever.
Engaged yet?
- When will you be, Giorgio?
- To whom?
Everyone knows to whom.
Been in Ferrara long?
No, about a month.
But I don't get out much,
like Alberto.
- Do you know Micol too?
- No. What's she like?
Very beautiful: tall, blond...
but unpredictable.
That way!
Here we are!
Come on, Alberto.
They're here!
You lunatic-- I'll fall!
There's our Micol!
There she is!
My brother and I decided
to hold our own tournament here...
since the club's put us out.
- It may even be more fun!
- It's lovely!
Like the country!
Sorry that the court looks like
an old potato field.
It needs a red clay top
and deeper backspaces.
But to Papa, any land left uncultivated
seems a total waste.
But next year maybe!
Excuse me.
You haven't met Adriana Trentini.
Carletto Sani.
And Tonino Collevatti.
- Want to change?
- Are we playing or not?
Let the children play first,
then the champions.
- You can change in the Hutte.
- What's that?
The cabana.
Don稚 you know German?
Very bad. Learn it at once!
Aren't you playing?
Later. I don't feel like it now.
Do you like him?
- Do you?
- Oh, he's not my type.
- Who is he?
- A great friend of Alberto.
Milan, college, love affairs.
He works in industry here.
- How are you?
- Fine. And you?
Fine.
- Did you get your degree?
- In February. And you?
- Me too.
- In Venice?
- Yes, but will they let us graduate?
- I hope so.
Where have you been hiding?
I saw you
at the Venice Cultural Contests.
I knew it was you.
You haven't changed.
Why didn't you come over?
It would have been nice.
I don't know.
Somehow, I finally decided not to.
What's your thesis on?
English. Emily Dickinson.
The 19th-century American poet.
A fantastic woman.
An old maid like me.
Here we are!
Jor!
Good dog!
Beautiful,
but maybe a bit silly?
Perhaps.
What do you care?
Oh, me...
I've always liked women
of Gladys' type.
Beautiful, stupid,
and sufficiently--
Whorish.
Do you like Ferrara?
It's not nearly as dead
as you told me it was.
It's lively.
Lots of interesting people.
Especially among the proletariat...
in the so-called working class.
But the middle class
I don't care for.
They're all of them
more or less Fascists.
Except for you Jews...
understandably...
considering--
But at least the workers
at my place...
are almost all antifascist.
This is nice...
but to think
of being here forever--
You never go out anymore?
No, never.
Anyway, where would I go?
If it were possible to pick the faces
one met on the street...
I would go out.
But whenever I did go out...
I always felt
I was being spied on...
envied.
Whereas here
you pick the faces.
Is that what you mean?
Not exactly.
There are never many of us here.
I never feel attacked.
I know what you think:
that I have no zest for life.
But who can give me that?
My seven old graybeards--
you know what they are?
- Palms.
- Good! But what kind of palms?
I don't know.
Granny Josette got them
from the Rome Botanical Garden.
Washingtonia fiilifera.
Why are you laughing?
You're so ignorant!
I bet you can't tell
an elm from an oak.
Come on, what tree is that?
To me all trees are alike.
I, for one, detest anyone
who doesn't love trees!
That plane tree, for example...
may have been planted
by Lucrezia Borgia!
Imagine!
It's nearly 500 years old.
Let's go.
Oh, a flat tire!
When I was little,
I used to run off.
Not Alberto.
He was always more obedient.
One day,
when I'd stayed out too long...
near the Wall of the Angels...
riding on bike handlebars
with a gang of boys...
when I got home,
I found my parents in such despair...
that I decided to be good.
- I never ran off again.
- I thought you only rode with me!
I never invited anyone else
into our garden.
Honestly?
Shall I stop?
Do you remember?
Ten years ago.
You were just a child, Giorgio.
You really must be blind!
What are you doing?
I've been watching you
for ten minutes.
If you were asleep
and I woke you...
do excuse me.
You have my sympathy.
Sympathy? Why? What for?
- What time is it?
- 3:00, I think.
You must be hungry.
Flunked an exam, didn稚 you?
Did you pass all yours?
I don't know. We private pupils
take orals after you do.
I had mine today.
Relax! It's not important,
repeating an exam!
Yes, it is,
when it's the first time.
But it's done,
and I'm over it now.
You are? Then why didn稚 you
go home for lunch?
- How did you know?
- We just know.
We have ways
of getting information.
How can you perch there,
like at a window?
On my trusty ladder.
Come on over.
I'll show you what to do.
But it looks too high.
No, it's easy.
Use the notches
and those nails I drove in.
Where can I leave my bike?
Signorina Micol, that's dangerous!
You get down!
All right! Stop yelling!
The professor said not to go out!
It's dangerous, I say!
Ten years had to pass
before you opened your garden again.
- Alberto!
- Let him whistle!
Wait for me!
Collevatti, you're an ace!
Well, that was nice today.
Yes, but actually,
it was nicer when we were alone.
Remember this?
Are you cold?
Yes, just a bit.
Gina, please bring up
a hot water bottle.
Right away.
Off to bed!
No, I don't feel like it.
What will I be like when I'm old?
Like Granny Josette?
Well, if we live, we'll find out.
Today's paper! Read all about
the meeting of the Supreme Council!
You think we値l move
into the B League?
We can make it!
Today's paper! Read all about
the meeting of the Supreme Council!
You spent yesterday afternoon
at the Finzi-Continis?
Yes.
And how were they?
Pleasant?
Very pleasant.
I'm sure they were!
Yes, because they're glad
about what's happening.
- It's quite clear.
- What is?
That they basically welcome
the anti-Semitic laws.
They're eager to see them passed.
Invitations, broad smiles,
low bows...
and the garden finally opened
to everyone!
Converted into a ghetto
under their noble patronage!
In ghettos there are only Jews.
At the Finzi-Continis,
except for Lattes and me...
they're all Aryans.
Take Adriana Trentini!
Tricks, vile tricks,
just to get hold of you!
Next comes your pet mania!
Meaning?
That our Mussolini
is better than Hitler...
our fascism better than Nazism!
Well, it's true!
Did you see today's paper?
Then read it!
What?
I don't have my glasses.
It says that Jews
may no longer marry non-Jews...
and are barred from state schools.
What about Giorgio's degree?
- Except--
- Except what?
Persons of high patriotic
and Fascist merit.
- You're a party member.
- Yes, but that's not enough.
Don't laugh, stupid!
You'll have to quit school.
Come on!
You may clear.
I forgot to add:
no more domestiques...
of the racearyenne.
No more domestiques?
- Apparently.
- How will we manage?
We'll manage.
We'll manage somehow.
- May I?
- Yes, Father.
What is that?
"" 19th-Century Europe""
Is it interesting?
- Quite.
- Let me read it after you.
Look, I understand how you feel,
but you have to admit...
we're not so badly off here.
Granted: no more mixed marriages.
That's actually not too--
No phone listings,
no public schools...
and that, I must agree, is serious.
So is being barred
from the armed forces.
No obituaries in the newspapers...
and now, no servants.
But apart from that...
you'll admit we can still live,
move about, own property.
- In effect, be a citizen.
- Third-class.
Third-class, if you will,
but still a citizen who can...
enjoy his basic rights.
Such as?
There have always been
few enough rights for anyone.
We weren't the first
to be persecuted. That is true.
But we all kept quiet
as long as we weren't hit.
Nevertheless...
I don't think you should
keep yourself so isolated...
or refuse to come to the phone.
It's very bad for you
to segregate yourself.
For your poor brother
and sister too...
because, naturally,
they imitate you.
Like giving up the Tennis Club.
They're not expelling you.
Nor me from
the Chamber of Commerce.
Don稚 you see, good God,
that you池e playing into the hands...
of the very people
who want us to stop being...
Italians!
I've already been expelled
from the Tennis Club.
Who are those two people?
My mother and father.
Don't stop.
Please don't let us disturb you.
Do go on playing.
Good afternoon!
Still at it?
I haven't played yet!
I'll just watch this time.
I feel you're not really
interested in men.
That's true.
In your case, at any rate.
What don稚 you like about me?
My friendship with your brother?
May I also speak quite frankly?
- Please do. Frankness--
- Is your fetish, we know.
The main thing is
you're too frank...
and therefore, inevitably, well--
- Ill-bred.
- Precisely.
Second--
You're too much
the industrious Lombard...
too much a Communist...
and, finally...
too hairy.
Bravo, Desiree!
You played for three hours.
Who won?
- Desiree.
- I've got something to show you.
Later, when we're alone.
- What a crowd!
- My uncles and my grandmother.
Micol, your uncles are here.
- This is a friend of Alberto's.
- Delighted.
Alberto has often spoken to us
about you.
Please do come visit us.
Have you perspired much?
Some.
You should be careful.
Was it hot in Bologna, Uncle?
Oh, yes!
Eighty-six degrees in the shade.
Here you can breathe.
You were on a consultation?
Yes, I was.
How did Uncle Federico
happen to go along with you?
Since being forced out
of his railroad post...
he has nothing to do,
the lucky fellow.
And he enjoys driving.
- How are you?
- Fine.
Just a little tired.
Are you sleeping?
Not well.
It's not going to rain!
Are you coming with me?
Let's go.
That crazy Micol!
See there?
That's where we had
our gym lessons.
And the carriage
I rode to school in.
You recognize it?
Good as ever,
but no flowers inside.
Perrotti still puts them in.
He only drives Granny
around the garden in it.
Perrotti works here
despite the new laws?
Isn't it risky if they find out?
- No, it's a secret.
- Sorry.
Papa's a big donor
to government charities.
Where will it end?
Get in.
It seems only yesterday
that you came to the synagogue in it.
How long ago that was!
The few times we went,
I'd look for you.
Giorgio, don't you like it
better now?
Why?
Why? Because we can stay here
by ourselves...
with no one to scold us,
for one thing!
Children are always prisoners
of grown-ups.
I mean...
I like to feel I'm a woman.
And you? Would you rather
still be a child?
No, but--
So many ""buts""!
- Micol, wait!
- Too late!
- It's raining!
- Oh, just a few drops!
You know the way to the gate?
Of course you do.
You came that way.
Phone us sometime.
Defend your queen!
It's no use.
You're too good for me!
- What's so funny?
- I was thinking--
About what?
I was thinking...
of Gladys in Milan...
and asking myself--
What?
Whether you ever slept
with her or not.
It's been three years now.
I didn't even find her
at all attractive.
Then what made you act mysterious,
even jealous...
over some ballet dancer?
Well--
And I was so full of scruples!
Maritain says you Jews
are never boring.
It's quite true.
You're so very complicated.
Come now.
Did you ever go to a brothel?
- Did you?
- Me? But of course!
How pretty and chic we are!
Listen...
our uncles are dining
and sleeping here.
He's dining here too.
- And sleeping?
- No, not sleeping.
I'll phone you.
Tomorrow morning.
Good night.
- Who was it?
- Giorgio.
I've decided not to stay.
We'll play another time.
- Why?
- Good night.
Do stay.
To please Alberto.
I might even apologize then.
Apologize for what?
Good night.
- Will you phone me?
- Yes, I will.
You really will phone?
She's in the kitchen
ironing your coat.
- Hurry!
- Dear, I only have two hands.
Someone at the door!
- Who is it?
- Me, Maria.
- Did anyone see you?
- Carlino.
But he minds his own business.
He won't talk.
I told her to come earlier,
but she lives so far away.
- You know it's unwise.
- She's only here a few hours.
But she's here.
Anyway, let's not tell your father.
He'd be worried.
- Hello. May I come in?
- Of course.
- You want to see?
- Signor Alberto.
Not likely today.
He's in bed with a fever.
He got drenched in the rain.
- And the young lady?
- She's not here. She's gone.
Gone?
- Where?
- To Venice, with her uncles.
They all went off
less than an hour ago.
She left no message for me?
The back table is free.
Excuse me, but the director
told me that...
you can't stay here.
You mean...
I have to move?
Not move.
Just get out of here.
- Why?
- Don't ask me!
I want to talk with the director.
- I can't!
- Go on!
Tell him I'm on my way
to see him.
I'm sorry, dear boy.
I'm so terribly sorry.
But it's not up to me.
Instructions are instructions.
- If I could--
- If you could--
Personally, I'd be delighted
for a talented young man like you--
As your father's old friend--
With your brilliant
literary future--
By the way, how is the poetry?
Still writing?
Listen.
Be patient. I have--
Yes, I know.
You have a family.
All Italy has a family.
He's sorry.
He has a family.
I understand. Poor fellow.
I know it wasn't up to him.
- How is Alberto?
- So-so.
- He's come here to study.
- Splendid, splendid.
- What's he doing here?
- Studying.
Good, good.
- What's he doing here?
- Studying, Mama.
There you are:
your table, your books.
What's your thesis on?
It will deal with the poetry
of Enrico Panzacchi.
Fine choice. Very interesting.
One of Carducci's school.
I think you値l find we have
everything the library has...
though we're more selective.
The major works are all here.
Thank you.
Is it true you have
some unpublished works by Carducci?
I'll show them to you one day.
I'm in there.
If you need anything--
coffee, lemonade...
a bit of advice--
just call me.
- They're lucky!
- Who?
The private pupils.
They're easy to spot.
They're different.
What's happening in Ferrara?
Whom do you see?
When am I coming back?
Tomorrow, if I could.
I must finish my thesis first.
Surely by Passover.
When is it this year?
No, I can't any sooner.
It's like a century
since I saw you.
What's wrong?
Why, nothing, Micol.
I'm fine, I assure you.
I long to have you back here.
That's true, but there's no reason
for you to worry.
I've had the X rays.
No, nothing new.
I said there's nothing new.
Shall I phone tomorrow?
If you like.
All right. I promise.
- Where are all these troops going?
- To their regiments. Then who knows?
Want some newspapers?
I'll wait and read
the French ones tomorrow.
I think there's a seat over here.
No, this way!
Ernesto!
Try to get some sleep tonight,
won稚 you, please?
No, I want to be awake
crossing the French border.
Try to economize.
We can't send much money abroad.
So put it away safely
and be very careful.
I'm just going off to school,
not to war!
- Got everything?
- Yes, everything.
Who can tell, who knows well
What is the meaning of One?
One God who dwells in heaven
Who can tell, who knows well
What痴 the meaning of Two?
Two, the tablets of Moses
One was, One is
One forever One shall be
One God who dwells in heaven
Who can tell, who knows well
What痴 the meaning of Three?
Our own patriarchs are Three
Abraham, Isaac and Jacob
Two, the tablets of Moses
One was, One is
One forever One shall be
One God who dwells in heaven
Who can tell, who knows well
What痴 the meaning of Four?
Hello.
Who is it?
- Who was it?
- No one.
That happens to me too,
at night.
Every night. I go to pick up the phone
and nobody answers.
What do they want?
Who are they?
Did you just ring up
and not answer?
Because someone just did
and wouldn't talk.
What? A surprise?
What kind of surprise?
Look, can稚 you at least
give me a hint?
Come on! How mysterious!
Fine, I'll be right over.
One God who dwells in heaven
- I'm so glad to see you again!
- When did you come?
This afternoon, with my uncles.
- I'm sorry.
- Why should you be?
I shouldn't have run out here.
It's my fault.
What lovely snow!
Venice didn't get any at all.
If I had heard about it--
- What's this?
- I'm engaged. Didn稚 you know?
I'm not!
Can稚 you tell I'm joking?
It's a Passover gift from Alberto.
Come, they'll be worrying about us.
Wait.
- Nothing.
- Did you like the surprise?
Did you like it?
He was nice to come right over.
Maybe he guessed.
I was curious, I must say.
There's another surprise.
That one I can guess.
You got your degree.
Good for you!
No cause for praise.
I made it, but without honors.
The German professor,
a brute of a Nazi, had it in for me.
Why, he even conducted his exams
in Nazi uniform!
We have guests.
Happy Passover!
Sit down here by me.
Giorgio, at last!
Why don稚 you come more often?
Alberto is so alone.
I'm glad you're here this Passover.
Sir, I was so pleased
to get Alberto's invitation.
I didn't even know
Micol had come back.
Fortunately our Micol
is home again.
It's so sad without her.
Behave, boys!
I can't breathe that way!
Alberto's told us
so much about you.
They're childhood friends.
How's the thesis going?
You haven't used our library lately.
After Passover
I'll be there again.
Will your thesis be ready by June?
I wonder.
You should get it done...
before they issue a decree
that now literature also...
is Aryan.
Such a lovely glass.
What's it for?
My daughter brought it from Venice.
It serves, she claims...
to predict the future-- a joke!
What has it said?
All sorts of things.
First we asked if I壇 get my degree,
and it said no.
Second...
if Micol will marry.
To this the answer wasn稚 clear.
Third, it said war is coming.
A long war...
painful for everyone,
not just for us...
Negroes.
But finally...
ending in total victory...
for the forces of good.
Yes?
It's the young man.
Come on in.
Don't be afraid I have the flu.
It痴 just a cold.
Sit down here.
We must talk.
What are you reading?
Cocteau. Very chic!
But nothing like those great books
of our childhood...
whenever we came down
with the flu!
The Three Musketeers,
Twenty Years Later...
Warand Peace.
Those were real novels!
Even when it comes to ""chic,""
they were better.
This room is so different
from what I imagined.
How are you?
So-so.
Listen, Giorgio...
I'm sorry to hurt you.
Terribly sorry.
On the other hand...
let's try not to ruin
our beautiful childhood memories.
Look, I've done my very best.
As soon as I noticed the bad turn
our relationship was taking...
the growth of something false...
of something wrong
and very dangerous--
you have to admit it--
I went away.
If I stayed in Venice so long...
it was on your account.
You must face it.
It's not possible!
But why?
Why isn't it possible?
Stop it!
Please, don't!
Someone may come in!
Behave yourself!.
Get up, please. I can't breathe.
What's the point?
It's utterly useless.
Useless? Why is it useless?
Why don稚 you go in there?
You're all flushed.
Wash your face.
Who is it?
It's Jor. Let him in.
Lie down.
There, that's a good dog!
Who was that?
And now, please leave.
- Shall I phone tomorrow?
- No, we mustn't phone each other.
And best not to come back.
Never?
Please.
It's much better for both of us,
believe me.
Good-bye?
Good-bye.
- Still awake?
- Yes, Father.
I'm up late tonight also.
I felt like taking a walk.
Too many people during the day.
Why are you still awake?
- Anything wrong?
- No, nothing.
You saw Ernesto's letter?
How would you like to visit him
in Grenoble for a few days?
We must get some money to him
before it's too late.
Too late for what?
Nothing. If a thing needs doing,
get it done.
I could leave tomorrow.
No, it takes a few days
to get a French visa.
Besides, to raise the money...
I have to sell our securities.
We must be cautious.
They're quick to accuse us.
- And they have lots of imagination.
- The French visa is no problem.
But will they let me out?
Why not?
We've not reached that point yet.
A change will do you good,
to leave Ferrara for a while.
- Good night.
- Good night, Father.
With all the 19- and 20-year-olds
they could draft...
why do they put the bite on us?
I've done my share.
Eighteen months in Ethiopia,
malaria and dysentery included.
Get someone else now!
- Where are we?
- We just passed Novara.
You're safe working at Fiat.
Without your guns,
how do we fight?
No, we're not safe.
Lots of our men have been called up.
All I ask is to stay in Italy.
Anything but Africa,
after what I saw.
Move over.
We really used poison gas?
We sure did!
Macaroni, vive la liberte!
What a superb beard!
How are you?
Fine! How about you
and Mother, Father and Fanny?
Fine! We're all fine.
So many soldiers.
Do they expect war to break out?
Yes. A lot of us Italians
are here now.
A Levi from Turin,
a Piperno from Rome.
All of them students.
But you値l soon meet them.
In Italy, they think
France and England...
will compromise again
at the last moment.
The Italians know nothing.
You can't think when you don't know.
For us, what is there
to look forward to now?
They talk a lot about the Stuka.
The call it ""the victory plane.""
I bet it's nothing new.
May I have the salt?
What's that number on your arm?
I'll tell you later.
It was put on me at Dachau.
Do they talk about Dachau
in Italy?
No? What a pity.
What is Dachau?
It's a hotel in the woods.
A hundred chalets,
all rooms without baths...
a single latrine...
surrounded by barbed wire.
The service is provided by the SS.
Instead of tagging our luggage,
they brand numbers on our flesh...
as a souvenir of their hospitality.
The guests at Dachau
are Jews, Communists...
Socialists like me,
dissidents of all varieties.
In other words...
those whom the Nazis call
the dregs of the human race.
I got out alive...
because I'm a coward.
I told them
I had become a Nazi.
My brother didn't know
about any of this.
So now he knows too.
You really want to go back?
I have too many ties
I can't bring with me.
I'll see you.
Giorgio, it's been ages!
I wondered where you were.
I've missed you
at the Finzi-Continis.
I've stopped going.
And Micol?
What's she doing?
She's the same as ever:
full of vitality, carefree.
But not Alberto.
He never leaves his room now.
He'd like to see you.
And Adriana? How is she?
That's all over.
Mixed marriages are forbidden.
She's engaged to a boy
from Bologna, I was told.
It may be best for both of us.
More so for her than me.
- Let's get together.
- Yes, let's.
By the way, you haven't been there
in so long. How come?
- Women?
- Did they ask about me?
Alberto did, several times.
And Micol?
What's Micol doing?
She translates English.
She plays tennis
and never goes out.
As if only the garden were safe.
Like her brother.
What shall we do? Go out?
Do you prefer a woman
or a movie?
- The clown!
- Bunch of riffraff!.
I'd like to know what's so funny!
- Stupid bastards!
- Get out, you dirty Jew!
If I ever catch you--
You're a real idiot.
You can thank your God...
the bum didn't know
you really are a Jew!
A hell of a shot!
If your aim's that good--
- Try me.
- Slow down!
Back home they say...
"" Big nose and black pelt...
you can't tell
what's below the belt.""
What do I owe you?
Beginner's luck!
Let's see you do it again.
Please be sure you get it
good and level.
Forgive me.
Forgive me for disobeying.
Today, I'm the one
who has something to say.
Have you been in Ferrara
all along?
More or less.
One time I rode past the wall
on my bike.
I saw you playing tennis.
You and Malnate.
You know, he and I have become
quite friendly.
That's nice.
You said you have
something to say.
What is it?
I just wanted to see you again.
That's all.
I love you.
It's never happened to me before.
And I know it never will again.
But I don't love you!
Lovers have a drive
to overwhelm one another.
But the way we are,
alike as two drops of water...
how could we ever overwhelm
or tear each other to pieces?
It would be like making love
with a brother.
Like with Alberto.
You and I are not normal people.
For the two of us...
what counts more
than the possession of things--
how shall I put it?--
is the remembrance of things...
the memory of things.
Isn't that so?
I wonder.
It may simply be that...
you don't like me physically.
That's all.
Don't talk such nonsense.
There's no connection.
Yes, there is!
And you know it.
Unless--
Unless what?
Unless there's someone else.
There's absolutely no one.
Who could there be?
Why ask me?
It could be anyone.
What else can I say, Micol?
I can't even persuade you
to let me love you.
I'm so helpless.
If anything happens to you...
the fault will be mine.
I'll never come here again.
I'll never come again
to this garden.
Il Duce will make an address
in one hour...
to the entire nation.
Italians...
Fascists...
you will hear the announcement
of an historic event.
Duce! Duce! Duce!
Shut up! Shut up!
What is it? What's wrong?
Italy's declared war!
The Duce is speaking!
Well, say something!
Giorgio? Is that you?
Why haven't I seen you?
Let's get together.
No, Sunday's too late.
I'll be gone.
I've been called up.
Yes, they caught me.
First to Bologna.
Then who knows?
I only hope I'm not sent to Russia.
Fine. I'll see you later.
Why don稚 you visit them?
- Why haven稚 you gone?
- I can't.
Are things that bad with Micol?
I loved her so terribly much.
If you knew
how much she likes you...
how she sticks up for you.
Alberto likes and respects you too.
I have no use...
for their liking or their respect.
I think you池e wrong.
Whatever happened
between you and Micol...
your friendship is worth saving.
Excuse me for asking...
but did you ever even kiss her?
Once. Yes, I did, just once.
Let's not talk about it.
At a time like this...
my broken heart is absurd.
Now you池e leaving too.
Will you write me?
We'll see each other again.
When I'm off duty,
I'll spend Sundays in Ferrara.
It's midnight! I must go
or I'll never wake up!
Good luck!
- You too!
- I'll need it.
Be of good cheer!
This is London.
Soviet forces
are fighting magnificently...
in defense of Moscow.
The Nazi forces are encountering
stiff resistance.
Stalin--
Is that you, Giorgio?
Yes, Father.
You know what time it is? 2:25.
I went out.
With your friend from Milan?
What's the news?
The Germans are outside of Moscow.
You think they can be driven back?
I doubt it.
I think they can.
But if they fail...
then it's really the end.
Look, Giorgio...
how are things with Micol?
Forgive me for bringing up
this subject...
but your mother and I...
have been aware.
Things are so bad...
they couldn't be any worse.
It's all over.
Oh, yes, I know how painful
that can be.
But in the long run, it's best.
You really wanted to be engaged?
Engaged, and maybe marry...
at a time like this?
If I may say so...
as families go,
the Finzi-Continis are not for us.
They're not our sort.
They're different.
They don't even seem Jewish.
Micol-- Maybe that's what
attracted you to her.
That she's superior to you
socially.
It'll pass.
You'll get over it.
And a lot sooner than you think.
I can imagine
what you池e feeling now.
Yet, in a way,
I rather envy you.
In life, in order to understand...
to really understand the world...
you must die at least once.
So it's better to die young,
when there's still time left...
to recover and live again.
When you're old, it's much worse.
Why is that?
There's no time
to start over from zero.
And our generation has made
so many, many mistakes.
A few months and it will seem as if
none of this had ever happened to you.
You may even end up being glad.
You'll feel richer,
one might say.
More mature.
Let's hope so.
I'm happy all that came out...
and I got this load off my chest.
How about catching some sleep?
You need it.
I'll try to close my eyes
a few minutes too.
Good night.
Go up to Alberto.
I couldn't lie to him.
Air raid!
Young man, try your luck!
No, thanks.
Hey, I know you!
Before this stinking war started...
you came with your friend--
my friend too.
Malnate?
He was killed in Russia.
And you--
how did you dodge it?
They didn't want me.
I'm a Jew.
A Jew!
- Beat it! Go away!
- Why?
They're hunting Jews.
They'll grab you anywhere!
Beat it! Go away!
An eight-hour patrol
is too long!
Signor Lattes?
Kindly come with us.
- To the police?
- Just a formality. A few minutes.
Please.
Stop!
There he goes! That way!
Open up.
This way!
Go in the other room.
Finzi-Contini, Prof. Ermanno.
Here.
Finzi-Contini, Olga.
Arton, Regina in Herrera.
Finzi-Contini, Alberto.
He died six months ago.
Finzi-Contini, Nicole.
Micol.
- Ascoli in Levi.
- Present.
- Lattes, Magda.
Lattes, Luigi.
Ancona, Olga.
Ascoli, Elisa.
This is for Montanari.
Move. Let us through.
All who've been called
and the newcomers--
Take this to Montanari.
Follow me. Line up.
Please.
Let's go!
Faster, faster!
Go on.
Stop.
Make room.
Inside, please.
Finzi-Contini, finished yet?
Good-bye.
You're here too.
We're all here,
but they've separated us.
They took me away last night.
Not Giorgio, just me.
Giorgio, my wife and Fanny should be
far away by now...
and hopefully they made it.
Thank God!
- Where will they take us?
- Who knows?
Pray to God they at least
let us stay together, Micol...
those of us from Ferrara.
""This Film Won the Golden Bear Award
at the 1971 Berlin Film Festival""