"Pelle the Conqueror"
- Papa?
- Pelle, everything's just fine.
Please, tell me about it again.
This new land is very different
from the one we left.
- They live a peculiar life.
- Tell me again how I won't believe my eyes.
And when they cook a pork roast...
it's all covered with raisins...
and they put butter
on their bread...
at least half-an-inch
thick of butter.
Now, the brandy...
it's cheaper than water.
But it's strong-- strong enough
to kill an ox.
But don't worry. It's not too strong
for your father, Pelle. He's hard.
And children are free all day.
Yeah, Pelle, yeah.
Tell me about it again, Papa.
The wages in Denmark
are so incredibly high that boys don't--
Boys don't have to
go out to work, you said.
- They can play. They can play all day long.
- Yeah.
Don't worry.
Go over there.
They won't fool me.
I won't jump at the first offer.
Go over there.
- Your papers. Your papers.
- Here.
This is my son.
- Is your wife with you?
- She's dead.
We come from Tomelilla, Sweden.
My name is Lasse Karlsson.
I'm offering you my services.
That man looks like
he would be kind to children.
Hello. My name is Lasse Karlsson
from Tomelilla.
I'm here to offer my services.
You should have stayed
in Sweden. You're too old.
Hello. Lasse Karlsson
from Tomelilla.
I'm here to offer my--
I shouldn't take the first offer.
My name is Lasse Karlsson
from Tomelilla.
I'm offering my--
Hello. My name is Lasse Karlsson
from Tomelilla.
I'm here to offer my services.
You're too old, Swede,
and the boy is too young.
I'm not-- I'm not gonna
take the first job offer.
I'm not gonna do it.
You're too late.
You were on the boat from Sweden?
Where are your parents?
Hello. My name is Lasse
Karlsson from Tomelilla. I am offering--
Let me see your papers.
I'll pay you 100 krone a year,
including the boy--your son.
Dear sweet Jesus.
- You'll sleep in there.
Any questions, ask me...
or my assistant.
Stop doing that!
Come back here! Stupid animals!
- You'll get me in trouble.
- You won't get away from me, you dumb beast!
You'll do what I tell ya.
That's it. Move it.
You gotta learn how to treat 'em.
Hit 'em on the teats. Then they'll listen.
The teats or the hind legs.
Hit 'em.
Keep moving. I said keep moving.
- Move. Keep moving.
- Stupid cows.
If you help me with the cattle...
and teach me to talk like a Dane...
I'll share my food with ya.
Always carry a stone.
When a cow starts to run away...
you throw it at her.
You take a good aim, you throw it
and you call her name.
Then she'll come back.
And she'll know who's boss.
- What's your name?
- Rud.
"Rut"?
Rud, with the tongue.
Rud. Rud.
If you put your head
between your legs...
and the sun is just above
the trees over there...
then it's time to give them water.
- The larks' song will tell you too.
- "Rut!"
My mother's from Sweden.
- She can't say my name right either.
- Rut!
Here's the food I promised.
Rut!
New man.
Just what is that cow doing there?
Why is Gabriella there?
The girls can't find their cows
when you move them around.
Aspasia. Can't you read?
Just as it's written.
A-spa-si-a.
Uh, are you saying there is
a difference where a cow stands?
Kongstrup is back.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Erik, why haven't you
unharnessed the horses?
Because I want to eat my food first.
What do you say?
I say you unharness
those horses right now. Come on!
Those horses are more important
than your stomach, you lazy dog!
Do you know the punishment
for stealing milk?
You could be whipped for it.
Well, I won't report you this time.
You know, Pelle,
I've been thinking.
I like you.
So I'll tell you a secret.
I know where you can find
a lot of gold coins...
but you've gotta keep it a secret.
A real secret. You promise?
Just come in here, Pelle,
very quietly.
The raven can be dangerous
if it hears us. Come.
Where are you?
Sir?
Are you here?
Jump, you stinking Swede! Jump!
- Jump!
No-good, rotten little bastard!
- Let's see how you like it!
- Help!
That's enough! Stop it, or I'll turn
both of you in to the authorities!
- I said that's enough!
- Little son of a bitch!
- Help!
- Erik, I'm warning you.
I'll-- I'll turn you in!
You get out of here fast.
You're lucky I was here to save your pelt.
Now get going.
He'll pay for what he did.
You can be sure of that.
You got your father's word of honor.
- I promise you I'll...
- Kill him?
kill the filthy swine.
- You're really gonna do it?
- I've given you my word.
- How?
- Yeah, how?
How are you gonna kill him?
- With a hammer, I think.
- Knock out his brains?
- Yeah.
- You'll really do it?
He's as good as dead.
But then who's going
to read all the names of the cows?
You're right.
Yeah. We'd better settle
for a thrashing...
so he can still read for us, yeah.
I'll give that one a flogging
that he'll never forget.
Yarn for the boy's gray socks.
The patch was for the--
what did she say-- Oh, yes.
The Sunday sweater your mother said.
She said that-- She said that
the sleeves should be let down a little bit.
You know, your mother was a-- She was
so worried about you just before she died.
She didn't think I could
take care of you, Pelle.
"Don't let him wear
those socks too long.
- Don't let him wear them through."
- Lasse?
Lasse?
It's him.
Where are you,
you Swedish bumpkin?
Are you going to do it now?
Yeah?
Sir, I wish to protest
what you did to my son.
What you did to him,
I want to protest.
Why don't you answer when I call?
Sir, I wanted to, uh--
- I wanted to protest about the way that Pelle was--
- You want trouble?
I could report you to the manager.
Aspasia will not be going
out to pasture tomorrow.
- She's ready to calve?
- That's right. Did you think she was gonna foal?
Just lie there and whimper...
but if one can't read Aspasia's name,
one has to show a little respect.
I know Aspasia!
She's the third one from the door!
You promised, Papa!
Knowing that she's the third one
from the door, it's not--
- it's not at all the same as reading her name.
- You promised!
I'm your father. You should show respect
and stop carrying on.
Lasse's old and poor.
What's left? No respect.
They can do what they want with you.
You have shorter breath.
You worry about your heart
and your blood pressure.
That's what getting old is like.
But you're young.
You can still conquer
the whole world.
Look at that. I nearly forgot.
Look here. Pelle, look.
Look what I have.
See, Pelle? I forgot that
I brought this from Sweden.
From Tomelilla.
Look.
If we're lucky, Pelle,
we'll get wild strawberries.
Just think, Pelle.
Real Swedish strawberries.
Nils, go and get some water
for your father.
Nils, how 'bout that water?
Look out over there!
Just who do you think you are, Nils?
Where have you been?
Your father's been looking for you.
The missus sent me to the store.
Let's see what you've got
under your jacket, Pelle.
She said no one was to know.
You're a good lad, Pelle. Come.
If you give me the package,
I'll give it to my wife.
No one else will see it.
Hmm.
Cognac.
It's mine.
I won't budge from this place
until you give it to me.
You bastard, Kongstrup!
I said give me that bottle!
You Satan! You devil!
Pelle, go and tell them all
how he bullies me, how wicked he is!
- Tell them how he's ruining my life!
- It's all lies.
You keep it.
God who keeps his children near...
look at me who's kneeling here.
My happiness is in God's hands...
whatever are the world's demands.
- Papa?
- Yeah?
Tomorrow, it's the day
after tomorrow.
And the day after tomorrow,
it's tomorrow.
My birthday.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
Pelle, was it the real thing
he threw out?
Really cognac?
He poured it into the flowerpot?
Happiness comes
and happiness goes.
My happiness is in God's hands
whatever are the world's demands.
You ought to start grooming.
Put a move on.
Pants, Pelle. Pants first.
But what about your pocket?
There's something in your pocket.
You weren't out stealing
eggs last night, were you?
I'll be very surprised
if that egg isn't broken.
Ohh, just a bunch of paper.
I guess that's what they call
stuffing your pockets.
It's your day--your birthday.
- God bless you, son.
- Thank you.
It's just a simple gift
from a poor man, Pelle.
Look.
Well, well. A real beauty.
It's a birthday present.
Yeah, I should have known
straight away.
You really look like someone
who is having his birthday.
Congratulations.
Happy birthday. It's your day.
They say-- They say that
you plan to run away to America.
What? Run away?
Do you take me for an idiot?
Do you really think I'd risk all I've worked for...
all my savings
and be a hunted outlaw, do ya?
Oh, no. I wanna be free, Pelle.
A free man.
That's what I'm waiting for.
That's what I want--
to be free.
Pelle?
I wanna show you something.
It's here.
Here.
This is the boat to America.
I've got only two years left
to work on this damn farm.
That's all, two years.
Then I'll have enough money
for my ticket.
As soon as the manager
pays out all my money...
then I'm going out
to conquer the world...
over the great ocean, huh?
First America, then China...
Spain, Australia.
It's out there.
It'll be mine to conquer.
It's all out there
just waiting to be conquered.
A man can actually live.
- It's out there waiting for us.
- Take me with ya.
Yeah.
Because today is-- today is--
today is your birthday.
Remember, in two years...
when the snow begins to melt,
we, too, will sail to America.
You and me will set out to conquer...
that great, rich, wonderful world.
Open. Surprise.
We've eaten wild strawberries
on all your birthdays.
Just think,
real Swedish wild strawberries.
How far is it to America, Papa?
America?
Uh, that's a long way.
You have to cross
a whole ocean, Pelle.
Erik says that he wants
to sail there first.
He told me
it's the strongest thing there is.
It's soft, but it can
hold up anything.
Yeah?
I wonder...
America and China...
are they made something
like a boat?
It seems impossible.
Are those countries drifting...
or are they anchored
to the bottom?
Well, the two are anchored
more than likely.
Kongstrup!
- Come out, Kongstrup! I wanna talk to you!
Your son is hungry, Kongstrup!
It's the sow and her cabbage head kid.
Kongstrup, come back.
Your son needs money for food! Do you hear?
Where do you think
you're going, you cabbage head?
We have to talk to your father! Kongstrup,
come say hello to your bastard son. He's hungry!
That dirty lecher has kids all over the place.
- Kongstrup!
- Except with his missus, that is.
- Your son is hungry!
- Some say she's good at hexes.
The monthly allowance for your bastard son!
Do you have so many you forgot?
Get out, you slattern. Didn't I tell you
not to come here? Get out!
- Out!
- The boy has a right to see his father!
Get out, you disgusting sow!
Kongstrup has to pay
for his lechery!
-Kongstrup, you'll never be rid of your son!
- Out, and stay out!
You'll never be rid of us!
Whoa.
Kongstrup. Kongstrup!
Take good care of your slate now,
Pelle, so it doesn't get broken.
And stay out of the way of the big boys
until you can handle them.
But if they won't leave you alone...
the way you handle it is you have
to be the one who hits first, Pelle.
But when you hit,
be sure to hit hard.
You must pay attention
to everything the teacher says.
Don't make trouble.
And when you blow your nose,
use a handkerchief.
Don't use your fingers,
whatever you do.
But if you're sure
that no one is looking...
then naturally it would make sense
to save the handkerchief.
You take care of that sweater
now that I have mended it, huh?
And should the teacher's wife
invite you for coffee...
take only one piece
of cake, Pelle, remember?
- She's not gonna do it.
- And why?
'Cause the teacher
hasn't got a wife.
- That's right. That's the bell now.
Go on.
B-A says ba.
B-E says be.
B-I says bi.
B-O says bo.
B-U says bu.
B-Y says by.
B-A-A says " baa-aa-aa."
You miserable brats!
Stop it! Stop it at once, I say!
I'll give each and every one of you
a good thrashing! Silence!
Silence in this classroom!
Silence. Silence!
You little barbarians.
We have here a new boy.
We must welcome him to our class.
Stand up...
and tell us your name.
- Pelle Karlsson.
- Mm-hmm.
And what are you good at?
- I can make a cow obey me
just by throwing stones at her.
- Listen, Mr. Hayseed.
- I can get the cows to stand
still when I buzz like a wasp.
- Swedish clod.
- I can tell time by using the sun.
- Can you read?
No. Reading's why I come here.
I don't care for your insolence
and sarcasm.
B-A says ba.
B-E says be.
B-I says bi.
This one here, you told me
but I forgot. What do you call it?
Papa, you mean
you've forgotten already?
I could remember
after seeing it only once.
It's an " F."
Yeah. An "F"is exactly what it is.
I don't know what's wrong
with my head today.
"F. " "F!"
What do you think it's used for?
It's the first letter in "afternoon."
F-ternoon, Papa.
Yeah, that's right.
Only you couldn't have figured that out alone.
Your teacher must have told you.
No, I figured it out myself.
Is that so?
You're getting so smart, Pelle.
I tell you, there's no end to what a boy
with such book learning can do.
Maybe a pork roast, Pelle.
Pork roast with raisins.
Or with apples.
They also make it with apples...
instead of with raisins.
Yeah, we'll see. We'll see.
Get out!
I don't want any more
trouble from you. Move!
Herring! Herring on Christmas eve.
I didn't expect that, even from you!
If you don't like the food,
then find some other place!
It would be a pleasure
to see the last of you!
Herring every single day. Couldn't we
have had roast pork for Christmas?
- A real Christmas dinner? Herring!
- You're always complaining!
If you don't like it in this country,
go back to Sweden!
What right do you have
to be so damn stingy?
Don't you think we work
hard enough for our food?
You of all people say that to me,
you lazy dog!
- Go to your quarters!
- To hell!
To hell with you!
To hell with your farm!
To hell with you and your farm!
To hell!
Any other complaints here?
Who asked you to look?
Yeah, you little sissy. Why don't you
go back to where you came from?
Yellow-bellied Swede.
Why don't you just stay with your own kind?
Get lost, Pelle.
You might slip and fall in the icy water.
Go home, Pelle.
- We don't like yellow bellies.
- So quit following us around.
- Go on home to your mama.
- I can't. My mama is dead!
- Can you prove you're not a yellow belly?
- Yeah. I'll jump in that water!
You must be crazy, jumping in the water
like-- like some...
lovesick woman....
just to show those kids.
A good beating is
what you deserve, Pelle.
It's a good thing you didn't drown.
I'd have given you such a beating
you wouldn't have sit down for a month.
Because if you had drowned
it would have been your fault.
Doctor?
You can-- You can use this
if you want to take some blood.
Drink this.
It will help your cold.
Don't be afraid of me, Pelle.
I'm not a witch.
Just very... lonely at times.
Oh, dear God.
You don't even have a mother...
do you?
It's three years since Mama died.
She's in the left-hand side
of the churchyard.
Do you think of her much?
Lasse sews my clothes.
She was a good mother, wasn't she?
She was so sick
and grouchy at the end.
And she used to be so happy.
But we'll get hitched again...
if Lasse can find someone
who will have him.
And then you'll go away.
The workers all hate it here.
It's as though
it were godforsaken.
As if it were cursed.
The earth is bloody.
They say that?
Yeah.
And when they talk about me?
They say you have a pact
with the devil...
and you turn into
a werewolf at night.
It's the price you pay...
yielding your heart
to the wrong man.
If he knew the anguish...
the suffering that he causes
with his lechery.
He's in town at this very moment.
Why does he do this to me?
I married him, made him
a property owner, gave him my love...
the best I have I've given him,
if only he could have given me a child.
- I really have to go.
- Oh, you're afraid of me again.
You're a good boy, Pelle.
If I had a son...
he would... be like you.
Come.
And this is where
we keep our cows.
Papa, it's the missus.
It's the missus with the young lady.
Oh, damn it. Pelle, go forward.
Go forward.
- Pelle, where's your father?
This is our cattleman
Lasse Karlsson and his son Pelle.
Hello.
And this is Miss Signe...
my niece from Copenhagen.
- She will be staying with us now.
- Yep.
I've forgotten what two times two are.
I may be a bit rusty on the subject...
but I think the answer
is the same as in addition.
Two and two are five.
What's lighter--
a ton of feathers...
or a ton of lead?
- Oh, now you.
- Sit down.
if you don't mind, I would like to hear
that question again, Pelle.
Repeat it, please.
Which is lighter--
a ton of feathers or a ton of lead?
Well, well, what have we here?
And where's the herring?
I eat nothing but herring!
Herring, please!
- Do you know what the difference
is between you and an ox?
- No.
No? I don't know either.
Erik, did you hear my joke?
- I asked him--
- I ask you for a favor, Lasse.
Could you take my place
tonight at the thresher?
- But it's Saturday.
- Yeah, but I want to get a bit of, you know--
- Will ya?
- Yeah, yeah.
No, no, not so fast.
Mm-mmm.
He's got a way with women.
Takes after his father.
Must have been a hell
of a long time ago, Karlsson.
A real good idea, Karna.
You and me. You do like Pelle.
You're always good to the boy.
The three of us staying together.
I bet we'd be real happy.
You're too old, Lasse.
For me, the man has to be dangerous.
You're not dangerous anymore.
I see. I'm sorry.
So, you're fishing for a young one?
You could end up missing
the boat altogether.
I don't believe it.
It's empty already.
- Hey, Lasse. Do us a favor!
- Yeah, Lasse. Run down and
get us some more brandy.
If you want brandy,
you can go and get it.
Just because someone is old--
There used to be respect!
"Lasse," the girls would say.
"I want Lasse Karlsson."
Even though you were married,
the girls were chasing you.
And there was respect.
Papa!
I'm sorry.
Yeah, I had hoped, when we left Sweden,
that there would be...
some money left over,
enough to buy a little house.
Then I could find
the right lady to--
to take care of us.
We could have had coffee under the sheets
some Sunday morning, Pelle.
What if we were to run?
Run to somewhere far?
Run away? Uh, but think
of the authorities.
- I don't want to become an outlaw.
- I mean, all the way...
- to America!
- America!
Voyage to America, across the ocean!
They don't follow anybody that far.
We'll get away.
What are you doing?
- Stealing eggs. I was hungry.
- For God's sake, tell no one you saw me.
I know who the father is.
You've got to swear
that you'll tell no one.
His father--
If he found out,
I don't know what he would--
And to his father,
a Swedish woman...
an immigrant worker, is--
For the love of God,
you're not going to tell anyone?
I've got to hide in here
until my time comes.
Understand?
Pelle!
Come here!
What were you doing
in the hen-house?
- Stealing eggs.
- Come.
Bend.
Pelle, can I have that coin?
My krone?
You're really out of your head.
I need it for when I go to America.
I'll pay you two kroners
for it when I'm big and grown.
You're not gonna grow.
Your body's unnatural.
I could be real popular
in a circus or a carnival.
- A carnival?
- Yes, as a monster.
I'll get filthy rich.
What about-- What about if I let you beat me
with nettles a hundred times?
A hundred good ones.
How would that be?
Me beat you?
- What do you say?
- You couldn't take it.
Is it a deal?
Are you ready?
No more!
- No more!
- If you don't wanna get paid--
You hit too hard.
- Well, make up your mind.
- The money first.
Can you tell us anything about
Adam and Eve and the serpent?
Well? We're all waiting.
Have you never heard
of Adam and Eve and the serpent?
Haven't you been listening in class?
What did the serpent promise
Adam and Eve if they disobeyed God...
and ate of the forbidden fruit?
You don't know what
the serpent promised them.
The snake in the garden
convinced them that they would--
would indeed be equal
to Almighty God.
I do not see how we can let you
continue in this class...
when it is clear that you
do not understand the basic tenets.
Are his parents here?
His parents are not in attendance.
You may take your seat.
- Next.
- Pelle.
Perhaps you can tell us
what God said to the serpent.
Our Lord said that--
that--
God said that the serpent
must crawl on its belly.
"Thou shalt crawl on thy belly. "
- And does it still do so?
- Yes.
- It hasn't any limbs.
- And can you tell me what a limb is?
A limb is, uh--
- A hand, for example.
- Mm-hmm. Very good.
And can you tells us what distinguishes
all limbs from other parts of the body?
A limb moves independently
from the rest of the body.
Can you provide the others
in the class with an example?
Ears?
Oh? Can you move your ears?
- Yeah.
- I should really like to see that.
You see, it was
your ears that saved you.
I always told you
to use your ears.
Rud!
Rud! Rud!
Rud, you idiot! Come back!
You'll never go to heaven!
You'll never see
your grandma in heaven!
You can have my knife
if you come back!
You can't do this, Rud!
No! No!
Rud!
Anna!
Don't touch those stones!
Your infant is lying there,
buried in the bloody earth under the stone.
Yes, he is! Anna killed your child,
and now she's in prison.
The crime is on my soul.
I murdered the child.
Natural fathers wouldn't do that.
Lasse would never
have done that to me.
Why don't you go away
and leave me be?
I see him at night!
A bonfire, you can see for miles!
His soul burns
on the rocks at night.
You mustn't say that!
You mustn't lie
in front of God!
The boy is lying up in the churchyard
in consecrated ground.
His soul is not up there.
It's under the rocks.
Come see at midnight,
see him burn!
And the reason is
he got baptized too late.
God won't let him into heaven!
Nils!
Who has gone out there
into the arms of death?
It's Nils. He went out with the line.
Hold steady! Take her around!
Let's get him over there!
With your young eyes,
can you see Nils?
♪ Blessed is the Earth ♪
♪  Blessed is our Lord in Heaven ♪
♪ And so, it's the angels ♪
He was a good son.
Did everything for me.
He was... a fine boy.
Not an evil word did he
ever say to me.
Not once.
Even though I denied him his love...
he was my son.
And my only one.
May he find peace now.
He had so little of it here on Earth.
He sacrificed his life to save others.
Perhaps now, in heaven,
he'll be welcome.
Come on, Erik!
Only a couple inches more
and you win the brandy!
- He won the brandy!
When will you drink it?
The foreman says you have to work tonight!
Listen, tonight I don't work.
He'll do it without Erik.
I'm goin' out
and have some fun.
- - That foreman can't keep me in
when I feel like havin' fun.
- Can I come with you?
- No.
Not now, Pelle.
Not now. In one year.
We can cross the ocean
when the snow starts to melt.
The two of us go out
into the great world.
First America, then Australia...
then China!
Out there's a whole world, Pelle!
Where do you think
you're going, you lazy--
They said there was work
for you at the supper! Erik!
You had to hear.
What do you call this?
I must have the flu.
Head's spinnin' like a top!
That sounds serious.
We'd better have a look at you.
Well, well, look at this.
All dressed up in your Sunday clothes.
What is it, your burial outfit?
Were you going out to
buy yourself a grave?
It's about time we got
you into the ground.
You're already beginning to smell.
I ain't dead yet.
And I don't smell any worse
than some people I know.
You're nothing but a lazy,
complaining troublemaker!
- And I'm sick of you!
- Go ahead. Do it again.
- Sick of you bellyaching!
- Go on. Hit me again...
in front of all these witnesses.
We'll make a report
to the authorities.
Get up and get to work.
One of these days, you'll see more
of the authorities than you want to see.
The foreman says--
He says you're making too much noise!
What did you say?
God, you're homely.
- The foreman says--
- You must talk a little louder. I can't hear!
- You're making-- You're making too much noise.
- He said to tell you.
- Too much noise, little chicken?
I think you should help us
make too much noise.
Come on.
Sing us a little song.
I wonder if he sings
like a chicken as well.
You tell the foreman to run
his own errands...
and not to send
his favorite whelp!
Scoot! Run!
- Scoot!
Run to the fat foreman!
- I ain't dead yet.
And not this, Ole Olsen.
- Where are you going, Erik?
- To rest.
- What's that word?
- Rest.
No, you can't rest now.
You get back at the job.
- You're after me again?
- After you?
What makes you think that?
The others are resting.
Yes, they get a rest
because they've earned it.
You get back on the job.
- I'm always the one you pick on.
- Oh!
Are your feelings hurt?
That's for being so clever.
For all the kind words
that you say...
while my back is turned.
Just what the hell do you think
you're getting paid for?
Are you so thick, so stupid...
that you think
you're on a paid vacation?
Final order--you get back
to work right now...
stinking Swedish bum!
All right. You get turned
into the authorities.
And you won't get a single krone.
Not a krone, Erik.
You're all done.
Lasse! Hurry, they're coming!
Dear Jesus. They're gonna do it.
I'm gonna--
Put him in the cellar.
You heard me!
Put him in the cellar!
The rest of you go back to work.
- Come inside to get warm.
- Oh, thank you.
It's a strong wind.
And then Mama died. And now she's lying
back home in the cemetery...
in Tomelilla.
So your father's a widower.
That's the word.
The sea is hard.
My husband went to sea a year ago.
And I've been like a widow since.
Has he drowned?
I can't say.
I haven't received an omen.
It's been a year that
she's been living all alone.
That's what she said.
That's a long time out here.
A long time.
Now you told her Mama was dead.
Yes, of course you did, yes.
This is all that's left
of your mother's things, Pelle.
Now, though, it's all or nothing.
Pelle-- Pelle, could you...
visit Mrs. Olsen
tomorrow after school?
And you can say I sent... my--
my thanks for taking you
in and treating you so well.
I had an omen last night.
In fact, you could call it
a form of vision.
I dreamt there was a huge dog
standing there, next to the bed.
His coat was dripping wet.
And I knew it was the ship's dog
with a message for me.
I got out of bed...
and outside my window...
I saw a ship go down
with all hands.
Then I saw my husband
rise to heaven.
He was dripping wet
with salt water.
I realized immediately...
that the dog was
an omen from him.
- Who's there?
- It's Pelle's father.
Lasse Karlsson.
- You're Pelle's father?
- Yeah. Uh--
He's very young, your son.
- Uh, yeah.
- Come.
Sit.
Yeah, Pelle was a... latecomer,
you might say.
But I can still do
a good man's work, though.
In every way.
- Drink.
- Yeah.
Thanks for the drink.
Now, I must be on my way.
Eat. Eat.
That's how you get to know
something about a man.
- You walked a long way.
- Yeah, I just came by to thank
you for being kind to Pelle.
Now, now. That's enough talk.
Go ahead. Please.
You must have been
a good wife to your husband.
Yeah. That's true enough.
Everything and anything he desired,
when he was on dry land.
But he was ungrateful.
You become tired of that.
I don't think my wife would have
spoken that way of me.
There's lots to do in a house like this,
if there's a man to help.
Yeah. Yeah.
There's only one cow.
But one could become two.
I'm only a poor laborer
by comparison.
But we have decent clothes, both of us.
And I have a good pair of hands.
And you'd not be afraid
to use them, would you?
Not in the least.
Nor afraid of, uh...
hot coffee in bed
on Sunday mornings either.
Then I think I should have a kiss.
Yeah, you should.
Yep.
We'll hope for happiness and blessings
on the three of us.
You already like the boy.
You might as well stay
for the night.
I must be back before
the cows wake up.
And Pelle's all alone.
Pelle! Lying out here.
Come on. Come on.
Everything is arranged.
We'll have a home and
a woman to take care of us.
Mrs. Olsen. You'll be happy.
And maybe we'll get coffee
in bed on Sunday mornings even.
Come. Come.
"Give us this day our daily bread...
and forgive us our--"
- Do you have the Bible stories there?
- Mmm.
Does it tell the one about the man...
whose sons pulled down his pants
and showed his--
- Noah?
- Yeah, that's it-- Noah.
- Old man Noah.
- "And lead us not--"
- What did he drink, old man Noah?
- Wine.
Wine. Then he must
have been a rich man.
Old Noah.
And then there was the one--
the one who was so devilish clever.
- Now, what was his name?
- Laban.
Laban. Yeah, of course.
That's who it was-- Laban.
Laban. Laban was the name.
How did it go?
How many wives
could a man have then?
All right,
I won't bother you anymore.
The great prophets.
What were they called?
Let's see. Isaiah.
There was Daniel and--
I remember them now.
I remember the prophets, Pelle.
- if you want, you can test me
on the great prophets.
- Let's hear them.
Don't you think you had better start reading?
Otherwise, you could lose track.
There were only four great ones.
isaiah--
- Come on, Papa.
- Yeah.
First, I need to concentrate.
They were--
They were Isaiah, Daniel--
I had them a minute ago.
Now where did they get to?
They were Isaiah, Daniel--
Ah, it's not working today, Pelle.
- You forget things when you get old.
- isaiah...
Daniel--
isaiah, Daniel, Jesus--
- Ah, not Jesus. How did Jesus get in there?
- isaiah...
- Yeah, their names were devilish
back in Bible days.
- Daniel--
- You could hardly get your tongue around them.
- Try, Papa.
- Isaiah...
- Daniel...
- Ezekiel...
- Ezekiel and...
-Jeremiah!
Isaiah, Daniel...
Ezekiel, Jeremiah.
Will you never grow up?
Don't be afraid. He wouldn't hurt a fly.
- Don't forget the bottles.
- That's the last thing I'd forget.
Erik, are you coming?
Are you coming to the fair, Erik?
Come, Erik.
Come on.
Come on, Erik.
- isn't Erik coming?
He can't stay home without
the foreman to look after him.
But he won't go.
Can't you go inside and get him?
You're the only one he listens to.
Come on, Erik. Let's go.
We're going to the fair.
Isaiah, Daniel,
Ezekiel and Jeremiah.
Those were really the days.
Just think, two wives to care for you, Pelle.
You've got one to cook the food,
the other one does all the mending and sewing.
Beautiful teeth for sale.
Smile, and the world
will smile back at you.
Pelle.
Here.
What's going on here?
I'm leaving, Auntie. I need to go.
But, Signe, is there a problem?
If so, I'm sure we can solve it.
It's the isolation
from all my friends.
At heart, I'm a city girl,
so-- so I'm returning.
But you said nothing, Signe.
I-- I know I should've
told you before this.
I'm so disappointed.
I don't understand.
It's just that I miss Copenhagen.
But I thought--
Kongstrup and I were so sure
you were happy here.
Dear Signe.
I don't really know
what else to say, Auntie.
I've made my decision.
But so suddenly.
If you had mentioned it before,
I could understand.
I'm sorry.
Why didn't you--
Is there a reason why you don't look me
in the eye? Should I know something?
Signe?
But how are you going to manage?
- Well, you see--
- Who'll buy your ticket?
Actually, Kongstrup has offered
to help me and see me to the boat.
Oh, thank God
that I don't have to worry.
If I could only understand you.
You will return here for a visit?
I'd hoped you would take over
and run the farm in our old age.
Kongstrup too wanted it.
Signe, dearest, don't cry.
It's not as serious as all that.
I want you to feel free to visit us--
visit us anytime that you want.
Kongstrup!
Kongstrup, come out
and talk to me!
I'm here to collect
the money, Kongstrup!
Kongstrup!
Look who it is.
Let me say hello to you.
Too proud to say hello, are ya?
Do you think that you're better?
Is that because you're going away to have
your bastard son on the other side of the sea...
when I had mine
in a turnip patch?
But it was the same old whore-monger,
wasn't it, Signe?
The same old whore-monger
as ever! Signe?
Signe?
Signe, would you go and tell
the whore-monger that I need the money?
- His wife would give me the evil eye!
- Come here, you!
- I warned you!
- Let me go!
Let me go! Kongstrup, come out
and help an old sweetheart!
Let me go! Let me go!
- Out! Don't come back!
- Let me go!
Why do you stare?
- If I have to search for you once more--
- Sorry, ma'am.
That beats me.
I would have thought that only death
could end such grief so quickly.
She must have
an iron grip on herself.
Wake up and fetch
the doctor, quick!
- What is it, Papa?
- Oh, dear Jesus. It must be something bad.
Karna, what is it?
- It's so awful!
- What happened?
- The missus cut him!
- What-- What are you saying? What did--
What happened?
- Cut him. The missus cut him.
- What?
- He's bleeding to death! Get some help!
-Jesus.
It's fun. Hey!
Psst!
Mr. Friese, could you tell us
what this means?
"Pelle Karlsson is the young cuckoo
in Mrs. Olsen's nest. "
- Isn't she married to a sailor?
- She's Captain Olsen's wife.
Your father doesn't care
about that, does he?
A Swede doesn't care if a woman
is married or not, does he, Pelle?
- Pelle's father is a real old goat.
- Watch out for the lech's son.
Old Swedish goats like
married women the best.
- Stop. Stop.
- What's it like in the nest, Pelle?
Please stop.
- Smash this kid!
- Here's one from Captain Olsen!
Just you wait, Pelle.
We're really gonna get you.
Pelle?
I've been thinking a lot
about the situation.
You and I, we are welcome
at Mrs. Olsen's.
We could move right in.
I mean, I-- I know
it's against the law...
to move in with a woman
who is wife to another.
But... to be--
You know, I...
want some comfort.
We could make it look
like the two of us are lodgers.
She-- She could
sew you new clothes.
Wouldn't it be nice
to have new underwear?
If-- If I did move in with Mrs. Olsen,
you'd move there too.
You'd come with me.
It's a lot easier for you.
Your life is all ahead of you.
Your whole future
to make something happen.
I need someone
to take care of me.
I'll run away
if you go and stay there.
You have the gall
to say that to me?
Just look what you are doing. Someone else
will have to fill in the holes with cow dung...
so the foreman
doesn't find you out.
You stop that right now, Pelle!
You'd better watch out I don't make
a carving of you and Mrs. Olsen in bed.
You're getting a little too big for your--
Come back here!
You'd better watch out...
I don't set the foreman on ya!
Pelle!
Could you go by Mrs. Olsen's
on the way home from school?
These are some things
she promised to mend for us.
And be sure to tell her
I'll come by this evening.
Why don't you marry her, Papa,
like others do?
Really, I will.
I will, Pelle, but...
you've got to deal
with a country's authority.
Mrs. Olsen needs a death certificate
from the government.
But soon, we'll have coffee in bed.
Well, it's Mrs. Olsen's young cuckoo.
Let's see how tough
you are, Pelle.
- into the sea with him!
- Run, cuckoo bird!
Run, you cuckoo bird!
- Come on, Pelle! Let's see you dance!
- Papa's little Pelle!
- Papa's little cuckoo bird!
- Cuckoo! Cuckoo! Cuckoo!
Cuckoo! Cuckoo! Cuckoo!
What's the little cuckoo bird
going to do now?
Go back to Sweden,
you whore-master’s son!
- Fly away, cuckoo bird!
- Away! Away!
Away! Away! Away! Away!
- Run away!
- Run!
- Run! Run!
Run!
Look, it's Captain Olsen!
You're home already.
Pa, Mrs. Olsen's husband
has come home.
First they steal one feather,
then another...
till you are standing there like a...
plucked hen in the shed.
I was only looking for a home...
to spend my old age in.
Found someone,
thought I was free.
Jesus.
Jesus, help.
What the hell
is the point of crying?
I want you to meet
my new sweetheart.
Kiss her, Pelle.
Oh, yeah, I forgot.
You don't do such things.
You're too fine.
Well, it doesn't help anything
to go around whimpering.
Oh.
- Oh!
- Papa!
Frisky, isn't she?
She's a little devil.
You're crying.
Did someone do something to you?
Tell them that your father is Lasse--
Lasse Karlsson from Tomelilla.
It's all right.
Your father is here...
and your father can stand
on his own two feet.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I'm going up there
to the big house.
Now the bastard's going to have
to answer for all these years.
We're gonna have a little talk
with the missus.
I'm not going to
let you go out there!
Erik? Psst, Erik.
Erik?
Spring is coming.
That's what Papa says.
And when spring gets here,
you'll be...
a free man.
Think of it.
Then we can leave this awful place...
and go out and conquer the world.
Pelle...
what is it they all talk about?
I wouldn't know.
You haven't heard anything?
Do you think I wanna go to class
and have them laugh at me some more?
Forgive a sinner, Jesus,
that abused your gift.
But it's difficult not to
when your heart is broken.
Pelle, I promise
you'll never again see me...
the way I was yesterday.
Then would you agree
to go to school?
Tomorrow, Pelle? Huh?
Because if you don't, Pelle...
then they will force you.
There'll be a lot of trouble
with the authority.
All right?
Say "yes."
Ten times 10 is 100.
100 times 10 is 1000.
100 divided by 10 is 10.
1000 divided by 10 is 100.
Mr. Friese?
- He's asleep.
- Mr. Friese?
It's time.
Sir, it's time to go home.
Hey, Pelle, where's your father?
Running around?
I'm sure my father would be
happy to marry him off...
as Mrs. Olsen's plaything.
Help! Papa, help!
You scoundrel!
How dare you hit my son!
You're going to hear
from the authorities about this!
Oh, Pelle, Pelle, Pelle. That was about
the worst thing you could do...
was tackle the minister's son.
The town minister has power.
I have very little doubt
he deserved it, sure...
but I wish you hadn't done it.
- What did the boy do to you?
- He said you could get married...
and be Mrs. Olsen's plaything.
He did? He did?
I tell you, he's a lucky kid
I wasn't there!
I'd tear his guts out,
the little swine!
- Do you feel avenged?
- No, not really.
His father came and rescued him before
I could give him what he really deserved.
Revenge.
Yeah. But it's a bad situation.
And you're not gonna
apologize, are you?
Uh, no, no, naturally not.
It would go a lot easier
if you would. No, no, no.
You just gotta twist and turn...
same as the eel in that frying pan.
Good day.
We are very sorry to bother you.
We have no other choice
but to ask for--
to ask for your help.
Blow your nose properly, Pelle.
- Good day.
We are very sorry to bother you.
Very sorry.
Yeah.
- There's probably no one home.
-Just go in.
- We can't stand here all day.
- Really?
Well, you go first then if you think
you can handle this better, Pelle.
All right.
All right. Uh-- Uh--
It's like this.
I hope that the proprietor
won't be angry with us--
that he won't be--
won't be angry.
Uh, you must forgive us...
for coming about something
that has nothing to do with the farm.
But, uh--
When the father's sins
are visited on the son--
Well, that's, uh-- that's, uh--
Why are you standing?
Please, sit down.
- Thank you.
- Why haven't you offered them a seat, dear?
- What is it?
- You need money?
- No.
It's that, uh--
It's just that, uh--
I hope that
you won't be angry, but...
it's the boy.
They're going to send away the boy.
Send him away?
What have you done?
I beat up the minister's son.
And why did you do that?
Because he said
evil things about Lasse.
And what did he say?
He--
He called me, uh--
He called me
Mrs. Olsen's plaything.
- All the boys have been teasing Pelle.
Yeah.
I was, uh...
Mrs. Olsen's sweetheart when everyone
thought she was a widow.
And then the other day, her husband
came home from the sea.
Here.
- So the boy made Pelle furious?
- Yes, unfortunately.
That's-- That's how it is.
With poor wretches,
they're only there to be pecked at.
I prefer the bird who pecks back
and defends his nest...
regardless of his wretchedness.
All right, I'll do what I can.
You needn't worry
about it anymore.
Thank you.
Oh, by the way.
My husband and I decided...
the young assistant to our foreman
will be leaving us come spring.
We thought that perhaps Pelle
would like to become his replacement.
Thank you.
Say " thank you."
Did you see how well I let the missus know
that you would like to take his place?
She thought
she thought of it herself.
You recognize these.
They're a bit big, but don't worry.
- We'll stuff them with paper.
- Try them on, Pelle.
I'll get some boot wax,
and they'll be like new.
Now, let's have a look at you.
Now, stand up straight.
I want you to stand very, very straight.
Shoulders back, the chin
a little forward, Pelle.
Not like that.
Lift your chin a little.
There. Yeah.
Now, a sharp look in the eye.
The thing is to command
respect for yourself.
The way you stand and the look
in your eye, that's what does it.
Yeah. Let the others labor.
You do the ordering.
"You want the night off?
Clean out the cow dung!"
Oh, Pelle, maybe you'll get to eat
Sunday dinner with the proprietor...
and have your own napkin ring.
It'll have your name on it--
Pelle Karlsson.
And who knows, Pelle?
Maybe one day you'll take over as foreman.
That's why I planted the seed.
I could tell the way
she was thinking. It was perfect.
Erik!
Wait, Erik! Wait for me!
I don't want it.
We must leave here, Papa.
Now.
- It's Karna.
- I got here in time.
I was afraid the foreman
or the missus would see me.
A gift for you.
It's a down quilt.
it'll keep you warm at night...
no matter where in the world
you end up.
Bye, Gabriella.
Bye, Blakka. You be a good girl.
Well, Aspasia,
time to say good-bye to Pelle.
He's going out
to see the world.
Papa?
What is it?
Can't we stay?
You'll have to go
without me, Pelle.
I no longer have
the strength to travel.
I'm too old is the reason.
Too old.
There's no future for old men.
Understand?
We'll make up a bundle for you.
You can have two of my shirts.
Then you will have four.
The one you are wearing is clean.
And, remember, never wear a shirt
for more than two weeks at a time.
Otherwise, you'll get
a bad name, Pelle.
And change your socks
before they wear out.
Keep your clothes clean,
keep your good name...
you'll save half the work
and all the shame.
You can have my boots too.
Well, they are a bit worn.
Oh, yes, here's the Bible.
Your mother said
I was to give it to you...
on the day you went out
into the world.
The next time we see each other,
maybe there'll be a proper home for you, Pelle.
Tell Karna good-bye.
Good-bye, Papa.
Thank you.