Can she see us?
Can you see us?
Take off your pants
and she'll see you.
[in Chukchi]
It will happen soon. I know it.
I am going to die soon.
This summer.
You always say that.
Hey, Lyoshka...
are there any prostitutes in Anadyr?
I think so.
Let's invite one out here.
We can find their numbers online.
I dunno.
She'd have to fly way out here.
Yeah... Five hours here on the plane,
an hour of work,
and then...
another five hours back.
We could ship her in like a cargo.
Are you nuts?
She'd freeze like a dumpling,
and then your dick would freeze too.
Remember that girl we watched?
What was that?
Wait, was that your first time?
You can watch chicks
on a webcam sex chat.
They even show you their tits sometimes.
They have ones from all over.
From Africa and America.
Like, ebony girls, or lesbo action...
So what's that girl's name?
HollySweet999.
You fall for her?
Are you going to watch her again?
Yeah, you've fallen for her.
Oh, it's you.
I'll die tomorrow for sure.
I'm busy tomorrow.
Hi.
How're you doing?
Can you hear me?
You're...
beautiful.
We don't have blondes
like you in my village.
What city are you from?
I'm Lyoshka.
Well, hey there!
You finally made it.
Give me a bigger piece.
I didn't get anything
from the previous hunt.
I was out in the tundra.
Thank you.
Hi.
Let's go to Lavry.
I set up a date with a girl there,
she's expecting us, like.
Wants to get to know us closer.
Well? Wanna come?
Lyoshka, I want you.
If you were in a porno
would you fuck a cow?
Shit, so much for our fucking trip!
What a shit bike.
It's totally dead.
I should get a better cross bike.
Well, it's summer. We won't freeze.
That chick... the one from Lavry
who wants to meet up...
you made her up, right?
Ten years or so ago,
my uncle stole a boat,
sailed across the Bering Strait,
crossed the border,
and made it to Alaska.
From there he walked to the big city.
It's called Teller.
So there you go, five hours –
and a new life, America!
They have skyscrapers
a thousand floors high.
McDonald's and hot chicks
as far as you can see.
America, America!
But you can't go any more,
the border patrol stops people halfway.
So how can I talk to her then?
- To who?
- That chick from the chat.
Dunno. Speak American to her, I guess.
That's where they're all from.
Go on, give her a wave.
Let's talk about boys and girls.
Who is that?
It's... Kolya. Kolya Tanko.
From Provideniya.
He was headed over there,
to Alaska.
He got there in 40 minutes,
crossed the border.
Then the Yankees found him.
He had a harpoon on him.
And they thought... it was a firearm.
They stopped him, started shouting,
"Drop your weapon!"
But he didn't know their language.
They shot him down.
Probably wanted to see America.
He tried.
- Galina! Galina!
- Out of the way, Chukchi!
Who is she?
Some chick my uncle brought in
from the mainland.
Everything's fine!
Don't worry,
things will work out great for you.
You'll have four daughters
and three sons.
You'll go to Moscow.
You'll see the Kremlin,
Red Square, Spasskaya Tower,
with the clock,
and the President.
Hang on, let's check this hand out.
You will have a lot of reindeer.
Well aren't you shy.
Give me a hand?
Don't worry, it's easy.
Don't stand around,
come on over.
Come on.
Don't worry. I don't bite.
See? Nothing scary about it.
Hey, come on.
Go ahead.
No need to be such a baby.
Go for it!
Touch me.
See how warm I am?
Please... I'm so sorry!
Nothing happened between us, anyway.
DETROIT CITY
Hey.
- What are you up to?
- Just watching.
- Watching who?
- HollySweet999.
She showed me everything.
Even her tits.
- Give it to me.
- No.
- Give me the phone.
Whoops! Check it out.
- You've had your fun, now stop it.
- She totally showed me everything.
- Give it back!
- You can have it. For a kiss.
- Fucking give it!
- Come and get it.
Come on, come on,
Kolyan, take him down!
Come on!
Come on, Kolyan, take him down!
Go back to America.
I can't take this.
Hey!
Get up!
Quit flopping!
HolySweet Nine nine.
You're still thinking about her?!
She doesn't exist. She's just virtual.
Millions of people jerk off to her.
I love you...
I love you.
What fucking user?
What user?
Are you with her?!
I know you are, you fucker!
Come on out!
USSR–USA
DITROIT
On the run?
Headed for Alaska?
This is an island,
in the border zone.
Are you... poachers?
I can show you the future,
if you want.
Look, kid: that there is Alaska,
and that... is Chukotka.
America. Russia.
The past. The future.
Take a step:
the past, the future.
Monday. Tuesday.
I killed my friend.
Over some woman?
I have a girlfriend there.
America...
I've had enough.
I am tired of this America already.
Hey bro!
- What's up?
- I'm alright!
- What's with your head?
- You bashed it the fuck in.
- Oh, I forgot!
- Shit, you're stupid.
Don't fucking hit it, it hurts!
Ages since I saw the village.
I thought I killed you.
Mom said I got 5 stitches.
My brain almost leaked out.
Take me to the tundra.
I'm going to die today.
I'm hungry.
I won't die today.
Take me home.