ROME OPEN CITY
The incidents and characters herein,
though based on the tragic and heroic events
during the nine months of Nazi occupation, are fictional.
Any resemblance to actual incidents and characters is purely coincidental.
Soar high, Red Eagle
O'er swamp and sand
O'er dark pine forests
All hail my Brandenburg homeland
Dear God!
I'm coming!
- Engineer Giorgio Manfredi. - He's not here.
Where is he?
We don't know. He doesn't always sleep here.
Where does he go?
I don't know. You know these young bachelors.
Of course. Which is his room?
That way.
Search the house.
- Does he have many visitors? - Before, but not now.
Of course.
- How many other lodgers here? - Two.
- Where's the phone? - End of the hallway.
Stop! I'll answer that!
Is Giorgio there?
Of course. Mr. Manfredi. Who is this?
- A friend of his. - What friend?
Who's this?
Who was that woman?
How should I know? I didn't see her.
- Find anything? - No, nothing.
- And that door? - That's the terrace.
- Keep calm. - Dear God!
- Who lives there? - That's the Spanish embassy.
The city will be divided into 14 sectors.
The Schroder Plan, implemented in various European cities,
will permit dragnet operations on a grand scale
with minimum force.
Come in.
Sergeant Bauer phoned, sir.
They didn't find the person in question.
No? That's odd.
The landlady and servant were there. Shall we bring them in?
No, that's not necessary. Thank you.
Bad news?
Someone missed an appointment.
Someone important?
I hope so.
You know them?
No. Who are they?
He's an engineer by the name of Manfredi.
That name's come to our attention.
Seems he's a military leader of the National Liberation Committee.
I have good reason to believe it's the same man.
How did you spot him?
I found him while sitting right here at this desk.
Every evening I take a long stroll through Rome
without leaving this office.
I'm fond of pictures that catch people unaware.
One comes across such interesting people.
For example, not long ago I came across Mr. Manfredi
and his little girlfriend.
I thought, "I've seen this man somewhere."
Look at this group, for example.
Second from the left.
I received these from Berlin.
I'm not mistaken, am I?
Of course not. It's the same person.
How annoying!
Excuse me.
What's all that noise?
Forgive me, Major. We're interrogating that professor -
Fine, but keep him quiet.
How these Italians scream!
Indeed.
And who's the girl?
A certain Marina Mari, a cabaret performer.
Yes, I've seen her before. Pretty girl.
Very pretty.
Take it easy!
I can't take anymore.
- What's going on? - They stormed the bakery.
- What about you? - Unfortunately I'm in uniform.
- Sergeant! - What do they want?
I can't do anything! This is a riot!
I'm helpless. - But just four ounces a day -
The dirty rat even had pastries. Look!
And they said there was no flour!
Agostino, go get some.
I can't. I'm a sexton. I'd go to hell.
Then wait for your pastries in heaven.
Put those down!
Pina, this is crazy. In your condition?
Should I just starve to death?
Sergeant, help!
Go hang yourself!
I'll see you home.
Bread!
- Here we are. - Thanks.
Shall I carry it up? It's heavy.
This way it'll be lighter.
I really shouldn't, but I've been starving.
Pina, you think these Americans really exist?
It looks that way.
- How about eggs for 16 lire? - Forget it.
How dare you talk black market in my presence!
Sergeant, save your breath.
See you.
- Who are you looking for? - Does Francesco the printer live here?
- Yes, but he's out. - Know where he went?
That's his business, not mine.
- Excuse me, but who are you? - What's it to you?
- You must be Pina. - How did you know?
Francesco always talks about you.
- So you're - - A friend.
Stupid me! I thought you were police!
What can I do for you? - I need to get in his apartment.
I'll get the key.
Sorry. I couldn't find it.
This way.
It's a mess, but -
It doesn't matter.
Listen, do you know Don Pietro, the parish priest?
I'd like to speak to him.
- I'll go get him. - No, not you.
- I'll send my boy. - Better.
Wait for me in there.
Marcello!
What?
- Come down a minute. - I can't.
- Go get Don Pietro, quick. - I'm busy!
I said come down here!
I've told you not to go up to Romoletto's. It's dangerous.
Go get Don Pietro. - What do I tell him?
To come here right away. Now move it.
And don't fool around on the way.
- Don Pietro will be here shortly. - Thanks.
We stormed a bakery this morning.
Second one this week.
How are the women?
Some know why they're doing it,
but most just grab all the bread they can.
This morning someone filched some shoes and a scale.
I'd like to know who filched my stockings!
Excuse me.
I bet you did - Mr. Manfredi!
What are you doing here? Looking for me?
That's right.
I met him on the stairs and let him in -
You could have let me know!
It doesn't matter. I just had a favor to ask.
You're fine just like that. Excuse us.
You see Marina, right? - Yes, at the cabaret.
Please tell her I can't see her for a few days.
I'll phone if I can.
- Anything else? - No, nothing else.
Then good-bye now.
- Does she live with you? - She's my sister.
Surprised, huh?
I wonder what lies she's told you about where she lives.
She's ashamed of us "starving workers." Says she's an artist.
But I wouldn't trade places with her.
Not because she's bad. She's just stupid.
But how do you know Laura?
Sorry. I'm being nosy.
No, she's a good friend of a girl I know.
- Marina? - You know her?
Since she was a baby!
Her mother was a concierge near my father's tinsmith shop.
She and Laura grew up together.
But please don't tell Marina
what I said.
Don't worry. I won't be seeing her again.
Why?
I just feel it's time to end it. It's gone on too long anyway.
- Have you known her long? - Four months.
I'd just arrived in Rome. She used to eat in a certain restaurant.
One day the air-raid alarm went off, and everyone ran.
Just she and I were left.
She just laughed. Wasn't scared at all.
- And you fell in love. - It happens.
Yes, it does.
But she's not the woman for me.
Perhaps if I'd met her when she was younger.
A woman can change, especially when she's in love.
Who told you she's in love?
Why shouldn't she be?
Heavens, I didn't even offer you coffee.
It's no bother. It'll only take a moment.
Mind you, "coffee" in name only.
Stop all this ruckus!
I told you before: No rough stuff.
Watch out, Don Pietro!
Well, well. It's a miracle to see you here.
- My mother sent me. - She's smart. It'll do you good.
Don Pietro, let me finish.
She says to come quickly. It's important.
- What? - I don't know. She acted mysterious.
But I think someone's in Francesco's apartment.
Very well. Let's go.
Gilberto.
You, out of the way.
Agostino will be here soon. You referee.
And behave yourselves.
Here!
Come here. Why are you always running off?
Why don't you come around anymore?
- This is no time for catechism. - What are you saying?
You priests can't understand,
but we have to close ranks against the common enemy.
Who tells you these things?
Romoletto.
Romoletto?
Don Pietro, please don't tell anyone.
Here comes Purgatory.
Don Pietro.
- What have you got there? - I've been shopping.
What a load of bread! Was that your whole ration book?
Not even one coupon.
Why all this bread?
- They were celebrating this morning. - What?
I don't know what holiday. Even the baker didn't know.
Excuse me. I have to go.
- What holiday could it be? - I don't understand.
I hope my mother knew about it.
Here you go.
It's not very good, but at least it's hot. Drink up.
Thanks. Francesco says you two are getting married.
The wedding's a little late... in my condition.
But we set a date a long time ago and had to keep postponing it.
- When is it? - Tomorrow.
- I'll need to get you a present. - Heavens no!
It's just a wartime wedding. Don Pietro says a few words and it's over.
- You're marrying in the church? - Yes.
Francesco didn't want to, but I told him
better Don Pietro, who's at least one of our own,
then some Fascist at city hall, don't you think?
In a way you're right.
The truth is, I believe in God.
Do you work?
I used to. In a fuse factory.
But they threw us out. The Germans are taking everything.
It must be Don Pietro.
Hello, Don Pietro.
Excuse me. I'll be across the hall.
- Thanks for coming. - Don't mention it.
- What's this? - Who's in there?
None of your business. Go get some water. Hurry up.
- I have to talk to you. - Come on.
There are 500 men in the hills above Tagliacozzo.
They're good men. We can't abandon them.
One of them will be waiting at 6:00 on the Tiburtine bridge.
I'd better not go, because I've been denounced.
Besides, the curfew's at 5:00 now.
I see.
I'll go. - I knew you would.
- What's the message? - No message.
It's money from the military committee.
Is it too much to ask?
No, too little, even, for those sacrificing their lives.
How will I recognize him?
He'll whistle that song "Morning in Florence."
But of course you wouldn't know it. - How's it go?
Like this.
Everyone's singing it.
Hello, Father.
How can I help you?
Would you have a statue of St. Anthony the Abbot?
Sorry, but there's not much demand for those now.
But I have a St. Roch.
Thanks, but I'm not interested.
Not interested in a saint like St. Roch?
Step inside.
Come and see.
It's a beauty too. - Let's have a look.
I'll be going.
Remember to stop by Chiurazzi's.
I'll give you a good price.
I need to speak to Francesco.
The man with the tight shoes sent me.
Wait a moment.
Come in, Father. They're waiting for you.
Down these stairs.
Don Pietro, what's happened?
Nothing serious, thank heavens, but it might have been.
The SS were at Manfredi's last night. - We know. Where is he now?
At your place.
Pina let him in. He'll be staying a few days.
He gave me this note.
I wanted to send him to the Passionist monks. He'd be safer there.
But he said he'd be too isolated.
It's true.
But he's in greater danger now that he's been denounced.
Yes, Father, but if our few men all hid in monasteries -
- I understand. - Allow me. This is our editor.
Pleased to meet you.
Same here. I've heard a lot about you.
That's not good for my modesty
or my health.
We appreciate all you've done for us.
It's my duty to help those in need.
Step into my office?
Here you are, Father.
Manfredi said it would be money.
There's not much to read in those books.
What do you mean?
Is it all like that? - A thousand pages.
- One million lire. - Precisely.
Who is it?
It's me. Open up.
- Guess who I saw this morning. - I don't care.
- Manfredi. He came to see me. - You? Where?
At my place.
What did he want?
He said he can't see you for a few days
and that he'll call if necessary.
Nothing else?
He didn't explain?
No, and I didn't ask.
I was in my bathrobe and curlers.
Aren't you going to change? You're on soon.
How did he know where you live?
Good question. You must have told him.
I never told him.
Well, I certainly didn't tell him.
I don't like people knowing where I live.
Speaking of which, I really can't stay there any longer.
Mind if I stay with you until I find another room?
Of course not. I've told you many times.
You're a sweetheart.
- What are you looking for? - A cigarette.
- I'll get you one. - Fine!
Thanks.
- When did he come by? - Who?
Giorgio.
Early this morning. I was getting dressed.
Miss Mari, you're on.
I don't understand. Are you in love with him or not?
He's nice, I'll give you that.
Would you kindly stay out of it?
It's nothing to me, as long as you're happy.
You feel sick?
No, it's nothing.
Marina... again? You know it's bad for you.
That's stupid.
Lots of things are bad for us, but we do them anyway.
I'm coming.
Good evening. How are you?
Fine, and you? How beautiful you look tonight!
But you're always so chic.
- I'll be going. - Ah, Laura.
Try and hurry, or the boss will be mad.
- I have to go. - Yes, dear.
Did you find some?
You're a darling!
He has no schedule anymore - always in and out.
And these days, when you shouldn't even stick your nose out the window.
He's always out and about.
- He must have a good reason. - Let's hope so.
Agostino, I'm surprised at you.
Come now.
You think I don't know you were behind that hubbub at the bakery today?
- Me? - Yes!
You think I'm an idiot? I know all about it.
And if you keep up these antics, you're all headed for trouble.
- Let's hope not. - Yes, let's.
Cabbage soup. - I can tell.
What time is it? The curfew's at 5:00.
Let's see. It's 4:30.
- I better be going. - You want to leave a message?
I wanted to talk to Don Pietro,
but I'll do it tomorrow before the wedding.
Ah, finally.
Good evening, Don Pietro.
I've told you not to cook on the heater.
And cabbage, no less.
Agostino, don't answer back.
- It's either the stove or the heater. - Fine.
More books! No money for food, and you keep buying books.
Hands off. I'm taking them to San Lorenzo.
You're going out again? The curfew's in 20 minutes.
It doesn't matter. Doctors and priests can still be out.
- And midwives too. - What?
I read it on the posters.
But you could get shot in the dark with these thugs around.
Don Pietro, I came... for confession.
I have to go out. Maybe tomorrow morning?
Fine. I'll walk with you a ways now.
Let me carry your package.
We can't have a priest carrying a package.
Besides, I'm already carrying so much.
Come on, it's getting late.
Bye, Agostino. - And stop worrying.
If this war isn't over soon, I'll go crazy!
Are you the priest here? Don Pietro Pellegrini?
I'd like to speak to you.
Please...
I'll be going. Here's your package.
I wonder what he wants. - Who knows?
Perhaps you should...
wait for me over there.
Have a seat.
Step outside a moment.
Please.
What is it?
From Don Saverio Derisi,
the priest in Minturno.
You mustn't think I'm a coward.
I can't take any more!
Don't lose heart. I'll try to help you.
Where have you come from?
Cassino. It's a living hell there!
What did he want? No, I'll carry it.
He wanted information.
Just the sight of those guys and I -
My last confession was so long ago that I'm almost ashamed.
No, let me talk.
I've led a bad life. I've done so much I shouldn't have.
You think I'm not ashamed to be married in my condition?
But you'd never understand.
There are things you do without thinking,
that don't feel like you're doing wrong.
I was so in love,
and he was so good, so decent.
I know he could have found someone better,
a young girl,
not a penniless widow with a child
who had to sell everything just to get by.
And life just keeps getting harder.
How will we ever forget all this suffering, anxiety, and fear?
Doesn't Christ see us?
So many people ask me that: "Doesn't Christ see us?"
But are we sure we haven't deserved this scourge?
Are we sure we've always lived according to the Lord's laws?
People never think of changing their ways,
but when the piper must be paid, they despair and ask,
"Doesn't the Lord see us? Doesn't he take pity on us?"
Yes, he does,
but we have so much to be forgiven for,
and for that we must pray and forgive many things.
You're right, but how do we forgive?
I see those guys and I want to smash their faces in.
You're right. I mean... give me that package.
It's getting late. Good-bye, Pina.
She came looking for help.
The Gestapo had hauled in her fiance.
"Don't worry. I'll take care of it," I told her.
What a pair of legs!
Halt! Hands up!
I have a permit.
Printer.
Says so right there.
All right. Go home quickly.
Auf Wiedersehen, Captain, and thanks.
Good night. See you tomorrow - don't forget.
Francesco, you scared me.
I'm a bit late. They insisted on seeing me home.
Nothing wrong with that, is there?
Hi, Francesco.
- You got away, eh? - This time at least,
with the landlady and Nannina's help.
You know they tore the place apart this morning?
A waste of time. There was nothing there.
- Pina let you in? - Yes, she was very kind.
- What do you think? - You're smart to marry her.
At first she took me for a cop and gave me hell.
I can imagine.
Did you know Don Pietro met Gino? - Really? I'm glad.
What did he say about my matter?
He's worried. You were to meet the old man today.
- When did he get in? - Last night. But you can't see him.
Gino says you have to drop all contact with central for a while.
True, but to stop short after months of work!
How'd they catch on to me? We have to find out what they know.
We'll try, but it won't be easy with the Gestapo.
If it was the Italian police -
Let's hope Don Pietro met our friend from Tagliacozzo.
Let's hope so.
Ah, I brought you our newspaper.
Came out all right, didn't it?
How many copies?
Twelve thousand.
That's Pina.
Hi. How are you?
I'm worried about Marcello. He's disappeared.
I've searched the whole building.
- He's probably at Romoletto's. - He's not.
And two other boys are missing too.
Where could they have gone?
- I'm afraid they've gone out. - After curfew?
Well done. I'm proud of you.
Let's step on it, boys.
Let's wait for Otello.
Good night.
So you're still alive! Well, I'll kill you now!
If I had a father like that, I'd show him.
Good night.
You little devil! Coming home at this hour!
We'd better go in one at a time.
You're right. You go first.
You little monsters!
They're back.
Trouble-maker!
I'll tan your hide! Give me heart failure, will you?
I'm going over for a minute or there'll be murder.
- Look how they look! - Where were you?
- At Romoletto's. - No, you weren't!
- We were downstairs. - Where?
- Can't you see they're lying? - I'll kill him!
No, I'll slap 'em silly!
Get to bed, you two.
Calm down. - I've had it with them!
They're just kids.
I can't get a moment's peace here! I work all day!
Some work!
What was that? Speak clearly!
You'd better just go back to bed.
Can't I talk in my own home?
This is my home. Go talk in your own room.
We pay for kitchen privileges. - Laura, forget it.
Forget it? I'm fed up with living in this zoo!
Then get out!
Do you people have to fight every night?
If she doesn't leave, one of these days I'll -
Elide, is it ready yet?
Oh! It's probably burned!
That little witch!
Come here.
It's a surprise.
Elide's baking a cake for your wedding tomorrow.
I hope you two won't quarrel at the last minute,
because we're going to have a real feast!
- That's his greatest worry. - Off to bed. Good night.
Turn out the light, will ya?
We fixed 'em good, eh?
You never take me along.
You're a woman!
So? Can't women be heroes too?
Sure, but Romoletto says
that women always mean trouble.
You still awake?
Under the covers!
Go to sleep.
Can't sleep?
I'm not sleepy.
Where did you boys go with Romoletto?
I can't tell you.
Not even me?
No, it's a secret.
Then you're right.
You mustn't tell anyone.
Good night.
Hey...
What?
Do I really start calling you "papa" tomorrow?
If you want.
I do. I really like you.
What's wrong?
I had a fight with my sister.
Again?
She wants to leave.
Says she won't even come to the wedding.
That's just talk.
No, she was serious. She's packing her bags.
She'll change her mind tomorrow.
I'm so tired!
There now.
Go on and cry. Come in for a while.
- No, he's in there. - So? He's a friend.
I've wanted to talk with you alone for so long.
Come here.
Let's sit down here,
like the very first time we talked. Remember?
You knocked on my door with a look on your face -
You drove a nail in the wall and knocked my mirror down.
Luckily it didn't break.
"Who do you think you are? King of the universe?"
You were so rude to me.
In two months you never once said hello on the stairs.
It's been two years now.
How long ago that seems now.
And how things have changed, though we were already at war then.
Everyone foolishly thought it would be over quickly
and that we'd only see it on newsreels.
When is it going to end?
Sometimes I just can't go on.
This winter feels like it will never end.
It will end, Pina...
and spring will come again,
more beautiful than ever, because we'll be free.
We have to believe it and want it.
I can feel these things inside,
but I can't explain them.
Manfredi could.
He's an educated man who's been to college and traveled.
He can really talk well.
But I think it's like this:
We mustn't be afraid now or in the future,
because we're on the just path. Understand, Pina?
We're fighting for something that has to be,
that can't help coming.
The road may be long and hard,
but we'll get there, and we'll see a better world.
And our children especially will see it -
Marcello and the one on the way.
That's why you mustn't ever be afraid,
whatever happens.
Right?
But I'm never afraid.
Hello?
Ah, Miss Mari. No one's seen him.
He hasn't at least called or sent someone over?
Nannina, tell me the truth.
You know something. You know where he is.
I swear I don't.
If I did, I'd tell you.
Let's hope not.
Good night.
The dummy, asking for information over the phone.
The Gestapo will get us all!
Come in.
The chief of police, sir.
Show him in.
Dear friend, you've come at the right moment.
Something very interesting has turned up.
Our Mr. Manfredi was spotted this morning around Prenestino.
And just a while ago,
a tank car of gasoline was blown up in the rail yard in the same area.
My dear major, my news is even more sensational.
I spent the afternoon in our records office,
and I too had a very interesting encounter.
Fantastic!
"Ferraris, Luigi.
Born in Turin, October 3, 1906.
Arrested in Bologna on February 4, 1928.
Sentenced to 12 years for conspiring against the state.
Escaped during transport. Spotted in Paris and Marseille."
Luigi Ferraris.
You've outdone me. - Oh, I would never presume.
In any case, the important thing still remains: To nab him.
Don't worry. He won't get away from me.
- Shall I see to it? - I forbid you!
I mean...
not that I don't trust your methods, but I prefer to do it myself.
Excuse me.
Ingrid.
Good evening. How are you?
My dear lady.
Thanks for the flowers and coffee.
I see you're corrupting my staff,
but you're forgiven.
He's made a very interesting discovery.
Really?
Fantastic!
The time for talk is over. We must act immediately.
Yes. Leave it to me.
Hello.
Hello, children.
Praised be Jesus Christ.
Forever and ever.
But you're always the last... to praise him.
Who is it?
Police!
Morning, Sergeant.
Wait a moment. I'm dressing.
Then with your permission, we'll pay our respects to your intended.
The Germans and Fascists are surrounding the building.
Let's go.
Get everybody out of the building, now!
They're surrounding the building.
Get inside.
Go up and bring everyone down, from every floor.
You go that way and do the same.
Tell them they're to go upstairs and bring everyone down immediately.
You three go that way and bring everybody down.
You men go that way and do the same.
Be strict with these tenants.
What are you doing? Come here.
Come here! What's he looking for?
What are you doing here?
I'm here on duty, but I have to go. I'm a sergeant.
Nonsense. He stays here.
You must stay here.
Marcello!
- What is it? - The Germans and Fascists!
- Where? - In our building.
- Let's go, boys. - Hold it there a moment.
It's the Germans!
- You stay here. I'll go. - We have to go too!
I said to stay here.
But Romoletto has bombs in the attic.
- Quick, to the railroad! - The Germans are downstairs.
- Francesco? - He's getting rid of the stuff.
Don't worry. They won't find him.
- Don't tell Pina. - Don't worry.
- What are you doing here? - Getting my things.
Get outside. We'll see that no one touches them.
How stupid of me not to think of that.
Hurry. Over there.
- Where's Francesco? - Don't worry. He's safe.
Those bastards! They're even dragging the sick down.
Grandfather wouldn't come down. What'll they do to him?
Nothing. Don't worry. Go over there.
My boy!
Giorgio!
Just look at that!
- Where was he hiding? - I don't know.
They took him away. What'll they do to him?
No men in this building? Nonsense!
Where are all the men?
You hear? Where are the men?
How should I know? I'm not the doorman.
What does he want?
- Where are you going? - To comfort a sick man.
The parish priest.
Don't bother.
We brought everyone down for a little fresh air.
Impossible. A man that sick? I have to go up.
Hold it!
Ah, finally. The poor man was begging for you.
He's probably dead by now. Go on.
Wait! They brought everyone down.
No, not this paralyzed old man.
Hurry, Father.
Some service! They used to be as prompt as firemen.
Romoletto, open up!
It's me and Don Pietro!
Go away!
Open up!
Go away, or you'll be blown up with me.
I said to open up!
- What are you doing? - I'll kill them all!
You want to kill us all, you lunatic?
Hold it there!
Help, Antonio!
Let me go!
What floor is this dying man on?
I don't know. Third or fourth.
I'll go have a look. I'm a bit of a doctor myself.
I'll go too.
No, I don't like your face.
No one's here.
Let's try the next floor.
The door!
Are you crazy? What are you doing here?
I'm perfectly fine!
Lie back down and pretend you're sick.
I'm fine! I'll live to be 100!
The SS are coming! The Germans!
To hell with the Germans, and the Fascists too -
Hand me that.
Look in there.
Come on, wake up.
Give me that.
Come on.
You really let him have it!
It's all right.
You have pretty eyes.
Bastard!
Get ready.
Watch for when they round the turn.
Aim at the drivers.
Flavio, us bring meat.
- Where? - Here.
What good is this? I'm an innkeeper, not a butcher.
Us slaughter.
Yes, you people specialize in that.
Good evening, Mr. Manfredi.
Go right in.
Evening, sir. Miss Mari's waiting for you.
Let's leave.
Giorgio, finally! I've looked everywhere for you.
I hoped you'd come here. What's happened?
Nothing. Why?
What could have happened? I don't understand.
At your place -
Allow me to introduce a friend. Sit down, Francesco.
It's a pleasure. Marina.
The SS were looking for you? - Who said so?
Your concierge. But why?
Maybe 'cause I'm an officer.
- Where are you staying now? - We'll stay with a friend tonight.
Why not my place?
- No. - Why?
I wouldn't impose, and he's with me.
He can take the sofa. You'll be very comfortable.
- Spaghetti for three? - We'll talk later.
- Ration books, please. - I don't have one.
I'll give him a coupon for you.
- What else? - I'll take care of these folks.
- They arrested Mezzetti. - When?
At 6:00 this morning. The painter told me.
If we don't lay low for a while, they'll nab us all.
You planned to stay there, right?
Someone here talked.
Poor creatures.
There's always an American station playing jazz at this hour.
Shall we have a little drink, boys?
This liqueur was a gift.
It'll warm us up.
Do you feel ill?
You have a fever. He's burning up.
I'll make up your bed. - Don't go to any bother.
Chin up, Francesco.
Help me, Giorgio.
You'll see. You'll be very comfortable.
I'll get you an aspirin when you're in bed.
Hand me that blanket, please.
You have to be careful. There's plenty of flu going around.
It's all there's plenty of these days!
Who can that be at this hour?
Who is it?
- Marina, it's me. - Oh, it's you.
Hello, sweetie. You see, I did come!
Fritz didn't want to let me go -
Are you drunk?
A wee bit.
Then go straight to bed.
Who's in there? You got company?
Oh, the engineer!
Laura, go to bed!
I'm not gonna eat him!
Francesco, what are you doing here?
Pina kicked you out on your wedding night!
I think Marina's right. Put her to bed.
Come on.
What long faces! What a welcome!
I should have stayed with Fritz. I'm going to tell Pina.
Go to bed. I'll get you some aspirin.
I fought with my sister. I'm never going back.
- Marina. - Come in.
Don't look!
I came to get aspirin.
There should be some in the drawer.
That idiot was just what we needed.
What do we do now? Where will you sleep?
Don't worry. I'll be fine in an armchair.
You'll be cold and uncomfortable.
What a shame.
Hello?
Oh, it's you. Good evening.
How are you, sweetheart?
I've been waiting for you to call.
You're not alone? - What about him?
Have you seen him?
Is he there?
Oh, it's Laura.
She came to stay with me for a few days.
Yes, of course.
All right.
We'll talk tomorrow morning.
Good night.
- Why's this in your purse? - What?
The dentist gave me that for that bad tooth pain, remember?
No, I don't.
Sure you do. This tooth.
I had to use it to kill the pain.
- And it still hurts? - No, that was a long time ago.
But you carry it around just in case.
I planned to take it back to the dentist.
Ah, that explains everything.
- What are you doing? - We'll take it back together.
Stop joking! Give me that!
Here.
You might lose it.
Then I'd be in a real mess. It's so expensive.
Why that look?
You don't think -
I don't think anything, and you're your own boss.
I don't own you. Who am I, anyway?
Just one guy who passed through your life for a moment.
- You mean "one of the many." - I didn't say that.
But you thought it.
Yes, I've had lovers.
Of course. What was I supposed to do?
How do you think I bought all this furniture, my clothes, everything?
With my pay?
It's barely enough for stockings and cigarettes.
I've gotten by like every other woman.
That's life. - Life is what we want it to be.
Words!
Life is filthy and brutal.
I know what poverty is, and it scares me.
Sure, I could have married a streetcar driver
and be starving to death today - me, my children, and him.
Poor Marina.
You think happiness means
a fancy apartment, nice clothes, a maid,
and rich lovers?
If you'd really loved me, you'd have changed me.
But you're just like all the others - no, worse.
At least they don't preach to me.
You're right. Forgive me.
So you had another fight... for a change.
You were eavesdropping, of course.
No, but I heard.
You hear everything here.
We'll go see Don Pietro tomorrow. He offered to hide me
in a monastery.
No, I could never do that.
I have to work harder than ever now.
She's dead.
I understand.
But you're upset right now.
You might act rashly and do more harm than good.
Don't be afraid that time will run out.
It'll be a long fight.
Our battle's barely begun.
I brought you some aspirin.
Good night.
What?
Maybe Manfredi's right. We're real dopes.
Be quiet and go to sleep.
- A man's here to see you. - Show him in.
Come in.
- Hello, Don Pietro. - I was expecting you.
I prepared your ID card.
"Giovanni Episcopo."
You made me two years younger. Thanks.
Who's he? - The Austrian. Didn't Francesco tell you?
A good man.
This gentleman will be coming with us.
Nice to meet you.
I spoke with the prior of the monastery.
He's expecting us. - Where's Francesco?
In the courtyard with Marcello.
We'd better hurry. Hand me my...
After you.
I'll be back late.
When will you stop getting mixed up in these things?
You and the boy go right to bed after dinner.
Who can sleep? Don Pietro?
To feed the boy I'll need...
Oh, right.
Here. That'll be enough.
- You've got nothing left. - Yes, I do.
Sure you do.
We won't see each other for a little while.
But I'll come back, and we'll always be together.
- Let's go. - I'm coming.
You might be cold. Mama gave me this.
Stop! Hands up! Nobody move!
Get in the car!
Get going!
Go on.
The information was accurate.
Well done.
Good girl.
You like it?
Try it on.
Go on, darling.
Magnificent!
Take a look.
- Did they arrest him? - Yes.
What will they do to him?
Nothing bad.
We need certain information.
Once he provides it, we'll set him free.
- And if he doesn't? - Don't be silly.
Don't worry.
He'll talk.
- And if he doesn't? - Why wouldn't he?
You're right. Why wouldn't he?
- You love him? - Me?
I don't love anyone.
Why so mean to me tonight?
Let me leave.
No, you're staying here with me.
No, no more! Let me leave!
Why?
What have I done?
What number?
Forty.
Here.
Go on!
Are you hurt?
- My glasses. - They're broken.
Doesn't matter.
It's all my fault. They must have been tailing me.
On the contrary.
They've probably been watching me for a long time.
I shouldn't have had you come to the church.
Quiet! The walls have ears.
Let 'em listen. We have nothing to tell.
Right, Don Pietro? - Of course.
We have nothing to tell.
Hear that?
We'll scream like that too!
Take it easy.
This was found at the priest's residence, sir.
And these are the prisoners' documents - all forged, of course.
- You searched the priest's rooms? - Yes, and the sacristy too.
That wasn't smart.
There was only a sexton and a young boy there, sir.
They were so scared that I'm sure they won't talk.
Rest assured, they'll talk. Thanks.
Straighten up here.
Aren't you afraid?
Yes, very afraid, but I feel very calm too.
Strange, isn't it? I don't know why, but I -
I understand.
You're both crazy!
Listen to me.
I know you must have something to hide.
Lives depend on your silence.
You think you can withstand their torture.
But you don't know.
They turn even heroes into cowards.
We're not heroes,
but they'll never find out anything, I assure you.
- What time is it? - 8:30, sir.
These men must talk before the curfew is up.
The rebels must not learn of their arrest.
We have ten hours.
Listen, Don Pietro.
I don't know if we'll see each other again,
but thanks for all you've done for me, for all of us.
No, let me finish. I must tell you the truth.
I'm not who you think I am -
Listen.
They're coming.
I beg you, don't betray me!
You!
Krammer, put out the light.
Come in.
Please.
What's your name?
Giovanni Episcopo.
Right.
"Born in Bari. Merchant."
What do you sell? - Oil and wine.
Oil and wine! Splendid!
Listen, Mr. Episcopo...
if I had time to waste,
I'd love to discuss your business with you.
But I'm pressed for time, and I regard you very highly,
so I'll make you an offer.
I know all about you:
Your real name and past political activity.
As for the present, I know from my informers
that you're a leader of the National Liberation Committee
and in contact with Badoglio's men.
I absolutely must learn the details of this organization,
and you're just the man to tell me about it.
You say you know who I am
and my past and present activities.
Then why make this offer?
Think I'd suddenly turn traitor?
I know you've made the same offer,
possibly in this very room, to Italian generals -
"Badoglio's men," as you call them.
And I know they paid for their loyalty and silence with their lives.
I hope I prove equal to them.
I'm sorry to see you refuse such a reasonable offer.
But I must say I expected it.
You Italians, no matter your party, have a weakness for rhetoric.
But I'm sure we'll come to an agreement before dawn.
Cigarette?
Come now. A cigarette won't make you talk.
There are so many strange rumors about the Gestapo.
Krammer, take him away.
Bring in the priest.
You!
Be calm, my son.
Try to pray.
We found these materials in your rooms.
You clearly aim to harm the Reich and its armed forces.
That wasn't exactly my aim.
Then what would you call a man who not only provides
refuge and forged documents
to Italians plotting attacks on our soldiers
but even shelters German deserters?
A man who humbly seeks to practice charity.
He's a traitor who must punished
subject to the military law of the Reich.
God will judge.
Listen to me carefully.
Your friend Episcopo heads a military organization
of which you too have detailed knowledge.
If you talk,
or persuade your friend to do the same,
you'll have merely done your duty as priest and citizen.
I'll tell you why.
These men plotting to sabotage German armed forces
are violating the rights of an occupying power
guaranteed by international treaties.
They are therefore defectors
subject to military justice. Is that clear?
Your words have moved me deeply.
Finally!
Krammer...
take his statement.
- There's just one problem. - What?
Personally I have nothing to say. I know nothing.
What little I know I learned in the confessional,
and those secrets must die with me. It's our vow.
I'm not interested in your vow!
But someone else is, someone higher than you... and me.
Then persuade your friend to talk.
I don't think he has the information you seek.
You'd have me believe that you don't know
what he really does, who he really is?
I only know he's a man in need of my modest help.
Really? Then I'll tell you who he is.
He's a subversive, an atheist - your enemy!
I am a Catholic priest.
I believe that anyone fighting for justice and liberty
walks in the ways of the Lord,
and the ways of the Lord are infinite.
I hope you're not going to preach to me!
That's not my intention.
I have no time to lose. Do you refuse to talk?
And you won't even try to persuade your companion?
You could save him from suffering
that you can't even imagine.
I can imagine it far better than you think.
But there'd be no point.
And if he is who you say,
he wouldn't be easily persuaded, would he?
Don't worry. He'll talk.
I don't think so. He won't talk.
- Really? - He won't talk.
I'll pray for him.
You won't get much credit for that from your heavenly father!
This will take a while.
Come get me as soon as there's any news.
Come in.
The deserter hanged himself, sir.
That idiot!
- Who's winning? - Same as always.
- Strenuous evening? - Not very...
but interesting.
Really? How so?
I have a fellow who must talk before morning,
and an Italian priest who claims the fellow won't
because he's praying for him.
- And if he doesn't talk? - Ridiculous.
If he won't talk no matter what?
That would mean an Italian is as good as a German...
that there's no difference
between the blood of a slave race and that of a master race.
What would be the sense of our struggle?
Twenty-five years ago I led execution squads in France.
I was a young officer then...
and I too believed that we Germans were a master race.
But the French patriots chose to die rather than talk.
We Germans refuse to realize that people want to be free.
- Hartmann, you're drunk! - Yes, I am.
I drink every night to forget.
But instead I see more and more clearly.
All we're really good at
is killing, killing, killing!
We've strewn all of Europe with corpses,
and from their graves rises up an unquenchable hatred.
Hatred... hatred everywhere!
That hatred will devour us. There's no hope.
Enough!
We'll all die without the slightest hope.
I forbid you to continue!
Without hope.
You hear me? You forget that you are
a German officer!
- Did he talk? - No, sir.
Wendel says he's never seen one so stubborn.
The man's gone completely numb.
What should we do now, sir?
- Well? - It's impossible, sir.
We have to let him regain some strength.
Impossible! It's too late for that.
Shall we try psychological methods, sir?
Are you crazy? He must talk now.
Syringe.
Mr. Ferraris, as I said before, I admire you greatly,
and I do appreciate this proof of your courage
and spirit of sacrifice.
But you must understand: This can't go on.
You are a Communist.
Your party has formed a pact with reactionary forces.
You're all working together against us now.
But tomorrow, when Rome is occupied -
or "liberated," as you call it -
will these monarchist officers still be your allies?
I offer you the solution to this problem.
Give me the names of Badoglio's generals.
Help me arrest them,
and I guarantee your release
and immunity for the men in your party.
Well, Mr. Ferraris?
Cursed dog!
Keep at him till the end!
How's it going?
I told you it wouldn't be so easy.
A cigarette.
The priest, quick!
Look, priest! Satisfied now?
This is your Christian charity.
This is your love for your brother in Christ.
You preferred to see him like this rather than talk.
But don't think you'll save yourself, you hypocrite,
or your accomplices either. You'll die a traitor's death.
We'll destroy you all,
to the last man!
You didn't talk.
It is finished.
You tried to destroy his soul, but you only destroyed his body!
Curse you all!
You'll be trampled in the dust like worms!
My God...
what have I said?
Forgive me, Lord.
Out!
Take the priest back!
Everybody out, now!
Stupid Italians!
Damn it! We failed.
That damned priest got me flustered.
I told you it wouldn't be easy.
You're always right.
The report, sir?
Ah, yes. "Cause of death:
Heart attack."
Yes, sir. And the young woman?
That's up to the lady.
Lock her up a while and then -
Come, my dear. I need a stiff drink.
Sir, what name shall I put down?
Manfredi or Ferraris?
Giovanni Episcopo.
Else we create another martyr, and they already have plenty.
Just a moment.
For next time.
We are a master race...
- What time do you have? - 8:14.
- Exactly. They're late. - Yes.
- Cigarette? - Thanks.
A match.
Positions!
Get ready.
Attention!
Your hat.
Come. Be brave.
Oh, it's not hard to die a good death.
What's hard is to live a good life.
Fire!
God, forgive them...
End this now!