GERMANY YEAR ZERO
DEDICATED TO THE MEMORY
OF MY SON ROMANO
The Russian sector had jam yesterday,
and the Yanks had margarine.
So they'll slap honey
on bread for us. As always.
I'm sick and tired of it all.
In that case,
jump in that grave.
Enough talk about being tired.
Didn't I say 6. 5 x 5 x 2 feet?
We're not digging for potatoes here.
That kid isn't pulling his weight!
- What's he doing here anyway?
- How old are you?
- Fifteen.
- He's lying!
If he's 13, I'll eat my hat.
He's only 12.
He goes to school with my boy.
- Is that true?
- Leave me alone!
Where's your work permit?
In my bag.
I'm sure it's forged.
These scamps will try anything.
You need a work permit
to work here, kid.
I want a piece too.
Get lost.
Go on, scram.
Leave that coal alone,
you rascal.
Just wait till I get
my hands on you.
What's going on?
It’s the man
from the power company.
You went over by 62 kilowatts.
- I knew it.
- There are 10 of us living here.
Five separate household’s.
That’s no excuse.
You can expect a steep fine.
- Got any cigarettes?
- I gave them all away.
These are my last.
- What about you?
- No.
- Did you bring back anything?
- Just some coal.
all right. I'll carry the excess
over to next month.
This is not to happen again.
Last week it was the gas,
now the electricity.
Next you'll all be
stumbling in the dark.
We need stricter rules.
From now on, no hot water.
We can't run around like pigs.
I always use cold water.
Nobody can say I'm dirty.
Can I still use
my hairdryer, Papa?
Keep quiet.
I'll sort it out with the Kohlers.
Let him talk.
Don't do anything stupid.
- Everything okay?
- Yes.
all that fuss with their father -
tea, hot-water bottles,
hot compresses.
This can't go on.
Don't forget he's a sick man.
Sick! We're all sick.
No one has it any better.
I know, but -
Easy for you to say. You have
no idea what we went through.
- Everything okay?
- Yes, don't worry.
What was all that about?
They read the meter.
Too much power.
- So they're cutting off the power?
- We talked him out of it.
You got all dirty again.
Did you get the level 2 card?
No, they found out I wasn't 15.
That’s easy to see.
I knew that would happen.
Actually, I'm glad it did.
That's no work
for a 13-year-oId boy.
It would have meant more to eat.
For Karl-Heinz too.
You hear that...
Karl-Heinz?
You understand that
your brother is shouldering
the entire burden
of our existence by himself?
And you?
What do you do?
You go on hiding.
You didn't even register
and get a ration card.
How can four people get by
on only three food cards?
We can't afford
the black market.
We've sold everything.
I'd do anything for you,
anything within
my feeble power...
but in my condition -
Just think what madness it is,
what you're doing.
What could
possibly happen to you?
I won't kick the bucket
in a POW camp.
I've had enough.
I can't go on.
But I showed you the newspaper,
and you heard it on the radio.
Ex-military don't have
to turn themselves in now.
You just have to register
with the police, like everyone else.
And when they find out
I fought to the very end
and what regiment I was in,
you think they'll let me go?
That was war. You were doing
your duty as a soldier.
They can't hold that against you.
Easy for you to say.
It's not your life on the line.
Papa, you have no idea.
You haven't been out there.
It's just logic.
Has anyone caused us
any trouble up to now?
Fine! If you'll take
the responsibility,
I'll turn myself in right now.
No, Karl-Heinz!
Stay here.
I'll find something,
and so will Eva.
Just give us a little time.
Of course, Edmund.
We'll manage somehow.
I have to go see
Mr. Rademacher.
He has something for me.
I'll be right back.
It's always worked out so far.
Father, you'll be
more comfy like this.
You and I have to talk.
- Fine.
But not here.
Come to my room.
So that person sees me, right?
- She's harmless.
- Harmless!
Sure, the so-called
"victims of Fascism. "
Then come to the bathroom.
No one will see us there.
See if anyone's out there.
No, there's no one there.
Come on.
I've kept my mouth shut
because I didn't want to quarrel
in Father's presence.
You know his condition.
We mustn't get him agitated.
I didn't start anything.
I'm happy to be left alone.
- Because you're a coward.
- Maybe.
And horribly selfish.
You don't care where the food
comes from, as long as it's there.
I didn't make Edmund go to work.
No, you don't make
anyone do anything,
and yet here you are,
hungry and thirsty.
You don't care where I go at night
as long as I bring home cigarettes.
Do I smoke them?
No, but you know they provide
the bare necessities.
Should I admire you for that?
all the girls do that these days.
- And more.
- You see?
You want me to become
a whore for you?
Sorry, I didn't mean it.
We're both on edge.
But just look at our situation.
We get more desperate every day.
- You needn't tell me.
We just can't let Edmund -
I know that.
Don't you think I worry about it?
But you all think
only of yourselves.
You've forgotten
what I went through all those years.
You're wrong.
We know that you almost
died of thirst near Tobruk
and nearly
froze to death in Russia.
I don't want to suffer anymore.
I'd rather end it all.
No, Karl-Heinz.
You survived it all,
and you'll go on living.
Ah, here you are, Gina.
Come along.
Mommy, I want to stay here.
Your girl’s no bother.
- You're working in this light?
- We must save electricity.
Not when you really need it.
Can I give you a hand?
Thanks, I'm fine.
- You're suspicious of me too.
- No.
- But the others are, aren't they?
- I think so.
Why?
Because I was abroad
for so long?
- No, it's your political views.
- That's ridiculous.
The Rademachers hate me
because I'm taking up a room.
- Are we moving again?
- No. Now hush.
You room with Miss KohIer.
They're nice, simple people.
What have they got against me?
I'm sure it's because their son -
Come on, Gina.
I'll pick out some linens for you.
You can make diapers
out of them.
She's always very helpful.
I don't believe
in help from strangers.
Everyone has to help
themselves these days.
I'm very understanding, my boy.
I'm no monster.
But there's a limit.
I've told you that before.
I didn't know what kind
of help you were offering.
Can't I get something for you?
You know
I hate the black market.
Or swap something?
That's what the official
Exchange Office is for.
They swindle us every time.
Give him the scale.
My scale?
How will I check my weight?
It's not the first thing
we've had to sacrifice, my dear.
Go get the scale.
- all right.
How much should I ask for it?
- What can we get for it, Mother?
- I'd think 200 marks.
Far too little. At least 300.
Exactly the price
of a pound of butter.
Edmund - Oh, pardon me.
Your food's getting cold.
Hurry. I still want to go out.
- I'll be right there.
- Excuse me.
Miss Rademacher...
may I please see the scale?
It's an outrage!
That woman has no shame!
Just like that hussy Blanke.
To think our daughter
has to mix with such people.
A typical sign of the times.
What have you got against my sister?
Why are you always groaning about us?
Be quiet.
Take the scale, and don't come back
with less than 300 marks.
Got that?
Yes, Mr. Rademacher.
I'll come for it tomorrow.
- Eva?
- What is it?
Where are you going?
- Out.
- Why are you going out?
- I go out every night.
- Why?
To take my mind off things.
- Ready to go?
- I'm coming.
They won't wait for us, you know.
Yes, I know.
I don't want you
to go out every night.
What's gotten into you
all of a sudden?
What are you thinking?
Come, my child.
Look me in the eye.
Now go to bed...
and don't worry about a thing.
- Cigarette, mademoiselle?
- Thank you.
Garcon, two cognacs.
- Merci. Not right now. Later.
- all right.
Jean, still in Berlin?
That's right, my friend.
Excuse me a moment?
He's nice, your Frenchman.
Yes, very nice.
You'd better hurry
and seize this opportunity.
I'm fine just enjoying
myself a bit.
I don't think you understand
how to really handle men.
- I can't do it.
- Don't be so stupid, child.
You might catch one for keeps.
I told you, I can't do it.
I'm just too stupid.
Having a good time?
Come to the Bavarina with us?
I'll walk with you a ways,
but then I'm going home.
Young people
just don't feel like working.
All they think about
is the black market.
- You know the Lehmann boy?
- Working in construction?
"Working"?
If you ask what he's doing,
he says, "I don't know.
I start tomorrow. "
Hurry, Hilde.
There'll be nothing left.
A few grams won't matter.
But if there's nothing at home -
Hey, get in line!
It's getting harder and harder
with three hungry men in the house.
I don't know what to make.
Butter was 200 marks
a pound yesterday.
My father's pension is 70 marks
a month, if he even gets it.
And you go out
for four or five cigarettes.
It's 20 marks.
So you can buy
five pounds of potatoes?
You're crazy. Trust me.
Maybe, but don't you see?
I just can't help it.
- Because of Helmut?
- Yes.
Don't you think he understands
your situation, like all POWs?
He won't be back
for a long time.
He'll certainly understand.
It's not about understanding.
The two of us -
How can I explain?
At first it was just
some innocent postcards.
Then I heard nothing
for a long time,
until suddenly a letter came
from the POW camp.
He wrote to me
because he had no one else,
and he had to write to someone.
He had nothing to hold on to
except me.
You understand?
He lives just waiting
for my letters,
and I have someone
I can turn to too.
But you have your family.
- I do what I can for them.
- It's not very much.
I know, but l don't have
the courage to do more.
You have to find the courage.
And after 10 shots of schnapps,
you do, believe me.
Why are you hanging
around here?
Leave me alone, will you?
Hey, kids,
what's going on here?
How much for the scale?
- Three hundred marks.
For that chunk of rust?
Are you crazy?
That chunk of rust works just fine.
Get on and weigh yourself.
Really? Fine, then.
I'll give you something good for it.
Take it easy.
I'm not running off with it.
Just wait a minute.
I'll give you this.
- What is it?
- Top-quality canned meat.
- That's all?
Stop your screeching.
I'll throw in another can.
I'm in a generous mood.
Now get lost.
- That's not enough. I need more!
- Shut your trap.
You're such a dumb ass!
Hello.
- You were in my class once.
- Yes, Mr. Henning.
See, I have a good memory.
What's your name again?
Edmund Kohler.
That's right.
Edmund KohIer.
You've grown up to be a handsome,
strapping young man.
How's your father doing?
My father's very sick.
I see.
You have
a big brother too, right?
Yes, he was in the war.
Now he's at home.
So he's unemployed,
just like me.
- Aren't you a teacher anymore?
- No.
The authorities and l
didn't see eye to eye
about educating today's youth.
Tell me, my young Edmund,
what are you doing here anyway?
Nothing much.
- Keep me company for a while.
- I'd be happy to.
I'm always happy to see
a former pupil again.
Hey, Henning.
You didn't even recognize me.
- Sure I did.
Dirty work, eh?
- Work? Slavery.
A fine situation we're in.
Before, we were still men.
National Socialists.
Now we're just Nazis.
The streetcar's coming.
- all the best.
- See you.
all clear.
- Did you have to shovel too?
- You bet. To clear up the rubble.
- And work on the rooftops too?
- That too.
My brother was supposed to too,
but he didn't register.
Unfortunately they caught me,
but I got on the sick list.
Remember how I scolded your dad
for that fake certificate
when he tried to keep you
out of the Hitler Youth?
You were very honest
and didn't tell me any fibs.
I should have taken stronger measures,
but I didn't, for your sake.
Here we are.
- Have you always lived here?
- No.
- You just moved?
- Yes, a good friend took me in.
- Ah, there you are.
- Hello, ma'am.
- Well, did you go?
- Yes.
- Nice kid. Who is he?
- One of my former students.
A fine boy.
Did you tell them we sent you?
- Sure.
- And?
I go back tomorrow.
Then we'll probably get the stamp.
Did you bring my nail polish?
Of course.
I hope it's the right color.
Excellent. Take a look.
Now, if you'll...
- Good-bye.
- See you later, my boy.
- You like this color?
- Much too showy.
What would you know
about women's things?
Hello.
- Nice kid. Never seen him before.
- Former student.
Is he around?
- Out on the terrace.
Come on.
Come in, my boy.
Give me your bag.
We'll put it right here.
Now tell me.
What have you got to tell me?
- Nothing.
Sit down.
What are they teaching you about
in school now? Democracy?
I can't really say.
I'm not going right now.
Don't you like your new teachers?
- Sure, but I have to work.
- Why?
There are four of us
and just three ration cards.
Poor boy.
Right, because your brother
didn't register.
Yes, he's in hiding.
And he fought to the very end,
right to the corner of our street.
Don't worry.
We'll find a solution.
I've tried everything.
Today I went for a work permit,
and then I went to work
at the cemetery,
but they threw me out again.
- So you're back, young man?
- Yes, Mr. von Laubnitz.
This is a former student of mine.
- Did you get anywhere?
- I think tomorrow.
- So it's still not decided?
- No.
- The matter must be settled.
- Yes, sir.
My dear little Edmund,
I'd really like to help you.
But you must promise
not to tell anyone.
Understand?
It's nothing really,
but I don't want to attract attention.
I'll give you something
you can sell,
but you must say it's yours,
if anyone asks.
Even in this building, okay?
- Yes, sir.
Go to the chancellery,
understand?
You'll find a bunch of Yanks
or Limeys or other idiots there
that you can palm
this record off on.
Get your bag.
It's a speech by HitIer.
Take the record player along.
You can just say
I lent it to you.
Prove to me
you're a smart boy, all right?
- And what did you get?
- Nothing.
Matches your looks, you idiot.
- And how'd you fare?
- Me? Great.
See you tonight, right?
- Jo and Christi, come here.
- What is it?
Take this little guy
to the chancellery.
He has something to sell.
Make sure he does it right.
He's just a beginner.
- You can count on us.
- Go with them, okay?
When I grow up,
I'm gonna buy a car.
- I can't wait that long.
- Edmund.
Wait here a minute.
Edmund, come quickly.
Hurry.
Here he is.
Yes, you can listen to it.
Hurry up.
- I'm not an express train.
- Don't be such a slowpoke.
... hold the flag high when
the storm rages and thunder strikes.
I am proud to be
the leader of this nation,
not only in happy times,
but especially in hard ones.
I'm happy that in such times
I can once again
give my strength and trust
to the nation,
that I can and must raise up
the entire German people
and tell them, "German people,
set your hearts at rest!
We shall overcome!
Victory awaits us in the end!"
Kids! What a coincidence!
Where have you been?
- At the chancellery.
- So it all worked out?
- Yes, sir.
- How much did you get?
- Two hundred marks.
- Where are they?
- Here.
Here are 10 marks for you.
See?
I take good care of you.
Come see me again soon.
Bye.
- Jo!
- Come on.
Wait here a minute.
- Why do we have to wait?
- Jo's pulling off a job.
- What job?
- Don't ask stupid questions.
If you're so curious,
go after him.
I will.
Jo!
I told you to wait outside.
What are you doing
down here?
- Selling something.
- What?
- This.
- What is it?
Soap.
Soap?
That's why I had to -
Pipe down. You'll see
what you can do with soap.
Now beat it.
You too, silly goose.
This stop Zoologischer Garten!
- Fifty marks.
- I don't have it.
Just take a Look.
- Smell.
- Nice, but too expensive.
For you I'll make it 40.
Come on. Hurry up.
Now you see how
to soap the people up?
No one here?
The gang was supposed to be here.
Wait for me.
I'll see where all Baba's hiding.
- Is he your brother?
- Jo? No.
Don't you live together?
Us? Live together?
I thought you lived together.
We don't live together.
Hey, Jo!
- Hey, sweetie!
- Hands off!
Don't be that way!
- Conceited princess.
- A mattress that dispenses cigarettes.
She's not the only broad
I've been with.
A trainload of potatoes
is coming in tonight.
Crazy!
We'll get ourselves some.
The cops will be there too.
- Jo?
- I know where to find him.
- Hey, Jo.
- What?
will you sell me
a piece of soap?
- Why not?
- How much you want?
Forty smackers.
Forty? I only have 10.
You'll get the rest
tomorrow and the day after.
all right.
Good.
- Now put it away.
- I want to take a Look first.
You dirty dog,
you cheated me!
Good night and sweet dreams.
Where are you going?
I have a rendezvous.
- Where are we anyway?
- Good question.
I live near the AIexanderpIatz.
How do I get home?
No one's making you go home.
- Where am I supposed to sleep?
- There's plenty of room here.
Alone?
With her.
Or don't you like her?
Afraid of girls?
- It's not that.
She's a nice girI,
you dummkopf.
Now get lost, you two.
You gonna keep
all those potatoes yourself?
You can have a few.
Where should I put them?
In here.
That's all?
Where would you put more?
In my bag.
I'll give you more tomorrow.
I promise.
Now good night,
and make each other happy.
You'll see.
It's lots of fun.
Come on.
Jo, listen!
They're gonna really
hit the roof, my boy.
You think so?
Staying out all night
won't go unpunished.
- What should I do?
- You'll have to pay the piper.
I only stayed out
all night because -
You needn't tell me.
Explain it to your sister.
Come on.
Edmund! Finally!
I thought you weren't
coming home.
You gave me such a fright.
You're a horrible boy.
- What's going on?
Nothing. It's just Edmund.
Go back to sleep.
To your room - march!
Where were you the whole night?
I didn't do anything bad,
Eva, honest.
I want to know where you were.
I was getting potatoes.
That's no reason
to stay out all night.
Tomorrow I'll get more.
Look.
Father's awake.
Hear him coughing?
He was very ill last night.
- Does he know?
- Yes.
Yes, Father.
Edmund's here.
Come here.
Closer.
It's not my fault.
The other boys made me -
Save your breath.
I'm not interested in your lies.
You should be ashamed -
so depraved
and corrupted at your age!
He didn't mean any harm, Father.
He was finding us some food.
- I won't eat any of it.
Me neither.
I'd rather starve.
Easy to say.
I'm tired of lying around,
of no use to anyone.
Don't get upset.
I'm sure he won't do it again.
Show how many
potatoes you brought.
And canned meat.
That's not for us.
- Who's it for?
- Mr. Rademacher.
Well? Any luck?
- It's not so easy.
- The main cable has to be in there.
Yes, but it's hard to get at.
And the power company might
easily notice we're tapping it.
No need to worry.
With five households,
it could have been any one of us.
- Here, Mr. Rademacher.
- What do you want?
- I brought canned meat.
- I didn't order any.
- For the scale.
- Where are the 300 marks?
This is all I got for it.
What? You dare bring me this
for my expensive scale?
Canned meat?
You want to poison us all?
- It's not bad.
- Then you take it...
Very kind of you.
... to my wife.
Out with the truth.
Where's the money?
What money?
For the scale.
I bet it's in your pocket.
- How can you accuse me?
- It's perfectly clear.
You're all dying of hunger
and trying to get by at any cost.
First you forced yourself on us.
That was the housing authority.
I'm the one who has to bear it.
We all have to put up
with your father's constant
bellyaching and whimpering.
Why doesn't he just croak?
We'd finally have some peace.
- Where are you going?
- To the bathroom.
Wait. I'll help you.
Thank you, child.
- Your soup is on the stove.
- Close the door.
Want some?
No, Eva warmed it up
especially for you.
How about
an American cigarette?
So Eva can hold it over me?
It's not from Eva.
Don't tell me you bought it.
No, it was a present.
From the boys
you were running around with?
It wasn't the boys.
It was a girl.
- You should be ashamed!
- Everyone else does it.
That's no excuse.
Her name's Christi.
She lost her parents.
She lives in a basement.
She laughed at me
because I don't smoke yet.
She often brings cigarettes
for the other guys.
You should have someone
who'd look after you.
Me? I don't need anyone.
I've had enough of this rotten life.
You mustn't lose courage now.
No, I mustn't.
A soldier can lose everything
but his courage.
But I'm not a soldier anymore.
Now I'm a nobody.
One more mouth to feed.
I'd like to jump out the window!
Come quickly!
Come quickly.
Father had another attack.
I think we should call a doctor.
You hear me?
Yes, but -
I'll get him.
I know where he lives.
Don't worry.
It's nothing serious.
His heart is very weak,
but it's his poor overall condition
that concerns me most.
What should we do?
He needs nourishing food,
with fats and vitamins.
- How can we get that?
- We only have a Level 3 card.
I know. It's the same
sorry state everywhere.
It would be best
to get him to a hospital,
but they're all
full to overflowing.
You think there's any possibility?
They've turned away
worse cases,
but fortunately I have very good
connections at the Health Department.
Hear that, Father?
You're going to the hospital.
You can eat all you want there.
Three meals a day.
Just a minute.
I can't make any promises,
but I'd be surprised
if I can't manage it.
Get well soon. Good-bye.
Happy now, Daddy?
- So you feel better?
- Much better.
Not so loud, Father.
Remember what the doctor said.
You're right.
Someone might hear us.
But you simply can't imagine.
- What?
- all I've had to eat.
First soup,
then meat with fresh vegetables,
and this much milk.
- Really?
- What do you think of that?
I'm happy you have it so good.
And in the evening
there's another hot meal.
You'll see.
You'll be better soon.
Yes. But when I think
of all of you -
Don't worry about us.
As long as you feel better,
that's a comfort for us.
It makes things a little easier,
doesn't it?
- Yes, Father.
- That's what I tell myself too.
- You think Eva's still coming?
- Yes. She just went to the hospital.
- May I smoke?
- Of course.
- Join me?
- Thanks, I just had one.
I'll get you a light.
Where are the matches?
- They're all gone.
- Go get some.
- With no money?
- Go ask Rademacher -
- No need.
My friend has some.
I have to go see her anyway.
Oh, here you are.
- What is it?
I'll tell you later.
I'm going to Hilde's.
all right.
- How's Father?
- He's doing better.
And we're doing worse.
- They cut off the power.
- How can that be?
They found out someone here
was plugging in for free.
- Rademacher suspected us.
- Of course.
That's why he's yelling.
That swindler!
Someone ought to shut his trap.
Lots of big words,
but you just sit around
while everything happens to us.
You starting again?
You must have done
something wrong.
- I only did my duty.
- Then you have nothing to fear.
I inquired again yesterday.
- With that refugee woman?
- No, with an allied officer.
Your moral guides -
allied officers.
Our troubles
don't even bother you.
For a while at least
Father's been in the hospital.
But he comes back tomorrow,
and we have nothing in the house.
I'll find something.
Now I know how.
And that's fine with you?
Let Edmund do the dirty work
and get more and more corrupted?
Leave me alone.
Go dancing with your Yanks.
Mr. Henning!
- What is it?
- Could I speak with you?
Sure. Come back later
or tomorrow.
Listen...
Can't you see I'm busy?
It's about my father.
- Okay, tell me.
- Come with me.
Wait here a minute, okay?
What is it?
My father comes home
from the hospital tomorrow.
And?
We have nothing in the house -
no bread, jam, margarine.
It's all my brother's fault.
What am I supposed to do?
We have to get him
something to eat.
Can't you help?
Tell me what I should do.
I have no idea, my boy.
You have to accept things
as they come.
He's old and weak.
You've tried everything.
You can't fight destiny.
- What if he dies?
- Then he dies.
We all have to sooner or later.
You can't all starve
just to keep him alive.
Mr. von Laubnitz.
- Another of your students?
- No, a little friend.
Come along, my boy.
I have something for you.
I hope you understood.
Stop this now.
You can't change things.
Everything isn't about you
and your selfishness.
Afraid that Daddy will die!
Look at nature.
The weak are destroyed
so that the strong survive.
One must have the courage
to let the weak die.
You have to be clear
about that.
It's all about saving ourselves.
So chin up, okay?
Think about your brother.
Bye.
Father.
Come, my boy. Sit down.
Come closer.
Give me a kiss.
It's so nice of you
to come visit me.
Four days here
have done wonders for me,
and it was easier
on you at home too.
Father, you know -
Let's see how
your temperature is today.
Is the little one your son?
- Yes, my youngest.
A nice boy.
Sit down.
You're not in my way.
Now I'll be a burden
on all of you again.
That's the worst part.
It would be better
if I were dead.
I've often thought
I ought to end my life,
POISON
but I lack the courage.
My existence is nothing but agony.
I know it full well.
For me...
and for all of you.
Here, Father.
We can eat now.
- Shall we move the table?
Yes.
Grab that end, Edmund.
A little further?
Wait, Father. I'll help you.
Just potatoes?
I couldn’t make you any soup.
Why not? The gas
hasn't been shut off, has it?
No, but we have
no more flour or oil.
At least a little tea.
That's all gone too.
My God, why didn't I
just stay in the hospital?
Now I have to lie around here
and be a burden to you again.
The misery of watching
and not being able to help.
Condemned to live.
Lord...
why don't you just let me die?
Don't talk like that, Father.
It would be a relief...
for me and all of you.
We'll manage.
If only Karl-Heinz had registered.
I thought my absence would
make him aware of his responsibility.
What would have happened
if I hadn't come back or I'd died?
Can you tell me that,
Karl-Heinz?
Or would you leave Eva and Edmund
to face their fate alone?
Of course not.
If only your mother were still alive,
but she was taken from me too.
Everything's been taken from me.
Inflation took away my life savings...
and HitIer took away my sons.
I should have rebelled,
but I was too weak,
like so many of my generation.
We saw disaster coming
and did nothing to prevent it.
Only now do we see
the consequences.
Now we're paying for our mistakes.
all of us,
me just as much as you.
We just have
to acknowledge our guilt.
Merely complaining
accomplishes nothing.
Yes, I know, Father.
My days are numbered,
but you're still young.
You can still set
a lot of things right.
Prove you're a man.
Have the courage to register.
You'll see how much easier
it makes life
for you and your family.
Eva and Edmund will be grateful.
And I'll be proud too,
my son.
You'll give me new courage to live.
You'll work.
You'll get a ration card
like everyone else.
So stop putting it off.
Stop living like a hunted animal.
Try to be a man again
who can show his face anywhere.
There's no shame
in accepting one's fate.
You know I was an officer
in World War I.
You think it was just child’s play,
but it was plenty for me.
Back then too we marched
along to waving flags,
conquered half of Europe,
and got all the way to Russia.
It seemed like no power
in the world could oppose us.
Then suddenly the end came.
First defeat...
then revolution.
I wept
when they tore off my epaulets.
No one can accuse me
of not being a good German.
But during all these difficult years,
I longed for just one thing,
and I can confess it to you now:
the collapse of the Third Reich
and defeat.
I don't want to know
how the world would Look
if things had turned out otherwise.
Here, Father.
Tea?
Edmund got it for you.
Tastes odd.
But it's warm,
and that does a man good.
You want some, Karl-Heinz?
No, I got it specially for you.
You're a good boy.
Thank you.
All three of you
are so good to me.
I can be proud
to have children like you.
Misfortune has befallen us,
but it has brought
my children back to me.
Come in.
It's a raid. The police
are searching door to door.
- Good heavens!
- You have to hide.
I'm not hiding anymore.
Open up. Police.
Take it easy.
We have to search the building.
Everything's in order here.
No need to make trouble.
I don't have papers.
Take care of this man.
No papers?
Where are they?
I burned my documents.
Then you must come
to the station.
- May I let my family know?
- Yes, but I'll go with you.
Go ahead.
- It's the rooms behind the kitchen.
- Go ahead, and hurry.
- The power's off.
- Who's the head tenant here?
- I am.
- It's our apartment.
- Who else lives here?
- Just some noisy broads.
- Your occupation?
- Artist.
Yeah, a freeload artist.
In there's a refugee woman
with her child.
- And next to them?
- A very pregnant young woman.
Her husband's in a POW camp.
- We can go.
- Karl-Heinz, stay here.
He didn't do anything.
Then we won't do anything to him.
Come along.
Don't worry.
Nothing will happen to me.
It's my father! Help me!
My father!
What are you screaming about?
My father! He's not moving.
I'm afraid he might be dead.
I'm so afraid.
The old man's dead,
no doubt about it.
Don't be upset, Eva.
In his condition,
it's all for the best.
And just now,
when Karl-Heinz isn't here.
Come. It's better
if you don't stay here.
Has anyone called a doctor?
A doctor can't help him now.
We can only arrange
for a quick burial.
- A coffin will cost a bundle.
- There's always a paper sack.
That's awful.
I don't want to be buried like that.
Don't talk such nonsense.
This doesn't concern you.
Go to your room.
Coffin or no coffin?
The main thing is to get
the body out of here.
Best to put it out on the terrace.
Maybe he had
a contagious disease.
Don't worry. He starved to death.
That's not contagious.
Let's get him outside.
- I'll get his head.
- Good. I've got his legs.
- Mother, lead the way with the light.
- Here we go.
Lucky he's not too heavy.
My poor boy.
Wait.
That should do it.
- What'll happen to his things?
- Good question.
His old torn pajamas
aren't worth anything.
What about the sweater
and woolen socks?
These?
Keep moving.
- I'm back.
- Karl-Heinz!
What is it?
Why are you crying?
- Father's dead.
- Dead?
And all I thought about
was how happy he'd be
to know I was free.
You made his wish come true.
That's the main thing.
Come.
No, this way.
- Poor boy.
- Is he free now?
Yes, completely free.
I took care of everything.
The coffin's been ordered.
It will probably come next week.
It just depends.
- You can't stay here.
- Where can we go?
My place. I have room.
For you too.
- Edmund, pack your things.
- I'm not going with you.
You can't stay here all alone.
There's plenty of room
for me to sleep here.
- Who'll take care of you?
- Let me worry about that.
You forget you're a little boy.
You should have said so earlier, before
I pounded the pavement for all of you.
Edmund!
Leave him alone.
He'll come to his senses.
Damn crater!
I told you to watch your step.
Come on.
I'll show you the way.
Well, good night.
It's awfully close to necrophilia.
You must have been dropped
on your head as a baby!
The buds smell
like a cemetery.
But they're easy to roll.
Man, you just fell
off the turnip truck.
Hash brown potatoes.
Christi!
What is it?
Get outta here!
Looks like you picked up
another trick.
I don't hang around with infants.
Mr. Henning!
- What is it?
- Can I talk to you for a moment?
Of course. Come up.
Come in.
Mr. Henning,
I have to talk to you.
What is it?
You're so pale. What's wrong?
Come sit down.
Now tell me what's wrong.
- I did it.
- Did what?
I killed my father.
- What? You really did?
- You told me to.
Me? I didn't tell you to do
anything, you little monster!
Get up.
How could you do such a thing?
People will find out
you've been coming around here.
I never told you
to do such a thing! Never!
Come on, get up.
Edmund, calm down.
We'll see what we can do.
I really am fond of you,
my boy.
- Can I play with you?
- No, we're playing by ourselves.
- I can show you how to play.
- No.
Come on.
Mr. Rademacher!
Someone should tell the children.
- Where's Edmund?
- I haven't seen him.
Have you seen Edmund?
We'll find him.
My God!