A SHINTOHO-KOI
COPRODUCTION
THE LIFE OF OHARU
Produced by
HIDEO KOI
Screenplay by KENJI MIZOGUCHI
and YOSHIKATA YODA
Based on a Novel by SAIKAKU IHARA
Story Editor ISAMU YOSHII
Cinematography by
YOSHIMI HIRANO
Lighting by KO FUJIBAYASHI
Sound by MASAKAZU KAMIYA
Musical Director ICHIRO SAITO
Production Design HIROSHI MIZUTANI
First Assistant Director
RYOHEI ARAI
Assistant Director
SEIICHIRO UCHIKAWA
Starring
KINUYO TANAKA
HISAKO YAMANE
TOSHIRO MIFUNE
JUKICHI UNO, ICHIRO SUGAI
EITARO SHINDO, AKIRA OOIZUMI
MASAO SHIMIZU, DAISUKE KATO
TORANOSUKE OGAWA, EIJIRO YANAGI
YURIKO HAMADA
HARUYO ICHIKAWA, KOMAKO HARA
KIKUE MOURI
SADAKO SAWAMURA
TOSHIAKI KONOE
KINNOSUKE TAKAMATSU
BENKEI SHIGANOYA
UNPEI YOKOYAMA
TSUKIE MATSUURA
Directed by
KENJI MIZOGUCHI
This way, mister.
Let me go home
You know what it means
to come to this side of the gate
- I'm going home
- Come inside, quick
Oharu?
You couldn't find
a customer either?
A woman of 50
can't make herself look 20
If you feel that way,
imagine how the rest of us feel
An old man took me
to an inn for pilgrims
I was glad
to get some business,
so I went along
Some pilgrims were gathered
He held a candle up to my face
A candle?
Then he said
to the young men there
"Look how she tries
to hide her age!
Would you sleep
with a woman like this?"
I think he was giving them
a lesson in karmic retribution
You're off
to a bad start tonight
Look, the old man's
making a fire again
Let's warm up
before heading home
Old man, let us get warm
You used to serve
in the imperial court
Did you ever think
you'd end up like this?
How did you fall so far?
Please don't ask about my past
Hey!
Making fires again!
I guess it's all right,
but be very careful
We will
Don't worry so much
or you'll go —
Oh, I guess
it's too late to go bald
Where are you going
in such finery?
To make an offering at the temple
on behalf of my master
That's good of you
You should see the sights too,
since you so rarely get out
I'd be scolded if I did that
Not at all Just pretend
you didn't know any better
You're going home early,
Lord Kikunokoji
I almost forgot
Nishinotoin is anxious
for your reply to his poem
He can't keep anything
a secret, can he?
It seems his poem
was rather forward
What did it say?
I don't know
Please excuse me
Wait! Please wait!
Please wait!
My name is Katsunosuke
Lord Kikunokoji begs your indulgence
to discuss a certain matter
Might I ask you to call at the house
of his friend in Teramachi?
I'm sorry, but I've been sent
to the temple on an errand
Then perhaps
on your way home
We would be deeply grateful
for just a moment of your time
Lady Oharu
Did you read the letter
I sent the other day?
Of course not
Who would read a letter
from a lowly retainer?
I burned it
without reading a word
I have no talent
for composing verse
I lack the wit
even to tell jokes well
But my heart is true
You can look down
upon my low rank,
but not upon my sincerity
The nobility makes sport of sincerity,
turning it into mere wordplay
If that's how they define
elegance, then I —
You'll never know
the meaning of elegance
You can't understand
the tastes of the nobility
Well, then
does any nobleman love you
as truly as I do?
Has any asked to marry you
and give you a happy home?
Please leave
I say this because
I want to see you happy
I don't need your concern
If you truly dislike me
as a person,
I'll leave you alone
Yes, I do!
But if it's my low rank
you disdain,
then I'll never give up
Go away
Lady Oharu, a human being —
no, a woman
can only be happy
if she marries for love
Rank and money
don't mean happiness
I asked you to leave
I didn't come here to listen to you
I'll wait alone
for Lord Kikunokoji
I said leave
My lord isn't coming
Please wait!
I'm sorry
I simply had to see you
Ever since
you came to the court,
every glimpse of you
has torn at my heart
Please at least consider
what I've said
I did read your letter
But no matter what you say,
we can never be together
Why not?
Neither the court nor my father
would ever allow it
Then we'll run away
We'll make a home of our own
I'll do my utmost
I'd gladly do anything
to protect you
Lady Oharu!
Madam, we have guests
Welcome
The imperial magistrate
sent us
We understand that
prostitutes use this house
That's absurd!
Who said such a thing?
I'll see for myself
Who are you?
I'm just passing through
Aren't you a retainer?
Yes
I belong to the Todo clan
of Iga province
My name is Inosuke
I serve Lord Senuemon Yasui
You dress
like a noblewoman
Where are you from, whore?
How dare you!
I'm not a prostitute
I'm the daughter
of Shinzaemon Okui,
a samurai
serving Chion-in Temple
Take her
I'm taking you
to the magistrate
Go!
Oharu Okui, while serving
in the imperial court,
you violated protocol
by associating
with a personage of low birth
As punishment for this illicit liaison,
you are sentenced as follows:
You are hereby banished
from the city of Kyoto,
never to return
Your parents, for failing
to provide proper guidance,
are hereby also
sentenced to exile
This judgment
is effective today,
the 7th of November, 1686
Katsufusa Itakura,
Magistrate of Temples and Shrines
Stop!
Relatives may go no further
Bid them farewell here
It's your fault we must live out here
in the middle of nowhere
You've single-handedly destroyed
this noble family's honor
You're a horrible child
Why is it wrong for a man
and woman to fall in love?
Why is it immoral?
What?
You slept with a man
without our consent
If that isn't immoral, what is?
Stop talking nonsense!
So what if we differ in rank?
How can it be wrong
if we truly love one another?
Silence!
Do you have
any last words?
Yes
Please give Lady Oharu
the following message
Very well
Proceed
"Please find a good man
and make a happy home
But be sure to marry
only for true love"
Is that all?
Anything else?
I hope the day will come
when people can love freely,
regardless of rank or class
Oharu!
It was a messenger
from the magistrate
He brought
Katsunosuke's will
But you mustn't tell Father
Oharu, stop!
What are you doing?
Let me go!
Stop!
Wait, Oharu!
Leave me alone!
I'm going
to join Katsunosuke!
Stop!
You mustn't!
Let me go!
This isn't
the end of the world!
If you kill yourself,
that's the end!
- An express messenger has come
- From where?
- Lord Matsudaira in Edo
- Matsudaira? Oh, goodness!
What is it?
A messenger
from Lord Matsudaira
Show him
into the drawing room at once
I'll change
into something else
Are you all right?
Oh, my!
Give him a hand
Now leave us alone
Thank you for your trouble
It must be a matter
of grave importance
To tell you the truth,
I seek a concubine
for Lord Matsudaira
- A concubine?
- That's right
You rushed here from Edo
to find a concubine?
This is no laughing matter!
Lady Matsudaira's illness
has left her barren
The clan will be ruined
if the lord has no heir
There can be
no greater calamity
The retainers,
sick with worry,
quickly found
some suitable young women,
but they were all
country girls
and not
to the lord's liking
Give me that
The retainers were at a loss
and decided that since Kyoto
is famous for its women,
there must be one here
that he would like
They ordered me
to rush here and find her
Is that so?
I was worried His Lordship
was seeking a large loan
Your mission seems
a rather simple one
I'm afraid
it isn't so simple
He has some
very specific requirements
Look at that!
To put it simply,
he wants a girl like that
I see
First of all,
"She should be
between 15 and 18
Her face should be
fashionably round
Her eyes
must be round too
Thick eyebrows,
with enough space
between the eyes
A small mouth, with a full set
of even white teeth
Long ears
with narrow rims
and detached,
translucent lobes
A natural, unaltered hairline
A long neck without wisps of hair
Long, slender fingers
with diaphanous nails"
That's a tall order
- There's more
- More?
"Feet smaller than eight inches,
with nice arches
She must have
a long, willowy torso,
a firm waist, but not too muscular,
a plump bottom,
a pleasant demeanor,
a fine figure
in whatever she wears,
noble in birth,
meek in personality,
and without
a single mole on her body"
Slender fingers
Let me see your face
Her mouth is too big
How old are you?
- Twenty-five
Oh, you're the leftovers
I'm her father, sir
No, her ears are too small
Her face isn't round enough
- What about her?
She just might be it!
Let me see the picture
Let's check
Her face is too long
Her face is round
Kahei, she may be the one
No, she has a mole
Her eyes are too slanted
Her nose is crooked
Her nose is flat
She has a mole
Her hairline is uneven
- What about this one?
She looks promising!
She might be the one
Turn her that way
Your foot size?
- Ten inches
What a pity!
Let's see here
No, her chin is too pointed
No, her forehead
is too broad
- Please look at my girl
- She looks sickly
This one's ears are wrong
What about her?
Her chin isn't right
Even in Kyoto,
nobody could assemble
as many beauties
as I have here today
There's nothing more
I can do
Won't you choose
one of them?
Are none of them suitable?
If the point is
to produce an heir,
any girl should do,
as long as she's healthy
"Thick eyebrows,
enough space
between the eyes,
a small mouth, with a full set
of even white teeth"
You have it memorized
I'll drop dead
before I find such a woman
I sympathize
but why send a man your age
on such a mission?
I'll tell you why:
A younger man
might try something
But me? I couldn't do
anything even if I tried
I see
What's that?
A blind man from Edo
teaches singing and dancing
to the daughters
of good families
Really?
The girls are popular
among the samurai
and serve at their parties
Is that right?
The town
Is laid out in a grid
Just like a Go board
Facing
Each other
Your hand
Clasped in mine
All is well
Let us lie
in each other's arms
Her!
Come here a minute
Let's have
a good look at her
Face the other way
Turn her again
Do you have
any moles on your body?
- Moles?
- Do you?
No
- None at all?
- I don't think so
Kahei, the search is over!
I'll buy her!
Yes, indeed
The messenger from Edo
is awaiting your reply
I'll rush back
and tell him you consent
What a relief
If she bears him an heir,
it will bring
even greater happiness
to you than to her
And to me as well,
as her new godfather
Thank you very much
If you please
Thank you for everything
We must be thankful
Things are looking up
I never expected
anything like this to happen
Oharu,
you've redeemed yourself
All is forgiven
Who would imagine mere
dancing lessons could lead to this?
We certainly had no idea!
You'll get 100 ryo
for clothing,
and an allowance too
What's wrong?
Aren't you happy?
I'm to be a concubine,
am I not?
What of it?
He's a daimyo
with a stipend of 30,000 koku.
You were at the imperial court,
so surely you understand
If a lord favors you,
you'll be given high rank
Indeed!
You've been chosen
to bear the heir to the line
You'll be a high-ranking
lady-in-waiting
That's right
I must ask the court
not to reveal her secret
before Lord Matsudaira
begins his inquiries
- And the temple too
- Yes I'll go now
Then we'll decide what to buy
and what to take to Edo
Come, Oharu
- I don't want to go
- What?
Going to a complete stranger
just to bear his child!
It won't be just any child
He'll be heir
to a 30,000-koku domain!
Katsunosuke would
never approve
You idiot!
Still going on about him!
I've accepted the offer!
You can't back out!
She's in excellent
physical condition
She is capable
of bearing a child
Lady Kasai
instruct her
in our etiquette
and take her
to Lady Matsudaira
Yes, my lord
The messenger
has returned from Kyoto
with the girl chosen
to be the concubine
Already?
She's waiting outside
Will you receive her?
Please endure this
for the sake of the clan
Her name is Oharu Okui
Show your face
Won't you pay homage
to Her Ladyship?
You may go now
Princess Morning Glory
answered the nobleman
She plucked the flowers
and offered them
Come sit here
For a long time
She stares pensively
at the flower in her hand
Does it remind you of Kyoto?
You didn't expect to see Bunraku
plays here in Edo, did you?
No, I didn't
Can this be real
It is her fate
To wither
In the shade
Day and night
She stares
at the deutzia blossoms
They fill her heart
Can you eat
the food here in Edo?
If you don't like anything,
just say so
By good fortune
She is given
To the imperial palace
What a lucky flower
How enviable
How fortunate you are
Reluctantly
She offers
The flower in her hand
But this flower
is only the go-between
In fact,
your face is the flower
That captured my heart
She has given birth
to an heir
Inform the head maid
Auspicious news:
An heir has been born!
A boy!
Auspicious indeed!
We must inform
His Lordship at once
A lovely baby
He looks just like you
Is that so?
Is His Lordship pleased?
He's delighted
I was so unhappy
when I was
first brought here
But now
that I've given birth —
No, you must say you were
"allowed to give birth"
Now that I've been
allowed to give birth,
I feel for the first time
that this is my home
His Lordship must be —
Oh, pardon me
Nothing could be
more auspicious for the clan
You have done well
Where are you taking my —
I mean, the infant heir?
I'm going to nurse him
Nurse him?
But I can nurse him myself
Thank you
I'll make a tidy profit
with this satin
You're worried
about payment, aren't you?
Relax
I have Lord Matsudaira's
30,000 koku backing me up
My master's very strict
about these things
You mean Kahei?
Listen, my daughter
just gave birth
to the heir to the clan
You look surprised
He'll inherit those 30,000 koku.
Heir to the clan?
Word arrived
the day before yesterday
Money is no object
Bring me the finest you have,
and lots of it
Congratulations
Look
It seems
your worries are over
Shall I bring out
the habutae silk?
- Don't be hasty
- Bring out everything
I'm opening a shop
on Muromachi Avenue
I want it to rival Sasaya's store,
so show me everything
What's happened
to the concubine?
His Lordship's love for her
has grown since she gave birth
What's wrong with that?
It's just that
he seems to grow weaker
by the day
The doctor says
if she continues
to share his bed,
it may shorten his life
We can't let that happen
The heir has been born
She's of no further use
Isn't that right, Isobe?
For the sake of the clan,
send her home
- But —
- Do it
She was dismissed?
Are you sure?
I don't know what to say
When she gave birth,
I was filled
with happiness and pride
I'm very sorry
So now you're back
After you bore the lord an heir,
you should have
withheld your affections a bit
Anyway, too late now
How much
did they give you?
Three hundred ryo
would be a great help
Just five ryo?
I thought you'd be rich
I bought
a huge amount of fabric
Now I'm deep in debt
For our sake,
work in Shimabara
as a courtesan
I'll buy your freedom
when I sell the fabric
You mean you'd actually
sell your own daughter?
There's no other choice
After everything
she's been through —
and now this!
Welcome
I've always wanted
to live it up in Shimabara
at least once before I die
I've risen
every day at dawn
and worked hard until the stars
came out in the sky
It must be 20 years
that I've been saving
my money
I think I've finally
saved enough,
so I've come
all the way from Echigo
Unfortunately
we're full at the moment
- Are you turning me away?
You're all
as pretty as a picture!
Pardon me, sir,
but this is a particularly
expensive establishment
Do you have
a letter of introduction?
All righty
If it's money you want
here's what I got
Enough to fill a five-quart container
Is that enough?
More than enough!
Welcome, sir
I'm the owner here
Is that so?
So you'll let me stay?
Prepare our largest room
and lay out our finest food
Call for Shizuhata
Hurry!
Thank you for honoring us
with your presence
See that my men
have a good time too
They've come a long way
Your packhorse drivers?
As you wish, sir
Hey, welcome them inside!
I have some sake
on my horse
Sir, we serve
the very best sake
Thank you
Shizuhata
our finest courtesan
All right,
let's liven things up a bit!
Hey, why aren't you
picking them up?
Here
Hey!
Where are your manners?
It's he who has
no manners
I'm not a beggar
Wait!
Stop!
Come back here!
Just a minute
What do you think
your job is?
Think you're too good
to be here?
You're not here
for your own enjoyment
Constantly carrying on
about your pedigree!
For all I know, you could be
a ragpicker's daughter
How dare you suggest
such a thing!
You're bought and paid for
You're no different
from a fish on a chopping board
We can serve you up
any way we like
He offered you money
What's wrong with that?
Fine, then
Never come back here again
What will your master
say to that?
If I dismiss you,
no one in these parts
will hire you as a courtesan
Now get out
It was all my fault
I'm sorry
Please forgive me
I'll try to do better
from now on
But please
don't tell my master
It's too late now
Get out
Master, the big spender
is calling for her
I'll give him
someone better
No, he says
he likes this one
He's never known a girl
who refused money
He wants to buy her
and take her home
Buy her?
You heard her
He wants to buy you
and take you to Echigo
Please put on a happy face
and serve him
Let's go
He's buying your freedom
Be nice to him, please
Will you really
buy my freedom
and take me to Echigo?
Yes, I'll take care of you
Actually, I came
to Kyoto to find a wife
I won't go back without one
Will you join me?
If your feelings are genuine,
I'll serve you faithfully
Why are you laughing?
Money
Money!
As long as I have money,
I can have
anything in the world
People see money
and their eyes gleam
They crawl on all fours
Even a haughty woman like you
smiles and sidles up to me
You think I'm greedy,
but I'm not
I want to be
with you because —
Because everyone has a price,
and this is yours
Thanks to this money,
your fortune has turned
Lord Money!
Almighty Money!
You fraud!
No wonder
you spend so freely!
He's a counterfeiter!
Your money is bogus!
You'll be beheaded!
Come quietly!
Don't resist!
Fool!
You're under arrest!
Please
try to smile
I'm begging you
You're our daughter again
You don't know
how I've waited
for the day you'd return to us
from Shimabara
We won't cause you
any more suffering
Please forgive us and smile
Welcome
My sad fate
Is pitiful indeed
Where did you learn
that song?
It's so beautiful
You must be
an accomplished singer
I'm so ashamed
Back when there were
pleasure quarters in Rokujo,
I was a courtesan
named Katsuragi
Take care of yourself
Thank you
Here you are
My pillow is soaked
With tears
I'm glad you came
You were once
Lord Matsudaira's concubine
I'm hesitant
to ask for your help
Please don't feel that way
Try to think of me
as your sister
We'll treat you well
while you're here
and find you
a good husband
I'm very grateful
My wife has few relatives,
so please be
a good friend to her
May I have
a word with her?
I must ask you
something right away
Will you hear me out?
What is it?
Please write a solemn oath
never to reveal
my secret to anyone
Why would I ever
reveal your secret?
Please, just do it
Thank you very much
Now, how may I serve you?
There's only one thing
I'll ever ask you to do:
Will you please
dress and style my hair?
I expected you
to ask much more
Then you'll do it?
I'm so glad
The woman I had doing it
suddenly
became indisposed
I'm not very good at it,
but I can try
The thing is,
my hair's so
Your hair is beautiful
No, it's not
Come with me
I was seriously ill last year
This is what
it did to my hair
I made this wig
while recuperating
at my parents' home
I've tried
to keep it a secret
I'm terrified that
my husband will find out
He'd be revolted
Please don't tell him
I promise I won't
Having your hair dressed?
Very nicely done
Oharu's quite good
She did it for you?
Dear
what would you say
to adopting Oharu
and finding her
a nice husband?
Certainly
Perhaps a man
from your store?
No, there's nobody
good enough here
Pardon me
What is it?
Shall I send the bill
to the customer?
Ask Jihei He knows
What are you looking at?
I'll do that
Now what?
What about the turmeric
salesman's bill?
Don't ask me
Ask Jihei
You're getting on my nerves
Fine I'll go
to the shop myself
What are you staring at?
Bunkichi,
stop staring and hurry up!
- Welcome
- Good day
Oh, you're here
What a rare treat
Please come in
- Sorry I haven't been in touch
- Not at all
Bring some tea
- Please don't bother
Looks like business is booming
- I wouldn't go that far
Oharu, please make
some tea for our guest
Shall I take it in for you?
No, thank you
May I observe you?
You're making me nervous
You do it so well
Stop that
Get away from me
I just can't make
any money these days
- I hear you do
- Nonsense
People like to talk
Thank you
It's you!
I didn't know you were here
Won't you wait a moment?
Wait!
You know her?
What's she doing here?
I'm taking care of her
You make it sound so noble
What on earth do you mean?
Don't play innocent
You bought her, right?
Bought her?
She's a Shimabara courtesan
Shimabara?
Shimabara,
as in the pleasure quarter?
Where else?
So when Hishiya told you,
that was the first you'd heard of it?
Yes
You knew before,
didn't you?
That's why you took her in
Don't be absurd
You sent her
to Lord Matsudaira
You must have known
I didn't know
I was shocked
You saw her at Shimabara,
didn't you?
What are you talking about?
I've never even been
to Shimabara
You think I'd waste
good money in a place like that?
I'm so tight I step carefully
so I don't damage my sandals!
You're lying!
Stop this!
Excuse me.
What is it?
- A letter from the money exchange
- I see
Be careful!
Watch what you're doing!
Cut your hair
Your hair — cut it!
Why?
You plan to use
your beautiful hair
to steal my husband away!
I heard all about it
I know all about your past
You lied to me
I apologize
But I swear I never —
Cut it Cut it!
Cut it! Go on!
That's not enough
Cut off more!
Please don't, madam!
Cut it!
If you don't cut it, I will!
I'll cut it off
Just watch me
Good morning
Oharu,
where did my wife go?
To the cemetery
I see
Oharu
you're a naughty girl
I heard all about your past
I'm sorry
I'm not scolding you
I'll bet you had
some fun times, eh?
One would never guess
just looking at your face
But you really liked doing
those dirty things, didn't you?
That's how you twisted
Lord Matsudaira
around your little finger
I did no such thing
It's all right
I understand completely
You can relax
and be yourself around me
I can enjoy
a top courtesan
and not even
have to pay for it
Calm down!
Remember this smell
All right?
What's wrong?
My hair!
Where are you going?
Oharu!
It was you!
You did this to my hair!
It's nothing
Go back to bed
She's just mumbling
in her sleep
Here you are
- More?
- No, thank you
Don't worry
It's too soon to despair
If one god forsakes you,
another will save you
Yakichi here works in the fan shop
He's singled you out
His boss is going
to help him
set up his own shop
He's asking
for your hand in marriage
I think
I'll excuse myself now
What about your proposal?
Perhaps you could
discuss that with Oharu
Look how naive he is
I hear he's devoted
to his work
He's never once been
to the pleasure quarters
You couldn't hope
for a happier life
than as his wife
I'm hardly worthy
of such a man
After all, my past
He knows all about you
We told him everything
Didn't hide a single detail
He said,
"I don't mind
I want to make that poor,
unlucky girl happy"
He's in love with you
- Going out so early?
- Yes I won't be long
You were up late last night
working on the books
Yes, it was nearly dawn
when I finished
I'm quite sleepy
Why don't you rest
for a while?
I have to deliver these today
Really?
I'll buy a sash for you
on the way home
How nice!
Thank you!
Wait a minute
Face this way
Perfect
Hurry back
Excuse me.
Welcome
I'd like a dancing fan
for my daughter
Certainly
It's very hot today
These are some of our best
I see
You have a lovely shop
Thank you
You should marry soon
and run a shop like this
Running an honest business
is a good life, isn't it?
Your husband
has accomplished much
at such a young age
He's just an honest,
hardworking man
I envy you
You're so pretty
You two make
an ideal couple
Any children?
Not yet
Is that so?
- Madam!
- What is it?
Awful news!
It's your husband!
What's happened?
He was probably killed
by a robber
He died clutching this sash
Yakichi!
A handsome youth at morn
is by dusk a heap of bones
All is truly impermanent
in this world
What do you plan
to do now?
My late husband's uncle
sold the shop
Where does that leave you?
I'm going back
to my parents
Did he leave you anything
to remember him by?
No, nothing
Nothing?
I don't need anything
I want to become a nun
and serve Buddha
A nun?
Please show me the way!
Bunkichi?
Hey, where's Bunkichi?
Here I am.
Look at this
Who's this charge account for?
An acquaintance of mine
I've told you repeatedly:
We don't extend credit
This is unacceptable
Go collect the money tomorrow
Can't it wait a month?
No
If it's too awkward for you,
I'll go myself
Where is he?
You refuse to tell me?
You won't tell me?
Excuse me
Jihei!
It's been such a long time
You're incorrigible,
luring poor Bunkichi
to a place like this
What do you mean?
He heard I was here
and kindly brought me
some fabric
Fine I'm here to collect
for what he gave you on credit
If you don't have the money,
return the fabric
I already made it
into a kimono
Already?
In that case,
I'll take the kimono
Jihei, you and I
aren't strangers
How can you be so cold?
Here you go
Cold?
I'm not Bunkichi
I can't be seduced
by a whore like you,
so pay up
What did you call me?
Fine, I'll return it
Is that the kimono
you made?
And the sash too
No need to undress
Here's the kimono
Now hurry up and leave
This is going to take
longer than I thought
Take this money
and get yourself
some tea and cake
Drink as much tea
as you can, okay?
Understand?
Oharu,
you must be very tired
Please leave!
I don't want to see your face
Leave at once!
I'm not the kind of woman
you think
He was trying to rape me
Please believe me, sister
I beg of you!
I really believed
you wanted to become a nun
You were just making
a fool of me
Did you really think
you could get away with it?
What kind of person are you?
Get out!
Oharu
What's the matter?
I've been driven
out of the temple
What? You too?
I was dismissed too
You were?
Oharu, come with me
I know I can make you happy
What?
Don't worry about money
When I left,
I stole 50 ryo in gold
What? Bunkichi!
They all think I ran off
with you anyway
No! I won't go
with a thief like you
I can't! No!
Would you like some?
It's very good
Wait a moment
How about an egg?
I'm at a loss
May I have one of these?
Oharu, these are good!
- Bunkichi!
- Jihei!
He's the thief!
Catch him!
Stop! Come back!
Jihei!
Stop!
Please let him go!
Out of the way!
- Oharu!
- You wench!
Go off somewhere and die,
you rotten whore!
Oharu!
This fleeting world
Is full of pain
And I, oh I
Am a thing of pity
This life
So full of regrets
Will vanish
Like the morning dew
What's the matter?
What's wrong?
Come along with us
and take a rest
Yes, let's go
Come along
I'll carry it for you
I'll get that too
She hasn't eaten
in three days,
and she's chilled
to the bone
Help yourself to the food
Your hair's turned
really gray
Yes, it has
Here we are,
covered with wrinkles
yet we try to coo
like young maidens:
"Hey there, handsome!"
What nerve we have!
You wanna earn
some money too?
It'll take your mind off things
I'm too old for that,
unlike you
Listen to her,
acting all innocent!
It's a pitiful life we lead,
but nobody's
going to help us out
Ain't that the truth!
It would be easier just to die,
but we can't even do that
Drink the sake while we have it
It'll lift your spirits
We've fallen this far
Might as well do
what we want
I can get you some clothes
What do you say?
Come on
Whatever we do,
the world's not about to change
That's right!
Old man,
we've got a newcomer
Bring her something to wear
Are you the newcomer?
You could probably
make good money
I'll rent you a kimono
and undergarments
for three bu a night
A sash and socks
will be one bu.
Footwear will be five mon.
This is so gaudy
What's wrong with it?
You can't make money
if they don't notice you
I expect payment soon,
so hurry up and get to work
If you're done here,
go away
Nasty old man
Come on
I'll help you get dressed
Hey, mister, wait a minute
Why don't we have some fun?
Old hag! Are you crazy?
Hey, handsome!
Come on,
let's have some fun
Go away!
- I'll give you your money's worth!
- I said no!
Madam, would you come
with me for a moment?
Certainly
Come in
Sit down over there
Cold, isn't it?
Shall I sing you a song?
Is there something wrong?
Your silence
makes me uneasy
Don't worry about it
You can just sit there
Please drop the fake voice
I'd really prefer it
if you spoke
in your natural voice
Come this way
Everybody
take a good long look
You see that?
You still want to sleep
with women now?
You all want happiness
in the next world
That's why you're on
the Thirty-three Temple Pilgrimage
However
if you'd rather steep yourself
in the impermanence of earthly life,
then follow the example
of this goblin cat
in human form
Thank you for coming
That will be all
Now please go
When you return
to your homes,
you can tell everyone
how you met a real goblin cat
Thanks a lot
What are you doing?
Looking at a statue
of an arhat
It looks like him
Like who?
Think of men you know
and try to find their faces
among the statues
You'll find quite a few
She's right!
They all have
such funny faces!
Oharu, what's wrong?
Look, it's your mother
I think she's waking up
I'm so glad to see you
Why have you come?
Someone told her
they saw you around here
She's been looking for you
I'm glad
to know you're safe
How is Father?
He passed away
He worried about you
to the very end
But don't cry
You'll find happiness again
Me? Happiness?
It's true
You won't have
to suffer anymore
You'll live in a big manor
A messenger came
from the Matsudaira palace
He said Lord Matsudaira
passed away
The young lord
has succeeded him
My son?
He's Lord Matsudaira now
The messenger said
the young lord wants his mother
to live with him in the palace
You mean
I'll get to see my son?
I can live with him?
Thank goodness
He's grown
into a good young man
I'd like Shinozaki and Tashiro
to deliver a stern rebuke
Have you forgotten
your debt of gratitude
to our late lord?
Who do you take us for?
The family line runs
from Tsunemoto Genji,
grandson of Emperor Seiwa,
through the Nitta clan
The lords of our clan
are direct descendants
of the great
Ieyasu Tokugawa
The late lord
was fourth in line
His son Yoshitaka is fifth
You were
the late lord's concubine,
but you reduced yourself
to a courtesan
and finally a prostitute
Do you have any excuse?
Are you not ashamed?
If word of your vulgar behavior
were to get out,
it would besmirch
the clan's name,
and the shogunate's punishment
would be severe
We cannot allow you
to come and go as you please
You are sentenced
to lifetime confinement
You must spend day and night
repenting for your sins
and beseeching the spirit
of our late lord for forgiveness
Now
in an exceptional
display of mercy,
His Lordship will grant you
a brief viewing
so that you may
bid him farewell
Keep your distance!
This is a serious affront!
Please allow me
to approach him
He's my child
I gave birth to him
Remember our orders!
I'm going after her!
You there!
Isn't she ready yet?
- Any minute, sir
- What's taking so long?
What is it?
We've lost her
How can that be?
Spread out and find her
Inform the others!
Spread out
and look for her!
The woman has disappeared!
Disappeared?
Find her at once!
Sentient beings
are innumerable
I vow to save them
Delusions are inexhaustible
I vow to extinguish them
The teachings of the dharma
are immeasurable
I vow to master them
Buddhahood is incomparable
I vow to attain it
THE END