''These smiling flowers''
''These fragrant gardens''
''This world filled...''
''with glorious colours''
''The nectar intoxicates the bees''
''What little have l to add
to this splendour...''
''save a fear tears,
a few sighs''
l told you to keep the place tidy.
lf that manuscript was here,
then where has it got to ?
- What do you know, then?
- He wished you good morning.
Fool!
l mean about the manuscript!
You've looked at my things?
Wings?
This is a newspaper office,
not a bird house!
Wings, indeed!
Things.
Have you read the poems l left?
l have.
Did you like them?
You'll publish them?
l haven't lost my mind.
Call that gibberish poetry? lt's
a crusade against unemployment.
Poetry deals with delicacies:
You must write poems about love.
You are incomparable, Sir!
Write about intoxication...
...the beauty of a cup,
or a fine woman.
Shut up.
You don't write poetry.
Have you read poets
like Mir and Momin?
Yes, and Josh and Faiz, who are
beyond your comprehension.
Give me my poems.
- We will find them later.
What do you think
you're doing young man?
What right have you
to throw away my poems?
Should l make a paper hat of them?
Don't insult them by
wearing them on a hollow head.
My head? Hollow?
How about yours? lf you're
a poet, l'm a donkey!
lt's clear, and it's nice
to hear you admit it.
Are you weighing
vegetables or gold?
There's Uncle Vijay!
l've caught him.
l'm not your enemy.
Why run from your mother?
Where have you been?
l can't bear to see your suffer.
l'm well, mother.
Sure you are. Just look
at the state you're in.
Come home. l've hidden away
some good food for you.
You've found him?
- Yes.
Well, mother.
So your poet is home!
Every literate fool thinks
he's poet.
Where else can he get food
as a parasite?
Take no notice of them. Eat.
See? We earn and mother feeds
delicacies to her layabout.
He's shameless.
lf he had any self-respect, he'd
starve rather than eat here.
Shut up, you two! l won't hear
a word said against him.
He's back after so long, and
you can't bear to see him eat.
He's hale and hearty. Why doesn't
he earn and not burden us?
After his father died,
you should look after him.
lt wasn't our wish that our
parents produce such a layabout.
That l must have to hear this!
lt was my misfortunate
to give birth to you two.
You won't even let me work,
because of your ''prestige''.
lf l could work as a maid,
l could feed my son.
Sister-in-law,
Where are my poems?
Address me, not the women.
l sold them for
10 annas as waste paper.
Waste paper?
You sold my poems for ten annas?
Uncouth fools no better.
You call me uncouth?
Did you hear that, brother?
l got rid of them this morning.
Now l'll get rid of you! Out!
Where will you go on an empty
stomach? Who will tend to you?
You take me along with you.
l don't want to stay here
for another minute.
Don't worry, mother.
l'll do my best.
l'll take you away from here
as soon as l can.
Let me get on with my work
instead of searching waste paper.
But there was an important file.
A file?
Containing handwritten papers?
Where are they?
- A woman bought them.
They caught her eye, she read
some, then she took them away.
Which woman?
Where does she live?
l don't know;
she wasn't a local person.
lf she comes again, l'll ask.
Come come!
Have you fallen out with your
brothers again?
Are you hungry?
You'll starve to death.
Well, today l got 20 rupees
from a rich man.
His car was run over a woman's leg.
l gave false witness for him.
Shyam, remember how you found
a lame sparrow as a kid?
You cared for it
until it was better.
l was only a kid.
But you are a kid now also.
''Lament not...''
''if l turn my face away...''
''your gaze is filled...''
''with such longing''
Listen.
l was saying...
''Who know what you said?''
''Who knows what l heard?''
''Something stirred in my heart''
''Who knows what you said...?''
''l felt my heart awaken,
l felt such elation''
''Slumbering dreams reawakened,
something stirred in my heart''
''Who knows what you said?''
''Who knows what l heard''
''Something stirred in my heart''
''l stumble no more,
my feet no longer falter''
''There is new life in my step.
Something stirred in my heart''
''Who knows what you said''
''Who knows what l heard''
''But something sure
stirred in my heart''
''The cascade of my hair
is filled with sweet fragrance''
''Doors open to reveal secret longings;
''something stirred in my heart''
''Who knows what you said''
''Who knows what l heard''
''Something stirred in my heart''
Excuse me...
- Yes?
That song you were singing...
- You like it?
Where did you get it?
lt's mine.
lt isn't yours.
- Then why ask, if you know?
Because l ....
- What do you want?
The file with that song in it.
ls that all?
l don't like prattle.
Do you like me?
No.
Then why follow me?
l want to know only that the
file is with you or not.
lt's valuable to me.
Whenever l have money...
So you've followed
me empty-handed? Get out!
Please understand.
l want only that file.
For me it is important.
You go, or should l
remove my sandal.
Stop shouting, silly.
Your customer will run away.
A pauper! l lured him here,
but he hasn't a penny.
Juhi, it was him.
Gulabo, where are you running?
l must apologize to him,
l treated him very badly.
Stop talking in riddles
and tell me in plain words.
What's all this about?
The man who followed me
is a poet.
The poet whose poems l bought
as waste paper.
Look: the same paper,
the same writing.
And l threw him out as a pauper.
He is a pauper.
You did quite the right thing.
Foolish girl! Come on
Have you written any poems
in the holidays?
A few.
Anyone can write poems. lf you're
a true poet, create something.
Extempore?
But on what subject?
Who is she?
There's your subject:
a poem about her.
''When l walk,
even my shadow lags behind''
''When you walk,
the universe keeps pace''
''When l stop,
clouds of misery gather''
''When you stop...
spring's radiance is outshone''
Miss Pushlata.
''Our love will survive every trial''
''We shall never forget
our oath of love''
''We leave the world
far behind''
''How long will we
journey together?''
Coolie!
A coolie.
- At your service.
Put these in the car.
What has the world come to?
The educated work as coolies.
Have your money.
No credit.
lt's counterfeit.
So you've got nothing else.
So that's your game!
Now who'll pay for that food
you've touched?
Pay up, or l'll have your shirt.
Take the plate away.
Put it back!
Keep the change.
Go to a barber and get yourself
made to look more human.
Do eat.
l'm not hungry.
- Yes, you are.
You've no right to take pity on me.
l'm sorry...
...take no notice of me.
You have every right
to be angry.
l treated you very badly
the other day.
l've nothing against you.
Then please eat...
...for my sake.
What did you say?
For your sake?
You don't even know me.
l know you very well.
- How?
Through your poems.
l know your thoughts
and feelings.
What else is there?
l don't understand.
But, Miss...
Why address me so politely?
l am not used to it.
Until today, people
have spoken rudely to me.
l have suffered
their vulgar remarks...
...their abuse, their crude jokes.
But you behave so respectfully.
Massage, oil massage,
make things gleam!
''lf your head reels with pain,
or your heart sinks in gloom...''
''Don't fret, leave it to me;
l'll set things right soon''
''Massage, oil massage!''
''The lotion l use has magic.
Curing baldness and dandruff"
''Once my hands begin to whirl,
your hair won't look so rough''
''Mark my words, my friend,
this lotion brings you joy"
''lt cures a thousand ailments,
so why not give it a try?''
''Suffering a lovers' tiff?
ls your business in the throes?''
''A touch of this supple hand
will dissipate all woes''
''Mark my words, my friends,
this lotion brings you joy"
''Be you a master, be you a slave.
Be you a leader, or one of the led''
''Come to me, as everyone does.
Come to me and bow your head''
''Mark my words, my friend.
This lotion brings you joy"
''lt cures a thousand ailments.
So why not give it a try?''
''Don't fret, leave it to me...''
''lf your head reels with pain,
or your heart sinks in gloom...''
''Don't fret, leave it to me;
l'll set things right soon''
Mr. Vijay, come here!
A great poet: l was singing
one of his songs.
Since l've been singing your
song, business has doubled.
Don't go
l'll just finish him.
- What?
Stay put.
Mr. Vijay, l'll give you a
special massage completely free.
No, thank you. The present
times have battered me enough.
lt's amazing how you still
manage to smile.
Only a donkey in the noon sun...
...and a poet lost in poetry
are so stunned.
True, only the glitter of gold
is like the sun.
So donkeys will.
What are you talking about?
- We're discussing donkeys.
Here l am.
Juhi, weren't you
waiting for me?
l'm waiting for a man in a car.
- ln a car? Not a masseur?
May He puncture his tyres.
May He puncture your head.
Juhi, what happened?
- Are you cross with me?
Have you no consideration for
the heart you've punctured?
Get it patched up.
- l have no wife to patch it.
What can l do about it?
- Marry me.
Stop it, idiot!
Did you hear? l have
the gift of massaging.
lf l had the gift of cheating
we could afford a car.
l'm done for!
A coconut? l get it.
l won't say another word.
Stop him, or l'll have to
chase him for a mile!
Stop! Naughty fellow
Hello, Pushpa.
Vijay! l didn't recognize you.
You were so handsome. Whose
''love'' brought you to this?
Someone who won't let me go...
Unemployment.
Your children?
- And their father's.
They're Gullu and Fullu,
bright sparks like him.
What do you mean?
There's a gathering at our old
college tonight; you must come.
Now l'll have to chase him
for a mile. l'll leave
You must come tonight.
Where is Bhattacharya?
He was going to sing next.
Vijay, why hide out here?
Come inside.
No, Pushpa. My clothes...
You're decently covered
from head to foot. Come along.
Ladies and gentleman.
Bhattacharya isn't here.
We're delighted...
...we're delighted
that Vijay is here...
...and request him
to recite a poem.
Don't be formal. Come along.
Let's hear you, Vijay.
''l am weary of this
troubled life''
''Weary of this troubled existence''
''ln my grief, may l not
reject the entire world''
Why such a sad song on this
occasion? Recite a happy verse.
''How can l sing of joy...''
''if l live in pain''
''l can only...''
''...return to life what
life itself offers me''
''Once again...''
''...the memories of love
stir in my heart''
''l confess...''
''that l am overcome
by life's blows''
''Today l break all belief...''
''...in the illusion of hope''
''Today l vow...''
''to voice no complaint
against anyone''
Are you an ex-student?
Have you a job?
No, l need one.
You recite very well.
Here's my card.
Come to my office tomorrow.
- Yourself?
Here are my poems.
When did you study at college?
- From '48 to '52.
Shall l read the poems aloud?
l married in 1952.
Did you study science or arts?
Arts. May l recite the poems?
You're sure you left college
in '52, or was it before?
ln '52. Mr. Ghosh, my poems?
- Will you work?
Service? l thought you called me
about publishing my poems.
There's still plenty of time
to publish your poems.
l must get to know
you better first.
Mr. Chatterji, this is
your new assistant.
You can start tomorrow.
''lf l were to give
my heart to you, only you''
''lf l were to lock
your heart away"
''lf l were to adorn your hair
with flowers of love''
''lf l were to shake the flowers
to the ground''
''lf l were to remember you
in my dreams''
''lf l were to give you
sleepless nights''
''lf l were to lay my heart
at your feet''
''lf l were to deny your love
and walk away"
How have you been?
- l'm alive.
l want to see you happy.
Don't worry. l have
learnt to be happy.
Has some girl taught you?
One girl was enough for me.
l don't want to suffer again.
You mean you have erased
your first love.
l should have.
l forgot: l was really going up.
Closing time. Three hours
you've waited. For whom?
Does Mr. Vijay come here often?
Yes, but not lately.
Any message for him?
So you find something to say
to the waiter. How about me?
Have you had time
to look at them?
- Which papers?
- Vijay calls them his poetry.
l've read them, they're fine.
Why not publish some?
Are you mad?
You must know we publish famous
poets, not the trash of novices.
Put in an advertisement instead.
What do you want?
Sir, this trash of a novice...
...may l take it away?
Are you free tomorrow evening?
-
Come and lend a hand
at a party in my house.
l'll be there.
lt's no good getting upset, Juhi.
Who will care for you
in your old age?
God willing.
Be careful, or a nut
will fall on you.
lf you want security,
listen to me.
lf l listen to you, l'll starve.
You can hardly keep yourself,
how can you feed me, too?
My hunger will be satisfied
by seeing you in my house.
Really?
Abdul Sattar, do you
love me that much?
Let's marry.
- Stop, it idiot!
Do you hear? No, nothing.
No nut.
Your husband?
- He's ill.
He wanted me to take him to
hospital, but l put it off.
How could l miss such a party?
You're very kind!
And the children?
How did you get my address?
Your address? Do you live here?
Let's go outside.
Mr. Ghosh told me to come.
Told you? Do you know him?
l work for him.
And you?
- l am his...
Who is the most
talented poet here?
They are all good.
But the one
in the black jacket is...
Don't tell him about us.
Understand?
Poems that serve the nation
are better than...
...love poems.
Gentleman, drop this argument.
The drinks are here.
Leave it to the servant, dear.
Come along, serve the drinks.
''How could l...''
''apprise her of my love?''
''The words froze on my lips''
''Tears welled in my eyes''
''ln the gallantry
of frigid hearts''
''Where pleasure is sought''
''Clammy fingers cling
to the cup of whine''
''l quaffed the wine,
a drop was spilled''
''An extreme despair
came to my rescue''
''Receiving my poet, out of pity,
she deigned to love me''
''Who are the fortunate ones...''
''who gain the love they seek?''
Great, Mr Ghosh!
Even your servants recite poems
l'll arrange for the dinner
Can only the rich be poets?
Go ahead, young man
''When l asked for flowers,
l was given thorns''
''Who are the fortunate ones...''
''who gain the love they seek?''
''When l searched for happiness...''
''l was lost in streets
of sadness''
''When l sought songs of joy,
l heard songs of sorrow"
''Every torment doubled
the pain my heart''
''When l asked for flowers,
l was given thorns''
''Who were the fortunate ones...''
''who got the love they sought''
''Companions came...''
''Companions came, stayed awhile,
then left me all alone''
''Who can spare the time to clasp
the hand of a falling man?''
''Even my shadow eludes me
as it fades away"
''When l asked for flowers,
l was given thorns''
''Who are the fortunate ones
who gain the love they seek?''
''lf this is called living,
then l'll live my life somehow"
''l shall not sigh, l'll seal my lips,
l'll dry my tears''
''Why should l fear grief,
when l have encountered it so often?''
''When l asked for flowers,
l was given thorns''
''Who are the fortunate ones
who gain the love they seek?''
Wonderful! Excellent!
l have come to see you.
Mr. Ghosh has gone
to the board meeting.
You shouldn't have come.
l have been very upset
since the party.
Do you bear me ill will?
No, Meena.
l bear no grudge.
Why did you sing that
heart-rending poem that day?
You revived my desires.
- Forget the past.
l had forgotten,
l had remoulded my life.
l controlled my heart.
Why disturb my heart?
Why return to my life?
When did l ever leave
your life? You left me.
Do not try to correct your first
mistake with another, Meena.
l've made no mistake.
Besides love, a sensible woman needs
security and the comfort of a home.
And some money is also required.
For those things...
You married Mr. Ghosh,
selling love for wealth.
Don't accuse me wrongly.
l loved you, but you
were poor and unemployed.
ln life, besides love
and poetry, there's hunger.
How could you bear my burden
when you couldn't feed yourself?
You gave me no chance.
When a man has responsibilities,
he shoulders them.
Don't deceive yourself.
You sought wealth and
high position in society.
Now you have them. Despite that,
you are restless and resentful.
You know why?
Because you have always
been selfish.
You never considered my plight.
Now you don't
consider your husband.
Life's real joy lies
in making others happy.
You've never understood that;
that's why you're unhappy.
Wonderful!
My wife's no better
than a streetwalker.
Vijay and l hardly know each other.
How long has this been going on?
We hardly know each other.
Anything else?
- Nothing.
Then let's see how upset you are
when l dismiss him.
Pay up!
- l earn my money the hard way.
Scoundrel! Pay Up!
Constable!
Save me, do something!
You?
What's the matter?
Has a girl run this way?
No.
Who is she?
- My wife.
Sorry sir, l made a mistake.
What is your name?
Gulab.
lt's all clear now.
You can go safely.
''Tormented by a long absence...''
''Radha longed...''
''for her lover''
''One day she went...''
''to her beloved and lamented''
''Hold me in your arms
today, my love...''
''so that l am fulfilled''
''Ease the pain in my heart...''
''slake the fire in my body"
''My eyes are wide open''
''My luckless eyes''
''l can't rest until
l am truly yours''
''l can hardly see ahead.
Behind me torment follows''
''Without you,
life is meaningless''
''Beloved, make my love complete''
''so it may last
''Call me your very own''
''Call me your own,
''Slake the thirst...''