Best African Feature
Festival of Black Arts 1966
Grand Prize Carthage
Film Festival 1966
BLACK GIRL
From a Short Story by...
Has anyone come for me?
You made it all right? Let's go.
Did you have a nice trip?
Lovely country, France.
Yes, sir.
Here we are at last.
Is that you?
Hello, Diouana.
I hope you'll like it here.
I'll show you your room.
Here's your bed.
And that's the Riviera.
Juan-les-Pins,
Nice...
Cannes...
and Antibes.
I'll show you the kitchen.
Kitchen, bathroom...
bedroom...
living room.
That's all I ever see.
This isn't what I
came to France for.
What are the people here like?
The doors are all
shut, day and night...
night and day.
I came to take care
of the children.
Where are they?
Why is Madame always
shouting at me?
I'm not a cook or a cleaning woman.
You're not going to a party.
You've dressed like that for
weeks. Put on something else!
I bought this apron for you.
Let's see.
Turn around.
We're having guests for lunch.
Fix a nice rice with peanut sauce.
Why this apron?
What am I here?
I've never been a cook.
Why does Madame want rice?
Her cook in Dakar never fixed rice.
Maybe the rice in
Dakar is different.
I came here for the
children. Where are they?
Why did Madame bring me
here if they aren't with her?
After I make this rice, maybe
they'll show me the city.
Maybe we'll go to Cannes...
Nice, Monte Carlo.
We'll look at all
the pretty stores,
and when Madame pays me,
I'll buy pretty dresses...
shoes...
silk undies...
and pretty wigs.
I'll have my picture
taken on the beach...
and send it back to Dakar...
where everyone will
be green with envy!
I hope they like my rice.
My sauce isn't too spicy.
What if the children don't come?
- I'm dying to taste it.
- It's good but very spicy.
Genuine African cooking
prepared by the maid!
Would you pass the rice?
You like it?
It's very good.
- Very spicy.
- Good. I like spicy food.
A plate of rice, and wine.
These people eat like
pigs and jabber away!
And do they ever drink!
A little sauce, please.
It's good.
A bit more.
You must come to Dakar.
Africa isn't safe now.
All those coups d'état.
Senegal is safe.
It's very good, but a bit rich.
And nicely prepared.
Your cook's a gem.
Africans only eat rice.
- What's in the sauce?
- Is it fattening?
I hope it's an aphrodisiac.
Always kidding around!
Thank you, Diouana.
Do you mind, miss?
I've never kissed a black woman.
She doesn't look too happy.
With independence, the natives
have lost a natural quality.
He was just kidding around.
The rice was very
good. I'm pleased.
Fix some nice coffee.
Put that down.
Come over here.
PUBLIC SCRIBE
Where are you going?
To look for work.
It all began that morning...
in Dakar.
I'd gone up and down,
from one floor to the next,
but it was the same all over:
No one wanted a maid.
- Think of the future.
- The future looks dark!
Don't exaggerate!
- A man can't have opinions anymore!
- But that's obstruction!
That's what you say!
It's in your interest.
- In your district - -
I'm elected by the people!
- Not so loud!
- I say no!
Think of your children.
He's right. You have
to ease up a bit.
Excuse me, miss.
I don't want any!
He walked right up to
me and just kept staring.
My mind was elsewhere.
I had to find work.
The street was empty
except for two women.
They were beautiful.
I watched them go by.
But he just kept talking.
He told me about “the maids'
square” where I might find work.
When we got there, he left.
I promised to see him again
and then sat down to
wait like the other girls.
The sun passed
overhead several times,
but we all came back
every morning and evening.
That morning I went
to the square as usual.
The others were already there.
I sat down on the curb,
as I did every day,
to wait on providence.
She came up from behind.
She paced before us.
No one could see her eyes.
She looked us over one by one.
We could tell she was
looking for a maid.
The other girls surrounded her.
Each wanted to be chosen.
She backed away
from all the outstretched hands.
I was getting up when
she came over to me
and asked if I wanted
a job. “Yes, ma'am.”
"Can you take care of
children?” "Yes, ma'am.'
“Have you worked for
white people before?”
“No, ma 'am. ”
She hired me anyway.
I was so happy.
I had a job! When I
maimed home that evening,
I was very, very happy.
I've got a job!
I've got a job with white folks!
A job with white folks!
Mother was there as usual,
and I told her about my job.
She threw the mask aside
and told me to be brave.
Let me have the mask. I'll
give you 50 francs on payday.
For me?
Yes, ma'am.
A present from the maid.
Looks like the real thing.
This is the new nanny
for the children.
Explain the house rules to her:
If she breaks anything,
she pays for it.
Give her something to eat.
- Yes, ma'am.
These are the children:
Sophie...
Damien...
and Philippe.
Now go play outside.
In Dakar I didn't do the cooking
or the laundry.
I only looked after the children.
I took them for walks.
I walked them to school
and then home again.
Senegal isn't safe.
With Senghor it is.
I have to think it
over. Don't pressure me.
It's a golden opportunity.
But all those coups
d'état! I have a family.
It looks worse from
here than it is.
But look at the Congo.
Senegal isn't the Congo.
Life is easy there.
How long before we'd
get back to France?
You get leave every two
years. And there's no risk:
Part of your salary
is paid in France.
It sounds interesting.
What about housing?
Everything's spelled
out in the contract.
You'd have no worries.
Here's our coffee.
- Does she speak French?
- No.
- But she understands.
- You mean instinctively?
I suppose so.
Like an animal.
In any case, she's
a very good cook.
It's late. We have to go.
You must come to Dakar.
Now I understand.
Madame wanted a servant
who'd do everything.
That's why she chose me.
Why am I here?
To look after the children
or to be a housemaid?
Have you noticed
anything about Diouana?
Look.
It's like she's wasting away.
Maybe it's the climate.
After all...
The climate! She's
lazy, that's all.
The children will be back soon.
We have to think about that.
Excuse me. I'm going to take a nap.
You do that. Listen, I'm not
cutting short my vacation!
I'm fed up with this life!
All you do is drink!
That has to stop when
the kids come back!
I'm going for a walk.
She wasn't like that in Dakar.
Neither was he.
When the children arrive,
who'll do the cooking and washing?
Back in Dakar they
must be saying...
“Diouana is happy in France.
She has a good life. ”
For me, France is the
kitchen, the living room,
the bathroom, and my bedroom.
Where are the people
who live in this country?
Madame told me...
“You'll see, Diouana. There
are lovely shops in France.”
Is France that black void?
What am I here?
The cook?
The cleaning woman?
The laundress?
And when the kids arrive,
what else will I have to do?
I'm all alone.
Did Madame bring me
here to shut me in?
That's why she was so
nice to me in Dakar...
giving me her old dresses...
her old slips...
Her old shoes.
I spend my life here in
the kitchen and my bedroom.
Is this what living
in France means?
Diouana, wake up!
Get up, lazybones!
Will you get up?
This isn't Africa!
Get up!
We're not in Africa!
I didn't hire you to sleep
in. The children are here now.
Diouana, come out of there!
I know you're finished!
Diouana, get out here!
Come out of there!
Come out here!
What's going on?
Diouana won't come out!
I had to make the coffee
myself! She's useless!
Soon I'll be the maid here.
- Morning, son.
- Morning, Daddy.
Go get dressed.
Perhaps a rest would do
her good. She needs one.
- What for?
- She could see the town.
She knows no one
here but the grocer.
And I'm responsible for her.
Philippe, go play outside.
Careful with your
balloon by the window!
Take those shoes off.
Don't forget you're a maid.
The kids are here
now. The picnic's over.
- Diouana, are you ill?
- No, ma'am.
Then what is it?
If you don't work, you don't eat.
If I don't eat, I don't
take care of the children.
Mail from Dakar.
Diouana, there's a letter for you.
It's from Dakar.
Shall I read it to you?
- Yes.
It's from your mother.
“Dearest daughter, this
is your mother writing.
I've had no word from
you since you left.
I got your employers'
address through Tive Correa.
My health is getting
worse by the day.
Why do you leave me penniless?
I've nothing to live on while
you squander your wages there.
I know you can't write, but I'm sure
your employer will write for you,
because she's a lady and a mother.
Didn't she give you
her cast-off clothes?
She'll write a letter for you.
You mustn't think only of yourself.
You've sent nothing since you left.
You're earning a salary.
What do you do with it?
Think of your poor mother,
who has to pay even for water.
I think of you and pray
for you and your employers.
Your mother.”
We'll send a reply.
We'll write back.
- I hope this will help.
“Dear Mother...
I received your letter...”
What else do you want to say?
Tell us what to write.
I'll keep going. Stop
me if you don't agree.
“Dear Mother, I
received your letter.
I'm in good health,
and I think of you.
Madame hasn't had time
to write on my behalf...”
It's not true. That
letter wasn't to me.
My mother didn't write it,
just like I didn't ask
Monsieur to reply for me.
And Madame is no lady.
It's because I can't write.
If I could, I'd tell all
about Madame 's “kindness. ”
I'm a prisoner here.
She's crazy! It's her own mother!
I'm their prisoner.
I don't know anyone here.
I have no family here.
That's why I'm their slave.
Go play with Diouana.
Let's go.
Diouana, you want to play?
Mom and Dad have gone out.
This mask is mine.
Madame deceived me.
Let her take care of her own son.
If she won't feed me, she
can take care of him herself.
Can I come in?
Diouana, when will my
brother and sister be back?
I don't know.
I haven't eaten. I won't work.
I'm not Madame's plaything.
They're fighting again upstairs.
That's life in France.
Why did I want to come here?
Madame had given me a
dress and a suitcase,
and I went with him for
a walk through the city.
All I could think of
was the trip ahead.
We had our picture taken.
We quarreled because he
did something I didn't like.
I got mad and walked away.
All I could think of was my trip:
I was going to France!
You think France is
prettier than this?
How would I know?
I've never been there.
Madame asked if I
wanted to go with her.
- What for?
- To look after the children.
He's angry. He's going to say...
“That's domestic slavery!”
But my mother said all
right, so I'm going to France.
To France!
FOR OUR DEAD FROM A GRATEFUL NATION
Get down from there!
That's a sacrilege!
Come down!
Don't stay up there!
You hear me?
Get down!
Hurry up!
Jump.
Come on. I'll take you to France.
- Just think.
- What?
I'm going to France
with my employer.
- What do you think you'll do there?
- I'll see the sights.
Why is he sulking?
I'm in his room. What
more does he want?
I have to go to France.
I promised Madame.
She didn't do the dishes!
Where can she be?
- How would I know?
Sleeping again!
On your feet!
Where's the mask?
Are you ill?
Do you want your money?
Here's 20,000 francs.
Honey, come look.
What's wrong with her?
I don't know. Let's
leave her alone.
Here's the mask!
It's mine!
- Let go!
- It's mine!
I said let go!
Help!
She's out of her mind!
She took down the mask.
It's hers. She gave it to you.
Ungrateful girl! After
all I've done for her!
This mask is mine.
I paid 50 francs for it.
Madame will never scold me again.
Never again will she tell
me, “Diouana, make coffee.”
Never again, “Diouana,
fix some rice.”
Never again, 'Diouana.
take off your shoes.”
Never again, "Diouana,
mash my husband's shin: "
Never again,
“Diouana, you're lazy.”
I'll never be a slave!
I didn't come here for
the apron and the money.
She'll never see me again.
She'll never scold me again.
Never again ”Diouana. ”
I'll never see them ever again.
Madame lied.
She's lied all along.
She'll never lie to me again.
Never again will she lie to me.
She wanted to keep
me here as her slave.
BLACK GIRL SLASHES THROAT
IN EMPLOYER"S BATHROOM
We're going back to Dakar.
Her bathrobe.
Excuse me.
Follow me.
This is Diouana's employer.
Come with me.
This way.
Mother, this is Diouana's employer.
This is Diouana's mother.
For you.
Here.
Take it. It's for you.
Take it!
She doesn't want
it. Keep your money.