Seibei Iguchi
Hiroyuki Sanada
Tomoe
Rie Miyazawa
Directed by
Yoji Yamada
Not that way.
No, no, no!
Thank you. You may go.
After a long illness
my mother died...
...when I was five.
She had consumption...
...so from when I can remember
I wasn't allowed near her.
Thus I have almost no memory
of my mother.
Ito...Ito...
You poor little darling!
I am from Unasaka, in the northeast
in what is now Yamagata Prefecture.
Before 1868 it was the castle town
of the Unasaka clan...
...a small fief of 70,000 koku
of rice per year.
Well done, one and all.
That's it for today.
Sakaguchi...
I've heard there's a good
drinking place in Hakkenmachi...
Oh, you mean "Hisago"?
Feel like a drink?
A fine idea.
Kawanami, will you come?
I will.
Iguchi?
For a change?
Not me, thanks.
We can't twist your arm?
If you'll excuse me...
Twilight's not very exciting,
is he?
With a sick wife, two young daughters
and an aged mother in his care...
...my father was unable
to drink with his colleagues.
He had to hurry home
every evening at dusk.
I was told the men
he worked with...
...gave him the cruel nickname
of "Twilight Seibei".
THE TWILIGHT SAMURAI
Ito...
Father!
Up you go!
Your face is dirty.
Father's back!
Welcome home.
Codfish stew tonight, Kayano?
Don't drop it.
I'm home, Mother
How are you this evening?
Of what household are you, sir?
I am Seibei Iguchi of the
Unasaka Clan, Castle Stores.
I see...
She's getting worse. She doesn't
even know her own son!
Kayano, I've simmered
some burdock. Take some.
Thank you. You're always
so kind to my daughters.
Naota...you can go home now.
Yup.
Good evening.
But Yazaki, can't we do something
about Twilight?
His kimono's all ripped
and hardly ever takes a bath.
There's this smell
when you get close to him.
It just won't do!
Yes, sir. We all find it
very hard to stomach.
We've asked around about
finding him a new wife...
...but no woman would want
his situation.
Indeed!
He's got two young girls
a senile old mother...
...and 20 of his 50 koku
gone in debt.
Any woman who went to him
would have to take in work.
Yes, he owes money
all over the place.
I don't know how he paid for
his wife's funeral.
Not even selling your sword
would pay for a funeral like that.
A funeral! That's something
I have to worry about, too.
My father's not going to
last much longer.
Kawanami's lucky.
Young parents and a pretty wife!
You'd better go easy with her.
It could hurt your work.
Is that why you're always
cat-napping on the job?
I am not!
Listen to him!
Kumi...
Welcome!
Isn't she gorgeous!
Kume...
Bed-time, Gran.
Good night, Seibei.
Good night.
It looks like
she remembered me.
"The Master said: To rule a land
of a thousand chariots..."
Kayano...
That's Confucius, isn't it?
When did you start learning that?
At the end of last month.
The teacher says...
...from now on even girls
will need book learning.
That's good.
When I was a boy I read Confucius
over and over again.
Father...
If I learn to do
needlework...
...someday I can make kimonos.
But what good will
book learning ever do me?
Well, it probably won't ever be
as useful as needlework.
But you know...
...book learning gives you
the power...
...to think.
However the world might change,
if you have the power to think...
...you'll always survive somehow.
That's true for boys
and for girls.
All right?
Yes.
Keep reading, then.
"Tseng Tzu said: Each day
in three ways...
"...I ask myself...
"...if I have faithfully carried out
what I undertook for another..."
My mother's illness had left
my father deep in debt.
As Grandmother lost her wits, all the
housework, the gathering of fuel...
...and the field work fell to him.
Left with little time
to attend to himself...
...he gradually became
unkempt and grimy.
As his daughter, I felt terrible
about this.
Wipe off that dust!
They're coming!
His Lordship attends!
Kawanami! Quick!
Provisions.
Vital stores of food for when
the clan must fight, or the castle...
...is besieged.
Next we have the Salt Storehouse...
Here you have your beans
green, soy and red...
We pay particular attention
to keeping them dry.
Dried giant horse-radish
dried fiddleheads, miso paste...
Kusaka!
This is dried codfish...
...very important provisioning
in times of war.
How much have we got?
Iguchi...
Iguchi? You may answer
directly.
By your leave. We have
760 strips...
...by weight approximately
120 kan.
How long does it keep?
Between five and ten years.
This here is the oldest
we have.
It was acquired
six years ago.
This dried cod from Kansaki is best.
It holds its taste for ten years.
That strange smell I noticed,
is it you?
Clan retainers must serve
as examples to the common folk.
Keep yourself clean.
Yes, Milord!
Carry on.
Idiot!
Sir, I...
I'll speak to you later.
But...
Be quiet!
Iguchi!
You damn fool!
The story spread
throughout the castle.
My father became
a laughingstock.
My Great-Uncle came from
the main house in a foul humor.
Hello!
Seibei!
It's Uncle...
I'm in for it now.
Is anybody here?
What, are you all dead?!
Coming!
Kayano, make some tea.
Who is it?
Great-Uncle!
Disgraceful!
You appeared before His Lordship
unbathed, smelling like dried cod.
The unpleasant impression
you created...
...shames the house of Iguchi.
That was inexcusable.
I went to Senior Retainer Terauchi
and apologized for you.
His Lordship is a generous man
so he did not find fault.
Had that been his father, though...
...this would have meant
hara-kiri!
I never dreamed
it would cause so much trouble.
I beg your forgiveness.
Kayano?
How old are you now?
I am ten years old.
Are you working at
your lessons?
I'm learning needlework
and Confucius.
A girl has no need
of the classics.
All you need is
to write women's script.
Too much book learning
and you'll never be a bride.
You can go.
I am here today
on an important matter.
A marriage arrangement.
You need a hard-working wife
to escape the misery you are in.
A village-headman acquaintance
has an unmarried daughter...
...whom he agrees
to marry to you.
He knows you are poor, have two
young daughters and a senile mother.
I'm sure you realize that you are
in no position to demand beauty.
You need a healthy wife with
big haunches to bear children.
Her face is of no concern.
So I'll proceed with this,
if you don't mind.
With all due respect
I must differ.
How?
I am not nearly as miserable
in my living as you may think.
Of course, offending His Lordship
by appearing unbathed before him...
...was wrong, and I vow
never to repeat it.
However...
...watching my daughters
as they grow day by day is...
...how shall I put it?
It's like watching crops ripen
or flowers grow in a field.
I enjoy it very much.
I'm not sure if the lady
of whom you speak...
...would understand that.
Who would understand
such foolishness?!
You've always been like this...
...tormenting your poor father
with this prattling of yours!
What has your marriage
got to do with crops in a field?
Then I beg leave
to speak more clearly.
I ask that you not concern yourself
with questions of my marriage.
You defy the main branch
of your family?!
You are welcome here.
Kinu...are you well?
I am, thank you.
May I ask of which household
you come?
I'm your damn brother!
Take her away, Seibei.
She's a nuisance.
Mother...
Most unseemly! What will
the neighbors think?
Tie her to a post somewhere!
"Expect no more help from me!"...
...shouted my great-uncle
as he left in high dudgeon.
Can you do that?
Let me see.
Here...twist it
as you fit it in.
Is Gran asleep?
Yes.
Good.
Father...
Gran was crying, you know.
Uncle shouted at her.
Poor Gran!
Do you like Uncle?
You don't?
I hate him.
He came to talk about a new wife
for me, but I said no.
I don't want to take
any help from him.
You'd think we were
buying a cow!
"All she needs is to be healthy."
That's rude to the lady as well.
Are you two lonely...
...without a mother?
I'm not lonely, if you're here.
Me, too.
That's my girls.
Do you want the toilet, Gran?
Look!
Butterbur buds!
Get lots, all right?
What's that?
A child!
The poor thing!
He's nothing but bones!
Where'd he come from?
Matsukawa, maybe.
Rise to Buddha!
As children
we loved to go gathering herbs...
...by the river
in early spring.
But those were times
of famine.
The cold meltwater often brought
the bodies of peasants...
...dead of starvation.
Aim...
Fire!
All of you, watch me
Elbows up...
Brace the right knee...
Seibei! Sorry to keep you
waiting.
You went to Kyoto?
Yes, with the Majordomo to talk
to merchants there and in Osaka.
What's Kyoto like?
I had high hopes for it
but it was horrible.
I've never seen the like
of Miyako-oji Boulevard.
Filthy masterless samurai from
all over the country everywhere...
...cursing and swearing
in dialects you can't understand.
Then someone shouts "Divine
punishment!" and the swords come out.
The Kamo River's full of headless
corpses all swollen up...
I thought it'd be geishas in Gion...
Dear me!
Prime!
Aim!
Fire!
Misfire!
Wait! What's wrong?
Ow!
Fool!
I told you to wait!
They're a bit late.
The Choshu clan may have been
beaten once,
but they'll be back with Satsuma.
They'll snuff out 250 years of
Shoguns like the wind does a candle.
What's our clan doing?
Our leaders aren't thinking!
How would you like
to go to Kyoto?
The Emperor's palace
is short of guards.
I'll recommend you.
You'll see how things are.
Someone like you shouldn't be
stuck in a field here right now.
I'm afraid
you over-estimate me.
The times are changing.
When they do, I'll give up
samurai status and be a farmer.
That's what I'm suited for.
You're a strange one.
But you always were.
No ambition at all.
Oh, I nearly forgot...
My condolences
on your bereavement.
Burn a joss stick for her.
You didn't have to...
I wanted to send my sister
to the funeral in my place,...
...but she was having
some troubles of her own.
I'm sorry.
Miss Tomoe? What's wrong?
You know she married the son
of Captain Koda...
It turns out this Toyotaro
is a mean drunk.
If I'd known
I'd never have agreed.
A mean drunk?
He'd hit her, kick her...
She'd come running
to my house to get away.
I was worried
one day he'd kill her...
...so I got the Castle
to order them divorced.
Divorced?
Just recently.
So now Tomoe's
back at my house.
Really?
And here I thought she was the wife
of a fine 1200-koku samurai.
I had no idea.
I made a mistake. She's gone
through hell because of me.
Well done, one and all.
That's it for today.
Sakaguchi...
Sakaguchi! Feel like
dropping in at "Hisago"?
You want to see O-Kume!
Quiet!
You come too, Kawanami.
Again?
Damn right!
I'll be going.
Iguchi...
You should come see the girls.
Take your mind off things.
I'm fine, thanks.
Iguchi...
Don't waste your breath.
Look, Naota. The azaleas are out.
Yup.
Kayano, Ito, I'm home!
No one's here...
Welcome home.
It's been a long time.
Uh...perhaps there's...um...
You were out
when I came by...
Have you forgotten me?
I'm Iinuma's younger sister, Tomoe.
Oh, Miss Tomoe!
I didn't know you.
I've just seen your brother today.
He told me what had happened.
So you know all about it, then?
Yes.
Because of that I'm back
living at his house.
There's nothing for me to do
so they have me weaving.
I came here to escape.
You're very welcome.
Let's go inside.
Your sock...
Oh, yes...
It seems your father
had forgotten me!
We always played together!
Welcome home.
Kayano, Ito, this is Miss Tomoe.
We're, uh...
Childhood friends.
He always used to tease me.
I did not!
I got a present.
Me, too.
Aren't they pretty!
Mother, I'm home.
Welcome home.
Do you know this lady?
She's Miss Tomoe,
the Iinuma girl.
See? She remembered me.
That's good. And of course
you remember me, don't you?
Of which household are you?
I'm your son.
You are, are you?
Hello.
Tane, watch the hotpot.
It was as if our house was brighter
from the moment Miss Tomoe arrived.
I've never forgotten.
It was when I was five.
I always wanted to do
whatever the boys did.
Once I was climbing a pine tree
and a branch broke...
...and I got hurt.
Really?
Yes! Your father happened
to be there that day...
...and he carried me piggy-back
all the way to the doctor!
I think he was 12 or 13.
His back was this big!
Just like a grown-up's.
He made me feel so safe...
Do you remember, Seibei?
I remember
something like that...
When I was nine
my mother told me...
...I couldn't play
with boys any more.
I was so sad...
Being a girl’s no fun, Kayano.
Drip, drip drip...
...come our Chonbei's tears.
Drip, drip, drip...
Let's catch his falling tears...
...and wipe them away...
Wipe them away...
Let's take his
tear-soaked kimono...
...and wash it clean...
Wash it clean...
Let's take the kimono
we've washed...
...and wring it out...
Wring it out...
Let's take the kimono
we've wrung out...
...and hang it to dry...
Hang it to dry...
You haven't changed
at all, have you.
It's as if I'm
a completely different person.
That's not true.
You still smile
just like you used to.
You don't have to console me.
I know I've changed.
People told me how radiant
a bride you were...
...when you went to
the Koda house.
I don't want to remember.
It's very late.
I'll leave you here.
Say hello to your brother.
Your beard's growing out...
It's so soft!
Iinuma! I want the truth!
That man's here!
My husband...
My ex-husband...I'd know
that drunken voice anywhere.
I'm going!
Your master's leaving.
Hands off!
I'm not drunk!
My sandals!
Iinuma! Where's Tomoe gone?
I told you, she's at her aunt's.
You're lying!
Please! Keep your voice down!
There are elderly people here!
To hell with her.
Listen, Iinuma...
If I'm not good enough for Tomoe,
she's welcome to leave.
But Iinuma...
...I've got a bone to pick
with you.
You went to His Lordship
and got him to divorce us.
Squire Koda, I've told you
time and time again...
Shut up!
You made me a joke
in front of the whole castle!
I demand satisfaction!
Squire Koda!
My sword!
Stop this, will you?!
Tomoe...
Where've you been
till this hour of the night?
Where I go is no one's business
but mine.
And I'll say this, too.
I am not your wife now.
It's "Miss Tomoe" to you.
Tomoe! Get inside!
Perhaps that's enough?
Who are you?!
I am Seibei Iguchi,
friend to Iinuma.
Perhaps I could accept
your challenge in his name?
But here we are in the town.
And you are drunk.
Let's settle this another time,
when the alcohol has worn off.
If you've put yourself forward
this way...
...you must know how to fight.
I make no such claim.
Fine. We fight tomorrow.
Tomorrow?
By the river behind Hannyaji
Temple, at the 8th hour?
Done.
Behind Hannyaji, 8th hour.
See you.
Seibei, he's serious!
Are you?
I had no choice.
He's good with a sword.
It'll work out.
I'll say good night.
Don't tell Tomoe about this.
Wait!
What if you kill him?
The Clan forbids dueling.
I'll think of something.
Good night.
Naota...
We're going.
Ito!
Yu Tzu said: Harmony is the
greatest beneficence of the rites.
Good morning.
Sit down!
I'm leaving.
This is no good. I'm slow.
You think you can take me?
Damn right!
Then get ready.
He's afraid!
Hold it!
I said last night
I'd take your place!
I should do this.
You're no match for him.
Go over there and watch
I'm sorry I'm late, Squire Koda.
I will be your opponent.
What's that stick?
My school of swordfighting
uses this for practice.
Do you mock me?
Draw your sword!
A sword might kill.
This stick will not.
It will break bones at worst.
I won't take this from a samurai
of your rank! I'll cut you down!
Watch for the draw-and-slash!
You can still apologize.
The apology is yours to make.
With a real sword, you'd be dead.
Do you apologize?
Or do you continue?
Splash some water on him.
That'll bring him to.
Come on, Iinuma.
You're all right?
Don't tell Miss Tomoe
about this.
Or anyone else, either.
Those men will talk.
No. A whipped dog
doesn't bark.
Is that soy sauce? Over here.
Excuse me for interrupting. I am
Zenemon Yogo, Master of the Watch.
I know that.
Are you the "Twilight Seibei"
who thrashed Toyotaro Koda...
...and left him with
a great big lump on his head?
I didn't really "thrash" him.
He asked for a match, and my
sword caught him on the head.
Koda is a drinking companion
of mine.
The other day...
...he came crying to me, asking
if I would take revenge for him.
That's the kind of man he is.
But it seems you can fight.
What school are you?
Many years ago I trained
under Toda-Sensei.
So you're a disciple
of Jinsai Toda?
I merely attended his dojo.
Perhaps we could
try a match one day.
I'd be no match for you
I'm afraid. If you'll excuse me...
I wish I wasn't getting old.
I can't read once the sun sets.
First your teeth go,
then it's your eyes.
And how's number three?
That went long ago!
That's it for today, everyone.
I'll be going.
Excuse me.
Sir Twilight's gone?
Didn't you hear?
The other day "Sir Twilight" fought
the son of Captain Koda.
A fight? And what happened?
Wood against steel.
Sir Twilight went bang!
Knocked him senseless.
He did?
I always thought he was strange.
I never thought
he was a fighter, though.
Maybe we shouldn't
be calling him "Sir Twilight".
You think he knows?
Sure he does.
Fumi! It's raining!
It's raining!
Is the laundry in?
Yes!
Welcome home.
Miss Tomoe was here.
She left you this letter.
She's got even nicer writing
than the schoolmaster.
Let me!
No!
I have finally learned what happened
from my elder brother.
I must apologize
for all the trouble...
...I have caused you.
I am, however, delighted.
I very much want to see you
and thank you in person.
Today I intruded upon you and
with your daughters...
...cleaned your house
and did your laundry.
Please do not scold your daughters
for allowing me in.
I would like in the future
to be of what use I can.
Written in haste,
To: Seibei Iguchi, Esq.
From: Tomoe
Tomoe started coming
every second day or so.
The two of us looked forward
to coming home from school.
We're back!
Hello!
You know what the teacher
did today? He farted out loud!
She cleaned with us,
did laundry with us...
...and taught us to cook.
On rainy days we'd practice
calligraphy and sewing.
And she'd tell us all kinds
of stories, the like of which...
...we'd never heard before.
Finished.
Bring this line over.
Finished!
That's good, Ito!
Hey! Stop it!
Ito! Write on
your own paper, all right?
No!
Don't you look nice!
How much fun it was to go off
to a festival in kimonos...
...she had made us.
Shoo! Go away!
Samurai then were strictly
forbidden to attend the festivals...
...of the peasants
and townsfolk...
...but Tomoe cared not a whit.
I remember well what
she said:
"It was because of the peasants
that we lived as samurai."
Why are you catching them all?
We're using the same bait!
You're trying too hard.
The fish sense it.
Your shoulders are too stiff.
It's like swordfighting.
Aw, stop lecturing!
Show me your rod.
This hook's too big!
Seibei...
...I want to talk to you.
It's about Tomoe.
She's had a few proposals.
She's beautiful and talented.
There's not many like her in our clan.
Any good ones?
She won't say yes
and I can't pressure her.
I asked her, half in jest
if she'd like to marry you.
You what?!
We may be old friends,
but that isn't funny!
She didn't take it as a joke.
She said she wouldn't mind...
...and turned all red.
That's enough!
You're both making fun of me!
You dolt!
She was serious.
Stop it.
Listen...
...I've already put her through hell
marrying her to Koda.
If it's all right with you,
I'd like to make that up to her.
It's a bit sudden...
I don't need an answer now,
but I will within two or three days.
I might have to go to Edo.
You've been really busy lately.
What's going on?
You probably haven't heard.
His Lordship's dead.
A month ago.
He is?
Why have they kept that
from us?
They're not agreed on
who's going to succeed him.
The Castle Warden, Lord Hori
has asked the Shogun...
...for permission to adopt
His Lordship's third boy, Tadaatsu...
...and seize control himself.
If that happens the clan will split
and blood will wash away blood.
I might not come through this
unscathed myself.
So if you could give me an answer
before I leave for Edo.
All right.
I'll answer you.
I'm very grateful to Tomoe for
all she's done for my daughters...
...all the cooking and sewing
and everything else.
It's like a dream come true.
However...
...having her come to my house
as my wife is something else again.
She's a daughter of the Iinumas,
a 400-koku family.
She doesn't know what life is like
for a 50-koku petty samurai.
Are you sure you're not
under-estimating her?
She's very much her own woman.
It'd be fine at the start,
but when it sunk in that 50-koku
would be her life forever...
...she'd be sorry.
My late wife was.
Hers was a 150-koku family.
She never got used to
the fall in status.
Rise in the world, she told me
or my family will grieve.
She said that all the time
after she got sick.
I don't want to put Tomoe
through that torment.
Tomoe's not 15 or 16.
I'm sure she'd thought about
what she said.
No more.
Let's forget this.
Let's try up there.
It's a girl!
What a stink!
Rise to Lord Buddha.
Eat your fill in heaven!
Let's call it a day.
From that day forward
Miss Tomoe stopped coming...
...to our house.
Make way!
Stand aside!
Turning left!
The Warden has returned!
Go!
What's that?!
It's the alarm!
Stop what you're doing and listen.
I have important news
from Lord Hori, Castle Warden...
...who returned
this morning from Edo.
The 12th head of the Unasaka Clan
Lord Tadatomo, died of measles...
...at the beginning of this month.
He was 32 years old.
He was a good and wise ruler
intelligent and tolerant...
...a true hero.
Only last spring we had
the honor of meeting him...
...and having him speak to us.
Iguchi, you haven't
forgotten that, I'm sure.
What a fine and gentle man
he was!
Senior retainers will
remain in the castle.
The rest of you are to leave and pray
for the repose of His Lordship's soul.
This could mean open war!
I doubt that...
...but Lord Hori's sure to go after
His Lordships reformers
Dispositions?
Yes.
Which side is
our Commissioner on?
The reformers
or the Hori faction?
He'll be with the mainstream.
Just like me.
While there were fearsome rumors
that the Castle was preparing for war,...
...it didn't seem to involve
a petty samurai like my father.
All right?
We wanted to ask Father
why Miss Tomoe no longer came...
...but for some reason,
we couldn't.
This was because even in
our children's hearts...
...we knew something
had happened between them.
Squire Iguchi!
I'm sorry you've come for nothing.
My husband isn't back from Edo.
I expect him in a day or two.
Has he written anything about
what's happening in Edo?
No.
There was a letter yesterday,...
...but all he talked about was what
he wants to eat when he gets home.
That's good.
I'm sure you know
they're handing down dispositions.
Some people have even been
ordered to commit suicide.
I was worried about what
might have happened to Iinuma.
I'm happy to hear he's all right.
Give him my regards
when he gets home.
You came just for that?
Yes.
Good day.
It was very kind of you.
Carry on.
Where's Squire Iguchi?
He went away.
Where are you going?
Squire Iguchi may still be
close by.
Why do you want to see him?
No reason in particular.
I haven't seen him for a while.
I'd like to say hello.
Wait!
Tomoe...
...it is unseemly for
a young woman to be seen talking...
...with some samurai on the street.
And you are a returned bride
with a proposal being discussed.
You shouldn't be doing that
in broad daylight with people around.
I've been meaning to tell you that
for a long time now.
What's wrong with a girl
talking to a samurai?
Are you questioning
your elder brother's wife?
Shouldn't I?
You should not.
A young women
does not question her elders.
With 60 from last month
that comes to 550 mon.
Could I have a receipt?
You know the bath fee went up
to seven mon last month.
Prices are going up everywhere.
Could you pay more
for these cages?
With things as unsettled
as they are...
...no one's buying insect cages.
Could you ask your boss
for me?
Well, I'll ask.
I take this work
as seriously as my duties.
I understand that.
If you'll excuse me.
Come on.
We're not thieves.
We're just picking up some
insect cages from Squire Iguchi.
Is he doing piece-work?
Hello!
Who is it?
Commissioner Kusaka.
It's very late, I know.
I'd like you to accompany me
to Lord Hori's quarters.
Yes, sir.
They said you don't need
full formal dress.
Just a hakama skirt.
So you're Iguchi's girl?
How old are you?
Five.
You're a sweetheart.
I'm ready.
Kayano...you all get to bed.
Let's sleep.
Seibei Iguchi
of the Castle Stores...
That'll do.
Iguchi, come over here.
We called you here this late,
because an awkward situation has arisen.
You know there was a revolt
among our retainers in Edo?
Yes, sir.
Fortunately no word of this
reached the Shogun.
His Lordship ordered Shima Hasegawa
and his faction to commit suicide.
But one of Lord Hasegawa's men
Zenemon Yogo, Master of the Watch...
...says he was merely following
the orders of his superior...
...asks why he should be punished
and refuses to commit suicide.
"If you want me dead
come and kill me!", he says!
And with these disgraceful words
has barricaded himself in his house.
This evening we sent our Master
of Foot, Genba Hattori, against him.
Zenemon Yogo! I come
at the order of the clan!
But he died himself.
He's a "one-sword" fighter.
No one in the clan
is his match.
We were talking about who
to send against him...
...and your name came up.
Iguchi, raise your head.
You're a "short-sword" fighter
of the Toda school?
It's been years
since Toda-Sensei taught me.
I merely attended his dojo.
We don't have time
for modesty.
We've learned that you were
an instructor at his dojo.
He must be beaten inside his house.
The short sword will help there.
That is another reason
we have chosen you.
Kill Zenemon Yogo
by twilight tomorrow.
That is an order from
the clan's Senior Retainer.
Kusaka...what's this man's stipend?
50 koku.
20 koku bespoken
for a net of 30.
That must be hard, with two young
daughters and an aged mother.
Bring us the head
of Zenemon Yogo...
...and life will be easier.
Do you accept?
Answer him.
This is an honor.
You shut up!
Well?
By your leave...
I am ashamed to say that
over many years of hardship...
...with two daughters, a sick wife
and an aged mother...
...I have lost the desire
to wield a sword.
A serious fight,
the killing of a man...
...requires animal ferocity and
calm disregard for one's own life.
I have neither of those
within me now.
Perhaps in a month...
...alone with the beasts in the hills
I could get them back.
But tomorrow, I am afraid
is completely impossible.
I ask that you extend
the honor of this commission...
...to another man.
What complete
and utter nonsense!
We are not here for foolishness
from a petty samurai!
Your clan orders you
to kill Yogo.
Do you understand that?!
The Clan's orders are
His Lordship's orders.
The very thought of refusal
is an offense!
You are relieved of your post!
You are expelled from the clan!
Please, Warden...
What do you say, Iguchi?
Do you accept?
Of course he does!
Don't you?
May I request
an evening or two...
...in which to give my answer?
You may not!!
You will answer now!
I obey.
I accept the commission...
...to kill Zenemon Yogo.
Well said!
An officer will call
at the hour of the snake.
Have your preparations made.
Withdraw.
Iguchi...
Don't worry. Who's Zenemon
Yogo anyway?
You're sure to win.
I have decided exactly that.
Good.
One should, however
always prepare for the worst.
That's true. The worst
can always happen.
In that event, Commissioner,
this will be farewell.
Thank you for everything
you've done for me.
Please convey my regards
to my colleagues in the stores.
I understand. And, uh...
...I'll take responsibility for
those you leave behind.
I'll see they are looked after.
That's a relief to hear.
All the best to you.
A strange noise made me
open my eyes.
Looking for the sound, I saw
my father sharpening his sword.
He looked so strange it was hard
to believe he was my father.
I still remember clearly
how he looked that night.
The Heart Sutra:
The bodhisative clearly saw
the emptiness of the five states...
...thus relieving misfortune and pain.
Form is only emptiness,
emptiness only form...
We're going.
Kayano!
The Master said: a man cunning
of word and smiling of face...
...is rarely benevolent.
Tseng Tzu said: Each day...
Naota, do something for me.
Yup.
You know Miss Tomoe's house
in Nishikicho, don't you?
Yup.
Go there, and speak to
Miss Tomoe.
Now, this is important.
You have to see
Miss Tomoe herself.
And then say...
..."I'm really very sorry, but
could you come right away?
"I'll explain why
when you get here."
All right?
I'm really very sorry...
...but could you come
right away?
I'll explain why...
Uh, I'll explain why...
I'll explain why
when you get here.
When you get here.
That's fine. Hurry!
Look where she laid her egg!
Could you come...
I'll explain why
when you get here.
Whatever's the matter
at this hour?
I'm really very sorry...
...but could you come
right away?
When you get here...uh...
He'll explain why?
Squire Seibei sent you
to tell me that?
All right. I'll get ready.
I didn't think you'd come.
The clan has ordered me
to go and fight...
...another retainer.
I'm going out under orders,
so I must be properly dressed...
...and I can't do my hair alone.
I'm in a bind,
so I asked you to come.
If you can spare the time,
could you help me?
When do you have to go?
The hour of the snake.
There's not much time.
Where's your kimono?
It's laid out over there.
Naota, boil some water.
Who's coming for you?
A clan officer.
Naota, will you wait
out by the gate?
Sit down. I'll comb your hair.
May I ask why...
...you're going out to fight?
I can't refuse a clan order.
Petty I may be,
but I'm still a samurai.
Bamboo baskets, hampers!
Your elder brother...
...asked if I would
take you as my wife.
I refused.
Did you know that?
Yes, I did.
But...
But since that day...
...when I told him no...
...I've started thinking
about you.
Now I think of it
ever since we were small...
...and I made dolls
to give you...
...I always dreamed one day
you'd come to me as my wife.
That dream stayed with me
even after I got married...
...and you married Koda.
It's never faded.
I'm going out now
to fight to the death.
I'm going to win
and return to this house.
At that time, if I were
to ask you...
...to be my wife...
...would you accept?
A few days ago I had
a proposal...
...from a retainer in Aizu.
I accepted.
I've been very rude.
I should never have asked you
to come here.
No.
I'm happy that you asked me.
I've been a fool.
Please forget everything
I've said.
Really? A retainer from Aizu...
That sounds like.
Are they here?
Yup.
Well, I'll be going.
Thank you very much
for everything.
Um...
...I'm afraid I can't wait here
until you come back.
I pray with all my heart...
...that luck is with you
and you come back safely.
Naota, see Miss Tomoe home
when she goes.
Take care of the kids.
Mrs Iguchi...
...how are you today?
Fine, thank you.
Of which household
would you be the daughter?
Me?
I am...
...Squire Seibei's
childhood friend...
...Tomoe.
Sir...
Squire Iguchi?
Zenemon Yogo has closed himself in
with the shutters down.
That is Genba Hattori,
Master of Foot.
We should remove
his corpse...
...but no one can get in.
Take care.
Zenemon Yogo is no longer human.
He is a beast!
Leave to enter!
Sir Twilight...
So they sent you?
Zenemon Yogo...by order of
the clan, I come for your life.
Draw your sword, please.
Have a drink?
I know you're all keyed up,
but I'm going to run.
Run?
Yep.
I want you let me get away.
If you please.
I didn't expect that from the clan's
best one-sword man.
My orders are to kill you.
I can't let you escape.
Don't be so impatient.
You can kill me any time.
I'd like to talk to you.
Have a seat.
It's a nice day.
Sit down.
What's going on?
They're talking.
Even if you escaped
where would you go?
Over that mountain and I'm out
of the clan's domain.
There are masterless samurai
everywhere.
I can lose myself in them,
go to Kyoto, to Edo...
If I do that for a few years...
...the world will have changed.
The samurai's day is done.
This isn't the time
for that talk.
Pick up your sword, please.
I am under orders
from the clan to...
Like hell!
You're the clan's errand boy
out to claim a reward.
Have a drink.
I was an errand boy, too.
I served Lord Shigemasa Toki.
Twelve years ago he was ordered
to commit suicide...
...after a power struggle
within his clan.
Then I wandered for seven years
with my wife and daughter...
...in search of a new situation.
Seven?
With no income?
Of course not.
I did manual labor and helped
peasants plant and harvest...
...to get a little rice.
Or we'd slink into a temple
and beg alms there sometimes.
Three years ago the Unasaka clan
made me an official retainer...
...but by then hardship
had killed my wife.
I'm good with a sword,
but I'm hard to get along with...
...and I can't hold my liquor.
But this time I promised myself
it'd be different.
I would do my duty
as a true Unasaka retainer.
I worked hard to do that.
My superior was
Lord Shima Hasegawa.
He liked me, and did
all he could for me.
To me...
...the tasks he assigned were
the tasks of the clan.
His orders were the clan's orders
and I carried them out faithfully.
What was wrong with that,
Twilight?
Why do I have to
cut open my stomach?
I haven't come here
to answer...
...that kind of question.
I heard your wife died
of consumption. Is that true?
I'm surprised you know that.
And her fever went up
as night came on?
Yes.
Consumption is a hard disease.
And it's catching.
My daughter died of consumption
caught from her mother.
You're not the only one
who's suffered.
How old was your daughter?
Sixteen.
When she should have been
a bud swelling into bloom...
...she died...
...nothing but skin and bones.
A sad, sad sight.
I'm very sorry to hear that.
Her ashes.
She was a pretty girl
with pale skin.
I guess Lord Hasegawa
took pity on me.
He gave me money for a funeral
well above my station.
If only for that...
...I'm very much in
Lord Hasegawa's debt.
What's your stipend?
50 koku.
A sick wife, and children
all on 50 koku?
That must be hard.
Doctor and medicine alone cost
a ryo and 2 bu a month.
Piece work wouldn't cover that.
I borrowed from relatives
but it still wasn't enough.
Sometimes we didn't even have
tomorrow's rice left.
I know how bad it feels to see
the bottom of your rice chest.
You've had hard times, too.
Where I really ran into trouble
was at my wife's funeral.
The family's main branch wanted
a funeral that wouldn't shame them.
I couldn't afford it.
I was desperate
so I finally sold my sword.
It was a fine sword
I'd inherited from my father...
...but I figured
the age of the sword was over.
I'm afraid this is just bamboo.
You're going to kill me
with a bamboo sword?
No.
I learned short-sword
from Toda-Sensei
I meant to fight with that.
Short-sword?
You mean to kill me
with some kind of cheap trick?
You're not taking me seriously,
are you?
Wait!
I won't have it!
I only told you that because
you wanted me to let you go!
Draw!
Sir!
You're very good...
If you want to run,
now's your chance.
After I kill you.
Draw!
Sir! There's still time
to stop.
Calm down and think!
You haven't rested
since yesterday.
You're already breathing hard.
You mock me.
Sir! Continue this
and I'll cut you down.
Is that what you want?
That's fine by me.
Draw.
You've cut me, Twilight.
This is what you get
for taking me lightly.
Have a seat.
Will you let me go,
Twilight?
That was...
...my intention.
It's dark.
I can't see.
Hell.
Twilight...
Is it over?
It's all yours.
Careful!
He's dead!
Ito...
Go buy some tofu.
Don't lose the money.
Miss Kayano!
It's the Master!
Ito...
...I'm home.
Miss Tomoe! Father's back!
You're still here...
Thank heaven!
I was sure...
...you were dead!
Finally Miss Tomoe
became our mother.
My father was happy.
But peace prevailed in our house
for less than three years.
With the Meiji Restoration
came civil war.
Our clan supported
the former Shogun...
...and fought as rebels
against the emperor's government.
During this "Boshin War"...
...my father was shot
and killed
Tomoe took us, her step-daughters
to Edo, now "Tokyo"...
...and supported us
until we were both married.
Now she sleeps with my father
beneath this stone.
In the new Meiji era, many men
who had worked with my father...
...rose to positions
of great authority.
I often heard them say...
...that "Twilight Seibei
was an unlucky man."
But I do not agree.
My father had no desire
to rise in the world...
...and I don't think
he considered himself unlucky.
He loved his daughters...
...and the beautiful Tomoe
loved him.
His life, I think
was short but full.
I am proud to have had
such a father.