Produced by
Jeonwonsa Film Co.
Cast: Jung Jae-young, Kim Min-hee,
Youn Yuh-jung, Gi Ju-bong,
Choi Hwa-jeong, Yoo Jun-sang,
Seo Young-hwa, Go Ah-sung.
Hong Sang-soo's 17th feature film.
Subtitles by: youtube.com/MySweetSeoul
I. RIGHT THEN, WRONG NOW
It's my first time in Suwon.
I walked to the market square,
in front of the Haenggung Palace.
There was a coffeeshop across the street,
so I bought myself a cup of coffee.
Wow, she's really pretty!
That little thing...
So slender and youthful.
I have to be careful.
She's too pretty.
- Aren't you tired?
- No...
- Are you all right?
- Yes, I'm okay.
- But, is that a sledding rink over there?
- That one? Yes, it is.
- Can I smoke, too?
- Sure, go ahead.
It's amazing that there's a
sledding rink in a place like this.
Aren't you hungry?
Well, I'm a bit hungry,
but I was thinking about going there.
I can't believe there's
a sledding rink here.
That's true.
Director, can I be your
Assistant Director?
Of course, I would be grateful.
But you've been an Assistant Director
three times already.
You're still not confident enough?
- I'm not sure if you believe me or not, but...
- What?
For me, you sir are the
most important film director.
It's true, even if you don't believe me.
I'm not the type of person who
recieves compliments very often.
But I really appreciate it.
Don't mention it. When I'm lonely,
you sir give me strength.
While watching your works, I say to myself:
"Thanks to these films, my life is worth living!".
I really think of it that way.
The weather is quite warm today.
- Doesn't feel like it's winter, right?
- Indeed! This weather...
It's warm, it really is.
- Shall we go?
- Sure.
Sorry!
- Are you okay?
- Yes, don't worry.
Wanna ride?
Is it fun?
Maybe because I stood still,
but this time it ran smoothly.
- How much?
- 1500 Won.
- Have a good day.
- Thank you.
We parted ways after eating some Kalguksu.
I told her I'm a bit tired and I need to rest.
I promised to take her to Suwon's
Chicken Alley if I get bored tonight.
But even if I get bored,
I don't think I'll call her.
I have to be careful.
It's just a day.
Bok-Nae-Dang
The characters for
"Fortune" and "Inside".
"Fortune springs from the inside"?
Fortune arises from within...
I'm not sure.
- Press here.
- Got it.
Get ready.
One, two...
One more.
After walking up and down,
I returned to Boknaedang.
It's the most beautiful place around here.
This person was still here?
Is it tasty?
Yes, it is.
It's Banana Milk.
What are you doing here?
What does it look like I'm doing?
- You're drinking some milk.
- Yes. Great observation.
How about you,
what are you doing?
Well, I'm just sitting here.
I've come to Suwon for a movie screening.
I also have to give an oral presentation.
Are you here for a lecture?
After the screening of my film,
I will be speaking with the audience.
It's not really a lecture.
- Do you have your own movies?
- Yes.
- Are you a film director?
- Yes, that's right.
- I see.
- What do you do?
I'm not doing anything.
- I'm just drinking some milk.
- I see. So you're not doing anything.
That's right.
So, are you a famous director?
Maybe someone I know?
Oh, my name is Ham Chun-soo.
- Is that true?
- Yes.
I know you very well!
You are a very famous director!
I'm flattered.
Now I see!
That's why you looked so familiar!
Nice to meet you!
- But, are you really the director Ham Chun-soo?
- Of course.
Please, drink your milk.
- So what is your occupation?
- Me?
Currently, I'm a painter.
I've not been painting for too long,
but these days I'm only
living my life while painting.
- You even have traces of paint on your jacket!
- Yes.
You're beautiful.
Thanks...
I used to have a different occupation.
But now I only live my life while painting.
- I see.
- Yes.
Would you like to drink
a cup of coffee with me?
Somewhere nearby. A warm coffee.
- Coffee?
- Yes. I think that would be great.
- To be honest...
I think I've seen you, earlier.
When you entered,
I've seen you briefly.
- Really?
- Yes.
I was so surprised to see
that you're still here!
- Today I stayed here for quite a while.
- Yes.
So, can I buy you a coffee?
Somewhere nearby.
Come on, let's go!
Okay, let's do that.
It would be an honor, drinking
coffee with such a great director.
Thank you!
I'm the one who's thankful.
- Let's stand up, shall we?
- Yes.
I'll carry this for you.
Thank you.
It looks tasty!
Is that Jujube Tea?
Yes, they make it here, firsthand.
It's steaming-hot, wanna try it?
No, thanks a lot.
You never drink coffee?
I can drink it, but if I do,
I get really tired. I'm a little sensitive.
It really looks that way.
You really seem like a sensitive person.
Really?
- Director, you're sensitive as well.
- Me?
Well, I'm a little sensitive, too.
But you look much more sensitive.
No, I think you have
more sensitivity than me.
Really?
That's probably why you're able
to make such great films.
Thank you.
But have you seen my films?
- No, not yet.
- I see.
- I usually don't like watching movies.
- I understand.
But I heard a lot of
people praising your works.
It's nothing.
You must be an excellent director.
It's not easy for people
to offer their compliments.
And from what I heard, it's much more
than just compliments about popularity.
Thank you very much.
I'm just doing the best I can,
so I appreciate every comment.
And it's not like I'm
capable of doing much, anyway.
- Is that so?
- However...
I strongly hope that one day
I'll be able to create...
...something more beautiful,
something remarkable.
I know the feeling. I think
I'm painting for the same reason.
Yes. I think so.
Now I'm really curious about
what type of paintings you make.
If you are truly interested, I'll
show you my paintings later.
Yes, thank you!
What are you doing today?
Me? Nothing special today.
I arrived a day early, like an idiot.
I'll have to drop by the atelier today.
Really? Are you going to your atelier?
Is there some sort of problem?
No, it's just that I promised myself
to not let a day pass without painting.
I understand perfectly.
You have to do your thing.
It's not supremely important, but it's
a routine that I don't want to neglect.
- I hope you understand.
- Of course I do! A routine is very important.
If you don't stick to it, it feels
like everything is about to collapse.
Painters, in particular, are
more likely to feel this way.
My brother-in-law is a painter, too,
and he's pretty much the same.
I think so.
Doing something on a regular basis,
I think it's a great thing.
Carrying out
while easing your mind.
I envy that kind of lifestyle.
If I...
If I don't keep this promise,
I feel like I'll be completely ruined.
That's how I feel.
I'm scared. That's why
I have to keep this promise.
I understand.
Earlier, I told you that I used to
have a different occupation, right?
Yes.
- I used to have a modeling career.
- You used to be a model?
Yes.
I was earning a good amount of money...
But then I realized it's not
how I want to live my life.
I think I know the feeling.
I don't know how could I
put up with that type of work.
I had no future,
I was so anxious...
That kind of work just didn't
feel like something worthwhile.
I hated it.
I think I know what you mean.
You were doing something
which didn't suit you at all.
I always liked painting,
ever since I was little.
No one encouraged me to start painting,
But once I had white
paper and painting supplies,
my heart would start racing,
I always felt that way.
I know! I feel the same!
Once I have paper and pencil,
I feel better for no apparent reason.
- Really?
- Yes.
I just...
Motivelessly doing the things
that I can, in an innocent way...
That's what I really like.
I see.
To be able to feel it,
as I'm living my life,
To confirm it to myself,
every day, again and again...
That's how I live my life now.
- I think that's wonderful.
- Yes.
I'm always eager for more.
You know?
Do you know this sort of feeling?
Yes, oh yes!
I know it all too well!
She invited me to see her paintings,
so we went together to her atelier.
- What should we do?
- What?
I run out of coffee.
I don't drink much coffee,
so I forgot to buy.
It doesn't matter,
please don't worry.
Really? Should I go and buy some?
There's a supermarket nearby, I can go.
No, don't worry, just offer me
something that you have in here.
- Really?
- Yes.
It's right across the street,
I would come back in a minute.
No, I'm perfectly fine without it.
- Really?
- Yes.
I would come back right away...
- Do you need anything?
- No, I'm fine!
Should we buy some snacks, at least?
No, please don't. Just offer me anything
you have. Everything is fine with me.
In that case...
I will offer you some of
the tea that I usually drink.
Solomon's Seal tea,
do you like it?
Solomon's Seal tea, that's great!
It's an organic product,
so it's good for your health.
Oh, great!
For a brief moment,
in a far distance...
I feel as if I'm traveling to
a very distant place, right now.
Director, what are you thinking about?
Oh, me?
I was thinking about you.
About the painting, as well.
I still have a long way to go,
a lot of progress is still needed.
But even so, I like it.
I really like it.
I think I know what are you
trying to do with it.
You took a very difficult path.
You certainly have what it takes
to walk on this path.
This path...
There's so much to explore, here.
Stimulating your senses
in such an innocent way...
Reaching out to your mind and heart
by making use of your senses and perception...
This is the path you took.
A lot of sensitivity and courage is needed,
in order to walk on this path until the end.
That's what it feels like you're doing.
Only by looking at it...
...it makes sense.
- Wow, there's a sushi restaurant here.
- Yes, it is.
Shall we go in?
It looks great inside.
- Do you feel like eating sushi?
- Shall we?
It's not expensive, either.
It'd be great if we treat ourselves
with some sliced raw fish and soju.
What do you think?
Miss Hee-jung,
do you like raw fish?
It's fine with me.
Let us enter.
Shall we? Okay then.
Great!
- Should I pour you some more?
- Yes, please.
Just a little.
Miss Hee-jung!
You must drink too,
why aren't you drinking?
Okay, you go ahead and drink, I'll
drink too. Please pour me a glass.
- Thank you.
- Yes.
- Let's drink!
- Let's drink.
- Cheers!
Your drinking skills are no joke.
You drink really fast!
It's the first time when I see
someone drinking like this.
- You must be a real man!
- Stop teasing me.
It's the first time for me, too.
With such a beautiful lady...
It's the first time.
Really?
That's fine.
I'm glad, then.
Seriously?
Sure, when a man looks at a woman in
such a way, it's great. Why wouldn't it be?
But how much do you
see me as a woman?
I'm curious.
How much?!
Stop joking around,
how can I put that into words?
How can I even express it in words?!
The alcohol is delicious today.
Please talk some more.
About what?
If you don't talk about movies...
At this rate,
you'll get drunk.
Please don't worry,
I never get drunk.
I never got drunk in my entire life.
Look.
It's no fun once you get drunk.
You had enough of
alcohol for today?
We must drink everything
till the last drop.
Please, keep drinking.
Come on!
Drink.
- Okay, I will.
- Great, drink.
Miss Hee-jung...
Thank you very much,
for staying with me.
I truly appreciate it.
You are...
You are so beautiful.
I'm...
I'm dazzled by your beauty.
Thank you so much!
Yes, I like it, too.
I like being with you here.
Really?
If you're happy,
then I'm happy, too.
Shall we...
Shall we toast?
- Cheers!
Down the hatch!
- Did you drink it all?
- Yes, I did.
- Good job!
- Really?
Yes.
Really good job!
Proud of my friend!
My very very...
very very very very...
- ...beautiful friend!
- I like being your friend.
- That's not it...
- What?
You're much better
than just a friend!
Are you okay with that?
Sure.
What?
It doesn't matter.
Of course it does!
Miss Hee-jung...
If only...
- What should I do?
- About what?
If only...
If only I had a ring in my pocket...
- Why would you have a ring in your pocket?
- I don't, but...
I just want to express
my feelings without any constraints.
It's because I feel
too uncomfortable right now.
I'm suffocating on the inside,
I really am!
I really...
Can you explain to me
why are you so beautiful?
I feel anxious, too.
- You do?
- Yes, it's distressing.
- You feel distressed?
- Yes.
To tell you the truth,
I have no friends.
Not even one.
You don't have friends?
I have men that I meet,
I have people that I like...
I do meet with some people occasionally,
but none of them are friends.
Director...
Do you have friends?
You do, don't you?
Oh, me?
I'm sorry, my bad.
Of course you have.
So why do you think I don't have any?
Director...
Why...
Why can't I make any friends?
Don't give me that look,
you're only making me feel embarrassed.
No need to stare at me with that look.
We just have an honest conversation,
...so don't do that,
I don't need that right now.
- Don't look at me like that!
- Okay.
Sure.
- I will...
- I'm...
Miss Hee-jung...
I'll go out for a smoke.
Wanna join me?
Yes. Yes...
What are you doing?
Why did you come out?
It's cold.
I have to go somewhere,
I totally forgot, I'm sorry.
What?
You're going somewhere?
Yes, I have to meet a friend,
I totally forgot.
It's a place where you can go, too.
Do you want to come?
Where are we going?
It's her birthday, or something?
No, it's not a birthday party,
just a normal party.
She runs a café and we decided to meet this
evening, the two of us and a few other people.
I really have to be there.
What should we do?
- That's a good question.
- Do you want to come with me?
Will you come with me or not?
- No, no...
- Don't worry, she's a really good person.
I'm sure you'll like her.
It's no problem if you join us.
So what's your final answer?
Will you come with me, or not?
Okay, fine. Let's go together.
- After I finish smoking.
- In the meantime, I'll pay the bill.
- No need to, let me do it!
- It's okay.
Up until that point,
everything went smoothly...
- This is the place.
- Great.
How is it called?
"Poet and Peasant"? Oh...
- Director.
- Yes.
When's the special lecture?
I want to go if I have time.
It's really not a big deal...
The movie screening is at one o'clock.
At three o'clock I'll deliver the presentation.
Something like that.
I never heard you speaking in person,
so I really want to come.
I won't have much to say,
I'm not too good with words.
He actually speaks really well, earlier at
the atelier his words were really nice.
- What words?
- Never mind.
- He talked about my painting.
- Come on now...
I never heard those words before,
today was the first time.
- She's just exaggerating.
- You got me curious now!
Please tell us what did you say to her.
I just told her what I felt
while looking at her painting.
Miss Hee-jung took this path
without knowing where she’s headed,
but precisely because of that,
she’s bound to discover more and more.
However, if you're not meant for this,
it's a very difficult path to follow.
A lot of sensitivity
and courage is needed...
...in order to walk on
this path until the end.
Are you walking
on this path, Hee-jung?
That's one way of seeing things.
Those words really gave me
a lot of strength.
Excuse me, but...
When you speak about your films,
you seem to give the same description?!
- Me?
- Yes.
The same description that you gave just now,
appears in one of your interviews that I read.
- Are you sure?
- Yes!
Is that right, Director?
Did I?
I'm not saying that just for the sake of it,
but it appears you always speak that way.
Director, an acquaintance of mine told me
that you're quite skilled with women.
Is it true that you're a womanizer?
- Did you really hear such thing?
- Yes.
Apparently, you were involved
with an actress in one occasion...
And word has it, you also had a serious
relationship with a member from your film crew.
- My memory never lets me down.
- I see.
It's not a big deal,
you just hear things.
The things that you hear
are no more than just that.
There is nothing to
comment on that subject.
It's just rumors.
Just rumors, most likely.
Besides, men and women are
supposed to like each other.
If they don't like each other,
who else will like them?
Professor, I agree with you.
- But... Aren't you married?
- What? Who, me?
Yes you, Director.
Oh well...
Of course I'm married!
Really? I see. The things that
I heard turned out to be true.
But I'm amazed by how many
things you heard about me.
I have a wide circle of acquaintances.
It's also because you're quite famous.
So I get to hear things.
But, you got married
a long time ago, right?
Yes, it's been a while.
I got married at the age of 23.
I was very young.
- Wow, so early.
- Director, why did you get married so early?
Oh, that? Jeez...
I can't believe
we're talking about this.
Back then,
my condition was not good.
I was ruined on the inside.
That's when...
That's when I met her. She was the
exact opposite of how I used to be.
She was truly a good person.
So I decided to live my life with her,
in order to become a decent human being.
I see.
It's a good thing to
get married early.
When their heads are not
crammed with many thoughts,
...two people trying to
accomplish something together.
Isn't that why we get married, after all?
- You got married early too, right?
- Yes, pretty early.
Soo-young, I have to rest,
I've been drinking too much.
Sure. You want me to
bring you something warm?
It's okay. I'll come back
after I rest for a while.
- Excuse me.
- Yes.
She always takes a nap after drinking.
Oh, really?
But she sobers up really quick!
After a quick rest,
she'll be as fresh as a daisy.
She looks even better
when she's drunk.
She's very pretty.
- She is.
- Right?
Right...
- Please drink some more.
- What?
- Shall we toast?
- Yes.
- I'm a big fan, Director.
- Let's toast.
- Cheers!
Thank you.
I drank too much,
it's not okay.
Your alcohol tolerance is pretty high.
I never got drunk once in my life.
- And yet, he's drunk.
- That's not true. I'm not drunk.
- Please don't worry.
- OK.
Are you sleeping?
No.
What's wrong?
Are you tired?
Just go.
You shouldn't have come.
- Should I go?
- Yes.
You want me to go?
You do?
Director, why are you
doing this to me?
Tell me.
Is it because of
what I said earlier?
Is it?
I'm sorry.
I'll leave.
Why did you come out?
Soo-young called me,
she said you left her place.
Who did you meet today?
Various people.
I met Soo-young...
And some others.
I heard you met a movie director.
Who's that director?
You don't know him, mom, he's an
arthouse film director...You don't know him.
Really?
But why did you drink so much, again?
Are you crazy? You're
getting drunk on a daily basis!
- Let's go inside, and get some sleep.
- Stop drinking so much.
Suwon Hwaseong Museum
(use the side door
during the event)
The weather is very cold, so we'd like
to thank everyone who gathered here today.
Everyone will work even harder for the
next year's edition of this film festival.
That's our a solemn promise.
Before wrapping up, I'd like to ask the
director the last and most important question.
Director, I will ask you
a short question,
and I expect your answer
to be equally short.
Director, what is film to you?
From all the experiences that you gathered
as a director, your affection for film...
What is it that defines film for you?
If you can answer in short,
it would be greatly appreciated.
- In short?
- Yes.
I started without knowing anything.
By doing so, I started to
discover other types of things...
A lot of sounds are
running through my head right now,
And if I utter those sounds,
they become words.
But...
At the end of the day,
words will remain just words.
The films, myself,
my experiences, your lives...
All of these things have
nothing to do with words!
The power of words?
What a joke.
Why do people keep searching for those
words as if they were something special?
For me...
There's no such thing as
important words.
On the contrary!
They're just a hindrance.
If you would have just asked casually,
it would've been much better.
- It's difficult.
- Is it?
What was your name, again?
Yes.
Oh, yes...
I'm Seong-guk. Oh...
Ahn Seong...Guk?!
Mr. Ahn Seong Guk.
I'll get up first.
Thank you all for coming to watch
my film. Be careful on your way home.
Thank you.
Looks like the director is leaving...
Director Ham Chun-soo is leaving now.
Director.
- Hello.
- You came?
- I didn't see you inside.
- I came in late, I'm sorry.
I drank too much, so I couldn't
wake up on time. I'm very sorry.
Don't worry, I haven't sobered up
yet, either. I'm just like yesterday.
I shouldn't have drank so much.
Today was a mess.
Why did it turn out so badly?
Oh, the host of the event... He's so
shameless, he only cares about himself.
He's so ignorant.
So embarrassing.
How could someone like him
even become a film critic?
So embarrassing.
- Did you hear everything?
- No, I came in very late.
Oh, I see.
I...
I hope you'll read
this book when you have time.
Thank you!
- You are the author?
- Yes.
Discovering the hidden things
laying at the surface of our lives,
Walking on that path
as a method to overcome our fears...
I concur with that thought.
Thank you very much!
I can't wait to read it.
Yes.
Well then, I'll take my leave now.
- Goodbye.
- You're going?
- Yes. Goodbye.
- Goodbye.
Thank you for the book!
Director!
Team leader Ahn is looking for you.
- Really?
- Yes, he's been asking about you, here and there.
- Will you go back inside, now?
- I'll smoke a cigarette, first.
Yesterday I should have called you.
I'm sorry, I was too tired.
It's okay. Did you rest well?
Yes...
- Can I smoke, too?
- Sure, go ahead.
Must have been difficult for you, earlier.
Yes, a little. Me and that
fellow are like oil and water.
How can a person be so shameless?
He is so shameless,
so ignorant...
How could someone like him
even become a film critic?
So shameless, so ignorant...
A lump of a snob!
And I bet he still
thinks highly of himself.
Ridiculous.
You two don't seem to
harmonize well with each other.
Does that mean you're not going back in?
Yeah, I'll just leave.
Miss Bora, you're a good person.
Too bad we didn't get to speak much.
I'd really like to talk to you some more,
can we meet again once we're back in Seoul?
Sure, let's do that.
Every day and every moment,
try to discover new things!
Thanks to all the things in this world,
I believe you can overcome everything...
...including your fears.
- Director...
- Yes?
- Okay. Take care.
- Yes.
Director, you're really cool.
Really?
Thanks.
I'm really going now.
Take care.
- Have a safe trip back to Seoul.
- Yes, I will.
- Goodbye!
- See ya.
II. RIGHT NOW, WRONG THEN
- How much?
- 1500 Won.
- Wow, it's great in here.
- Shall we take a picture?
A bit more to your right.
One, two, three...
Is it tasty?
Yes, it is.
It's Banana Milk.
What are you doing here?
What does it look like I'm doing?
You're drinking some milk.
Great observation.
How about you,
what are you doing?
Well, I'm just sitting here.
I've come to Suwon for a movie screening.
I also have to give an oral presentation.
Will you deliver a lecture?
After the screening of my film,
I will be speaking with the audience.
It's not really a lecture.
I don't have much to say, anyway.
- Are you a film director?
- Yes, I am.
- I see.
- What do you do?
I'm not doing anything.
- I'm just drinking some milk.
- I see. You're not doing anything.
So, are you a famous director?
Maybe someone I know?
My name is Ham Chun-soo.
- Seriously? Is that true?
- Yes.
I know you very well!
You are a very famous director!
I'm flattered.
- But...are you really the director Ham Chun-soo?
- Of course.
Really?
Now I see!
That's why you seemed familiar!
Is that so?
- Nice to meet you!
- Nice to meet you, too!
I hope I didn't bother you,
maybe you wanted to be alone.
I'm the one who should say that. You were
trying to sleep, but then I showed up and...
- I'm very sorry.
- Don't worry about that.
Please, sit down.
It's the place that I treasure
the most, that's why I came here.
I see.
It's the most beautiful place.
Really?
- So what is your occupation?
- Me?
Well...
You could say I'm a painter.
I've not been painting for too long,
but these days I'm only
living my life while painting.
You even have traces of paint on your jacket!
Yes.
You're beautiful.
Thanks...
I used to have a different occupation.
But now I only live my life while painting.
Perhaps...
Would you like to drink
a cup of coffee with me?
A warm coffee. Somewhere nearby.
- Coffee?
- Yes. It's cold, so...
I think it would be great.
I'm quite embarrassed to ask you this.
- Coffee?
- To be honest...
I think I've seen you, earlier.
- When you entered, I've seen you briefly.
- Really? Where?
Right there.
So can I buy you a coffee?
A warm coffee.
Let's go for a coffee!
In that case, it would be an honor,
drinking coffee with such a great director.
Thank you!
- Let's stand up, shall we?
- Yes.
- I'll carry this for you.
- Thank you.
Why are you looking inside?
It looks tasty.
You never drink coffee?
I used to, but not anymore.
I became too sensitive.
You really seem like a sensitive person.
- But I really like the fragrance.
- You can drink just a little, if you want.
No, thanks.
Please enjoy it yourself.
Okay.
A long time ago, I used to drink
a lot of alcohol and smoke a lot, too.
When did you quit
smoking and drinking?
A few years ago.
I used to drink and smoke a lot...
But then I realized it's not
how I want to live my life.
So I changed my ways,
which wasn't easy.
Wow, good for you!
What are you doing today?
- I'll have to drop by the atelier.
- Really? Where is it?
- It's near the Haenggung Palace.
- I see.
It'd be great if you can
show me your paintings.
Aren't you busy?
Well, I arrived a day early, like an idiot.
So today I have nothing to do.
Why did you come early?
The people there didn't contact me.
The date was changed, and apparently they
tried to call me, but I missed their calls.
- So what will you do now?
- They rented me a room.
You know my hostel, right?
They rented me a room there.
I see.
Miss Hee-jung, where do you live?
- You live nearby?
- If you walk up the hill, it's right up there.
- Do you live with someone?
- With my mom.
So you don't live with your father.
He got divorced,
and now he's living in Seoul.
- So you're living with your mother.
- Yes.
Do you meet with your father,
from time to time?
You don't?
Why do you keep asking me
this sort of questions?
I apologize.
I was just curious.
You must be asking
out of sheer boredom.
No, I'm not bored at all.
I'm not the type of
person who gets bored.
Me, neither.
Really?
I keep hearing everyone saying how bored
they are, but I'll never understand why.
I know.
Why would you be bored,
with so many things to do?
I agree.
I don't have time to get bored.
I paint every day, I take care of the
household chores, I also have to study.
Besides, I go out for a walk,
one hour every day.
There's no time to get bored.
That's great.
Now I'm really curious about
what type of paintings you make.
I'll show you my paintings,
if you're truly interested.
Yes, I really am!
Really?
Yes.
I always liked painting,
ever since I was little.
No one encouraged me to start painting,
But once I had white paper
and painting supplies...
...my heart would always start racing.
I know. Once I have paper and pencil,
When I desire to write something,
I feel better for no apparent reason.
- You get the same feeling?
- Yes.
That's amazing.
Yes.
We are alike.
Miss Hee-jung, you seem
like a beautiful person.
You strike me as a
very honest man, Director.
But I'm not beautiful at all.
I'm not beautiful.
You are.
It seems that
you don't know yourself.
Stop teasing me, Director.
I'm not teasing you.
What are you thinking about?
Me? I was thinking about you.
About the painting, as well.
It's the first time when I try this.
- It doesn't feel like it.
- Really?
Yes, on the contrary.
You definitely have skills.
Really? I don't think so.
I still have a long way to go.
It's nice, it really is.
The quality is undeniable.
But it feels as if... As if you're
taking solace into this painting.
A painting made to
conceal your feelings.
- You think so?
- Yes.
Something that makes you feel at ease,
something that provides some consolation...
That's the type of painting
you're creating here.
You should express yourself
more bravely, but...
But now you're going through
a hard time, you're lonely...
That's why you reached a dead end.
Now you're hoping to erase it all,
...so you took solace in painting.
You're reading too much into it.
You're really something...
A sentiment of self-pity, that's
the feeling I get from this painting.
But that's not a bad thing.
You have to regain
control of your emotions, first.
There's quality to it, I mean it.
The quality is there, but...
What exactly are you looking at,
in order to feel all these things?
...but it feels a little
bit too conventional.
Being conventional is comfortable.
When you're looking for solace, it's only
natural to find it in conventional things.
Even so, there's quality to it.
But perhaps...
Perhaps slightly too conventional.
You have to express yourself more boldly.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Mhm.
Is that so?
I don't think I'm painting
just to find consolation...
In that case, I'd better
find a man to sleep with.
Oh, if... If you do that,
it would be even better!
First you get consolation out of the way,
and you can focus on painting afterwards.
If you keep thinking about painting over
and over and over, you might go crazy.
You need to ease your mind, first.
You need a touch of love in your heart.
That's a very important thing.
A hundred, a thousand
times more important!
You shouldn't have bothered
coming all the way here.
This painting is not
worth your effort...
It's not like that,
please don't take it the wrong way.
I just wanted to be honest with you
in my own way, so don't think like that.
How do you know
what I'm thinking?
That's right,
so please don't get mad.
When did I get mad?
Was it really necessary
to speak to me that way?
I'm sorry.
- Can I smoke?
- No.
Smoking is prohibited in here.
If you smoke,
I'll end up paying a fine.
I see.
In that case, I'll smoke
outside, I'll be right back.
How can you speak so bluntly
about other people's works?
You directors are all like that?
Sure...
Great view!
Really nice!
You can see everything from here.
Miss Hee-jung, can you
see your house from here?
Halfway up that mountain...
Yes, I can see it.
Do you see that big
Buddha statue over there?
Right below the statue, can you
spot a small portion of a big house?
Well, I see the statue, but
I'm not sure about your house.
Miss Hee-jung, are you rich?
No, I only have the house.
I don't have money.
A robber broke into my house, once.
A robber?
Yes, a few years back,
a robber broke inside the house.
But he didn't steal anything,
and just left.
Really?
He only left his footprints.
Why would he do that?
That Buddha statue brings good luck.
I used to hate that statue before.
Having such a large statue
right behind the house...
But one day,
Strangely enough, that big statue
started to make me feel more at peace.
As if it was protecting me.
You're cute.
Do you always speak out
so bluntly, Director?
Why?
You really are cute.
It's cold. Let's go.
- You sure drink a lot.
- Yes, that's true.
- I'm sorry.
- Don't worry.
If you want to drink, go ahead.
If it makes you feel good, why not.
Yes...
It's very good.
- Should I pour you some more?
- Yes.
Miss Hee-jung,
you should drink some, too.
Yes, you go ahead and
drink, I'll drink too.
- Okay, let's drink.
- Yes, let's do this.
You drink really fast!
Your drinking skills are no joke.
It's the first time when I see
someone drinking like this.
You must be a real man!
It's the first time for me, too.
With such a beautiful lady...
It's the first time.
Really?
Are you sure you're not saying
this to all the women you meet?
You're not a casanova? I heard that
all film directors are womanizers.
Really?
I'm not sure if I'm a casanova.
Do I look lonely?
That's what you said earlier
while looking at my painting.
I felt you're lonely from the first moment I
saw you, even before looking at your painting.
But...you are very beautiful.
How did you know I'm lonely?
I didn't know, I just...
I just felt that way.
At the atelier, I shouldn't
have talked so much, right?
Don't worry.
The truth is, I...
I have no friends.
No?
I don't know why.
I can't make friends.
It's probably my fault.
You seem like you've always
been this type of person.
But do you at least
meet with people?
Yes, because it's a necessity.
It's okay, then.
Why do you give me that look?
It feels strange.
I have fallen in love, that's why.
I really want to get married.
Really?
Yes.
You're really peculiar.
However...
I won't be able to.
What?
I'm already married.
I have two kids.
Oh...
But even so...
Even so, I love you.
Since the moment we talked
at the coffeeshop earlier,
I have fallen in love with you.
You did?
Yes, that's what...
That's how I feel.
After I...
Tomorrow after I go back to Seoul,
I won't be able to see you again.
We have to love the ones
that are dear to us, right?
You must feel relieved now, after
being honest about your feelings.
I'm a bit disappointed, though.
Really?
You're a bit disappointed?
What are you so happy about?
You just said it won't work out.
You're a bit disappointed, so...
Now that you told me you're
a bit disappointed, I feel better.
I feel better now.
If we would've met a long time ago,
it would've been much better.
When you were younger, I bet you
were even more handsome than now.
All the girls were
crazy about you, right?
I don't know.
I got married too early.
So you got married early...
Miss Hee-jung...
You are very beautiful.
So beautiful, that I...
I love you.
Oh...
I...
I'd like you to wear this,
at least once.
What is this?
I picked it up off the street.
Wanna try it?
I can't believe it,
it fits perfectly.
Did you really pick
it up off the street?
It looks intact.
It's beautiful!
You can have it.
It's not expensive, anyway.
This is our wedding ring.
Oh, that's right!
It's our wedding ring.
We got married!
We're married!
- We got married!
- No we didn't.
Director, you're cute.
Thank you for the ring.
Don't mention it.
I'm the one who's grateful.
Thank you for letting me
experience these strong emotions.
I will...
I will cherish these feelings
for the rest of my life.
Shall we have a drink?
Please pour me some.
Yes. Let's drink.
- It's delicious.
- Yes, I like it, too.
I'll go out for a smoke.
Wanna join me? Oh...
That's right, you quit smoking.
- I'll go by myself.
- Okay.
What are you doing?
Why did you come out?
It's cold.
I have to go somewhere,
I totally forgot, I'm sorry.
You're going somewhere?
Yes, I have to go to a
friend's party, I totally forgot.
Do you want to come with me?
It's a place where you can go, too.
Where are we going?
It's her birthday, or something?
No, she runs a café and we decided to meet this
evening, the two of us and a few other people.
I really have to be there.
What should we do?
That's a good question.
Do you want to come with me?
If not, should we part ways?
- No, no...
- You can come, she's a really good person.
But I'm not one of her friends.
It doesn't matter, she's very
kind, I'm sure she'll like you.
You can come if you want.
Okay, fine.
Let's go together.
- After I finish smoking.
- In the meantime, I'll pay the bill.
- No need to, let me do it!
- It's okay.
I'm the one who should pay the bill...
I'm so happy to have
met you like this, Director.
I'm even happier.
Whenever you release a new film, I watch
it on the first day, at the first screening.
- So please treat me beautifully.
- You are very beautiful, already.
Director, usually she's not like this,
but because she has fallen under your spell...
Really?
Director, you seem
like a very good man.
I'm a huge fan!
- You're the best, enough said!
- I don't deserve so much praise.
You're by far the best of them all!
- No one else can come near you.
- We understand, we got it.
- Director.
- Yes.
- I think I like you, too.
- You do?
You seem different than how
the rumors describe you to be.
What?
You're more innocent than I expected.
When you arrived with Hee-jung earlier,
I almost got the wrong impression.
But you're more virtuous than I thought.
You're a good man.
Thank you very much.
Thank you both.
- Let's toast!
- Okay.
Cheers!
But I think I drank too much...
When you're in a good mood,
the alcohol goes down smoothly.
I shouldn't have drank so much...
Oh my!
- What's wrong?
- Director...
Director, are you all right?
What is happening to him?
Director?
- Is he all right?
- I don't know.
Director...
What should we do?
Director, are you feeling well?
Director...
What now?
Director?
Get up, try to get up!
Oh, I'm...
I'm just...
Don't worry, I'm just acting.
What's the meaning of this?
Well, I...
Sometimes, I...
I act!
When I'm bored.
Out of boredom.
You gave us a big scare!
Startled, weren't you?
You really scared us.
Why did you do that?
I'm okay, seriously.
Goodness!
You sure know how to act.
I was just acting, just acting.
I'm quite good at it.
- You sure you're all right?
- Of course I am.
I'm okay.
What a scare.
You really scared us.
What can I say, I love acting.
- He's drunk.
- He's wasted.
Director...
Yes.
Oh dear...
Oh dear!
- What is this?
- Director, what are you doing?
- My goodness!
- What should we do?
What has gotten into this person?
- Director, what do you think you're doing?
- What?
Why are you doing this to us?
He's crazy!
- Director.
- Yes.
We have to do something.
What's wrong with you?
Director, please control yourself!
- You're sleeping?
- No.
- Are you tired?
- No, I'm fine.
- How about you?
- I get ready to go.
You're leaving?
I have to go,
I'm suffocating in here.
I want to go out
for some fresh air.
Will you come with me?
Fresh air?
It's too cold outside.
It's okay. If you're cold,
I'll hold you tightly.
Let's go somewhere nice,
and have some fresh air.
If we leave together at this hour,
my friends might get the wrong idea.
That's true.
They might get the wrong idea.
Should I just tell them
that you're taking me home?
They trust you,
so I think it will be okay.
You go and tell them that, then.
What's the big deal, anyway?
We're just living our
lives the best we can.
What more can we ask for.
Should we go out, Director?
Let's go.
Come on.
Okay.
Let them think what they want.
That's right.
Great!
You're leaving?
Yes, we're about to go.
Professor, I had a great time.
- Professor, it was an honor.
- The honor was all mine, Director.
- I hope to see you again.
- Yes, I'm sure we'll meet again.
- Goodbye, Professor!
- Goodbye.
- Please take her home safely.
- I will!
We'll have some fresh air,
then we'll go right home.
Okay, but please be careful, it's cold.
I hope you'll forgive me for
the mistake that I made today.
- Goodbye!
- Be extra careful.
You are two precious human beings.
- Take care, Professor!
- You too, Hee-jung.
- It's cold!
- It's okay.
Good night!
Should we go to Kangwon Province?
Where in Kangwon?
At the Gyeongpo Beach, maybe.
Shall we?
Yes.
How expensive is the taxi fare?
Pretty expensive, right?
I don't know,
maybe around 100.000 Won?
I'm not sure, I've
never been there by taxi.
- Around 100.000 Won?
- Yes.
Hop in!
Do we take it from here,
or from the other side?
Oh, well...
I'm not sure.
Let's go towards the market square,
there's a taxi rank there.
Yes, okay, let's do that.
Mom! I'm almost home,
go to sleep.
Who are you with?
What? I'm alone,
I'm on my way home.
Soo-young told me you
left with a film director.
But why did you leave
without telling her a word?
She was worried you were
kidnapped by that lunatic.
Really?
But why do you call him
a lunatic, all of a sudden?
You should choose your
words more carefully.
That director is crazy!
Why would he get naked
in front of two women?
When did he get naked?
You're clueless.
He even took off his underwear,
in front of Soo-young. You dummy!
- You didn't see anything?
- No, I had no idea.
But why would he do that?
How should I know?
He's crazy, why else.
- He really did that?
- I just told you!
What kind of nutcase
are you hanging around with?
Hanging around?
I just met him, by chance. By chance!
- Anyway, are you really alone?
- Of course I am.
Just calm down already.
I'm coming home right now.
I'm in front of the Haenggung Palace,
I'll be home soon.
- Come home quicky!
- I will.
Did you strip in front of my friends?
Yes...
It was too hot.
That's why I did that.
Besides, I was drunk, and...
Something must have bothered me,
I was feeling stuffy.
- I'm sorry for that, Hee-jung.
- So it was true?
Yes, I...
How could I miss this?
No, please don't say that.
It's great that you weren't there.
You really are peculiar.
I don't know why I did that, either.
I just... felt the need to do it.
I wonder why?
I'm sorry your friends
had to see me like that...
- Hee-jung!
- Hi!
But what if they'll
file a complaint against me?
Soo-young is fully
capable of doing just that.
- Seriously?
- You bet.
I sure hope not.
But...
I'll talk to her.
Don't worry. After I talk to
her, I'm sure she'll understand.
Yes?
That's a relief.
- I shouldn't have drank so much...
- I kept telling you to drink less!
- It's cold.
- You're cold?
I'm cold! Let's go, hurry up.
So cold!
This way. Just a moment, my mom
might come out any minute.
At the end of this road,
that's the house where I live.
Okay.
Are you...
Going home?
Of course, I have to.
We've been in the cold for too long.
Yes...
But...
Can't you come back, later?
I'd like to talk to you some more.
We're freezing, and
we drank so much...
You're freezing, too!
Not at all, I...
I'd really like to
talk to you some more.
If it's possible.
- Are you serious?
- Yes. Can you come out later?
- Okay, I'll go in, then I'll come back.
- Great.
Once I go to my room, my mom will
fall asleep, that's when I'll sneak out.
But how can you wait like this?
Outside, in the cold...
I can. If you come out, I'll wait.
Very well.
I'm going in for now,
then I'll come back.
- It's my mom! I have to go.
- Sure, go.
Next time,
I'll kiss you on the lips.
- Wait for me.
- I'll be waiting.
- Hee-jung. What were you doing there?
- Why did you get out?
Why did you get out?
What were you doing there?
Is someone there?
What are you talking about?
- Then, what were you doing there?
- I was smoking a cigarette.
I didn't know how you would react,
so I stopped there for a smoke.
Really?
Were you really smoking?
It was so difficult for you to
quit smoking, why did you relapse?
I just felt like it,
after drinking.
- Are you tired, Director?
- No, I'm okay.
Just a small hangover.
I'm fine.
Thanks to your hard work, the audience
gained a lot of insight today.
Please, I don't deserve such praise.
No, you explained
everything in great detail,
I was so surprised, I didn't expect
you'll be so considerate to them.
A lot of students showed up,
so it just turned out that way.
But what was up with
that guy wearing glasses?
Tell me about it...
He just couldn't get over himself.
No matter how much he talked,
I still have no idea what his question was.
He was just showing off
in front of the ladies.
- Really?
- Most likely.
- Do you mind if we shake hands?
- Not at all.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
How will you go back to Seoul?
Did you bring your car?
No, I don't own a car.
I'll just take the subway.
In that case, miss Bora
can give you a ride.
Don't worry,
I'll just take a taxi.
It's the least we can do for you.
Miss Bora, do you mind?
Of course not.
I'll give you a ride.
You're too kind.
Thank you!
Excuse me.
- You're here!
- Yes. The lecture went well?
- Yes.
- I'm here to watch your film.
Oh, it's screening right now?
I had to run to arrive on time.
- Are you okay?
- Yes.
It's the first time when
I watch one of your films.
Oh, really?
Thank you!
I'm going back to Seoul, now.
- Really?
- Yes.
Then I'm glad we at least
got to meet here like this.
Yes, me too.
- Will you be all right?
- Yes, don't worry about it.
Are you sure?
- Soo-young said she understands.
- What?
She says she can forgive you,
since you're an artist.
- Really? So she understands...
- Yes.
Thank you for everything.
I'm grateful, too.
I have to go inside.
The movie is about to start.
- Yes, hurry up and go inside.
- Yes. Have a safe trip back to Seoul.
Goodbye.
- Who was that?
- Oh, someone that I know since a while back.
I'm going, now.
- You're going?
- Yes.
Sorry for last night,
I couldn't sneak out.
It's all right, I didn't wait
long anyway, it was very cold.
- Really?
- Yes.
- So you're going to watch this one.
- Yes, it looks interesting.
I hope you like it.
I missed you.
Me too.
Director,
I'll enjoy your film.
From now on,
I'll watch all your films.
Thank you.
I'm the one who's thankful.
I'm so happy that I met you.
Yes, me too.
I'm going, now.
Okay, goodbye.
- Bye!
- Bye.